IN. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE APRIL 7TH, 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN NOT
PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENCE
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MILK OUR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR
SAUTER PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT SUPERVISOR WANG WANG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNSEATED
ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAHMATULLAH SALONI WHO ARE THE
ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THEIR ARMY TO SALONI HAVE NEVER CEDED LOSS
NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMA SOCIAL ONLY COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
PARTICULARLY SUZE ENOS. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE AND. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE OFFICE OF THE CLERK OF THE BOARD IS IN RECEIPT OF A MEMO
DATED APRIL 7TH, 2026 FROM SUPERVISOR FIELDER REQUESTING
TO BE EXCUSED FROM THE MEETINGS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE AS WELL
AS THE LIFE CO MEETINGS BETWEEN APRIL 7TH AND JUNE 30TH.
AND FOR TODAY'S PURPOSES A MOTION WILL NEED TO BE MADE
IN ORDER FOR HER TO EXCUSE HER FROM TODAY'S MEETING AS WELL AS
FOR FUTURE MEETINGS OF THE BOARD AND THE GAO.
>> ADDITIONALLY, THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
WELCOMES YOU ALL TO BE PRESENT IN THE LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER.
HERE WE ARE IN ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND FLOOR OF CITY HALL
AND WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE HERE WE ASK THAT YOU WATCH THE
PROCEEDINGS THAT ARE AIRING LIVE ON S.F. GOP TV'S CHANNEL
26 OR CATCH THE LIVE STREAM AT W W W DOT S F G OR VTV DOT ORG.
IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT THAT YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT IN WRITING
JUST SEND IT TO THE THROUGH THE US POSTAL SERVICE TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA
94102. AND IF YOU'D LIKE TO SEND IT
VIA EMAIL YOU CAN SEND IT TO EMAIL ADDRESS AT BOX AT S.F.
GOV.ORG IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A
FUTURE MEETING. UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH
DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE
CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS
IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
THANK YOU MEMBERS. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, COULD I HAVE A
MOTION TO EXCUSE SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM TODAY'S MEETING
MADE BY SUPERVISOR MAHMUD. SECONDED BY WALTON.
AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
WITHOUT OBJECTION. SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS EXCUSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING
MINUTES. YES.
APPROVAL OF THE FEBRUARY 24TH, 2026 AND MARCH 3RD 2026 BOARD
MEETING MINUTES. CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN SECONDED BY CHERYL.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED? >> SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
MANDAL MEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR
I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED AND I WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT WE WERE
JOINED HERE IN THE CHAMBER BY A FORMER MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS BEVIN DUFTY. WELCOME TO SUPERVISOR DUFTY ALL
RIGHT MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA PLEASE CALL
ITEMS ONE THROUGH NINE TOGETHER ITEMS ONE THROUGH NINE.
THESE ITEMS ARE ON CONSENT AND CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE.
IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED
SEPARATELY PLEASE CALL THE ROLL MADAM CLERK ON ITEMS ONE
THROUGH NINE SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MADELEINE I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUDER SORTER I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR ONE WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EITHER ARE CHINESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED
BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM TEN. >> ITEM TEN THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE THAT AMENDS THE HEALTH BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATION AS THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE REGARDING COMPACT MOBILE
FOOD OPERATION DEFINITION AND FEES.
COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 11 ITEM 11 THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 34.36 MILLION
FROM PERMANENT PREMIUM AND COMP TIME SALARIES AND TO
APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY THAT SAME SET AMOUNT TO OVERTIME
SALARIES IN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO SUPPORT THE
DEPARTMENT'S PROJECTED INCREASES IN OVERTIME AS
REQUIRED PER ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTION 3.17 AND FISCAL
YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026. >> AND LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 12 ITEM 12 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO REQUIRE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS
TO PERFORM EVALUATIONS AND REPORT PERIODICALLY ON
MECHANICAL STREET SWEEPING OPERATIONS TO INCLUDE SUBMITTAL
OF WRITTEN PERFORMANCE REPORTS TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND THE MAYOR AND TO AMEND THE HEALTH CODE TO REVISE
AND CLARIFY OUTDATED TERMS CONCERNING REFUSE RECEPTACLE
REQUIREMENTS AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND AGAIN
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED. MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 13 ITEM 13 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE POLICE
SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY FOR ELECTRONIC LOCATION
TRACKING DEVICES AND TO MAKE THE REQUISITE FINDINGS PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 13 SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER
SAUTER I SUPERVISORS CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WILSON NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND ONE
NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS PLEASE
CALL ITEM NUMBER 14 ITEM 14 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
THE THIRD NOT MODIFICATION AND TO A CONTRACT WITH HALLMARK
AVIATION SERVICES LP FOR AIRPORT INFORMATION AND GUEST
ASSISTANCE SERVICES TO EXTEND THE TERM FOR ONE YEAR FOR A
TOTAL TERM OF JULY 1ST 2024 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 AND TO
INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY 10.4 MILLION FOR A NEW CONTRACT
AMOUNT OF 30.4 MILLION PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 14
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT. >> MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SUTTER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 15 AND 16 TOGETHER ITEMS
15 AND 16 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT APPROVE AGREEMENTS
AGREEMENT AMENDMENTS FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH.
ITEM 15 APPROVES THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT
BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO AIDS
FOUNDATION TO OPERATE A HEALTH ACCESS POINT AND PROVIDE
CAPACITY BUILDING SERVICES A FOUR YEAR TERM EXTENSION NOW
THROUGH JANUARY 1ST, 2023 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030 AND TO
INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY 11.9 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 21.8
MILLION AND ITEM 16 THIS APPROVES THE SECOND AMENDMENT
TO THE AGREEMENT WITH THE RAFIKI COALITION FOR HEALTH
AND WELLNESS TO PROVIDE HEALTH ACCESS POINT SERVICES A THREE
YEAR TERM EXTENSION NOW JANUARY 21ST JANUARY FIRST, 2023
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030 AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY
APPROXIMATELY 10.6 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 20
MILLION. >> I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE
ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
17 ITEM 17 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE OFFICE OF THE
ASSESSOR RECORDER TO EXECUTE THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO A
CONTRACT WITH SAPIENT CORPORATION FOR THE
IMPLEMENTATION AND MAINTENANCE OF THE PROPERTY ASSESSMENT
SYSTEM REPLACEMENT PROJECT TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY
6.7 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 33.9 MILLION AND TO
EXTEND THE CONTRACT DURATION FROM NINE YEARS AND TWO MONTHS
TO 13 YEARS AND EIGHT MONTHS FOR A TOTAL TERM THROUGH JUNE
30TH 2032. >> CHAIR JAN, THANK YOU PRESENT
AMENDMENT COLLEAGUES AND THIS ITEM CAME OUT OF THE BUDGET
WITH A RECOMMENDATION EVEN THOUGH THE PROJECT ITSELF BY
ITS IMPLEMENTATION HAS ALMOST A FIVE YEARS DELIGHT.
THE REASON BEING THAT WE END UP VOTING IN SUPPORT OF THIS
AND MOVING OUT TO FOR YOUR VOTE TODAY IS BECAUSE THE CONTRACTOR
HAS YIELDED AROUND ABOUT $15 MILLION WORTH OF STAFFING
SPENDING AND TO TO REIMBURSE TO THE CITY WHAT WE REALLY ASKED
FOR DURING THE COMMITTEE THOUGH IS FOR US TO UNDERSTAND THE
SPECIFIC AND DETAILS OF THAT $15 MILLION OF STAFFING WORK,
WHETHER THAT WE CAN INDEPENDENTLY VERIFY THAT
DOLLAR AMOUNT THAT RESULTED IN THE TYPE OF STAFFING WE HAVE
YET TO RECEIVE THAT INFORMATION.
I THINK THAT THEY JUST NEED A LITTLE BIT MORE TIME.
THE ASSESSOR RECORDER HAS AGREED FOR US TO CONTINUE WITH
THIS FOR A WEEK. IT WILL NOT IMPACT THEIR
CONTRACT AMENDMENT. SO I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE TO
CONTINUE TO DO FOR US TO VOTE ON THIS TO NEXT WEEK SO WE CAN
HAVE ALL THE INFORMATION ON THE RECORD BEFORE WE CAST OUR VOTE.
>> THANK THANK YOU CHAIR JAN FOR YOUR MOTION AND YOUR WORK
ON THIS SECONDED BY WALTON COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THAT WOULD BE CONTINUED TO APRIL 14TH.
>> GREAT. AND WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. >> THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL 18 ITEM 18 HIGH TO MAINTAIN IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE
AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE DEPARTMENT
OF PUBLIC HEALTH WITH INSTITUTO FAMILIA DE LA RAZA INC TO
OPERATE A HEALTH ACCESS POINT SERVICE TO EXTEND THE TERM BY
THREE YEARS FROM JUNE 30TH 2027 FOR A NEW TERM OF JANUARY 1ST
2023 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030 AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY
APPROXIMATELY 9.2 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 17 MILLION.
>> AND LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 19.
>> ITEM 19. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
RETROACTIVELY APPROVE A CONTRACT BETWEEN THE CITY
AND COUNTY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO MARIN FOOD BANK FOR
THE PROVISION OF THE CAL FRESH STOP GAP EMERGENCY GIFT CARD
INITIATIVE FOR A TWO MONTH TERM OCTOBER 30TH 2025 THROUGH
DECEMBER 31ST 2025 AND THEN NOT TO EXCEED AMOUNT OF 9.1 MILLION
AND TO RETROACTIVE APPROVE THE FIRST AMENDMENT ADDING
REPAYMENT INSTRUCTIONS AS WELL AS REVISED REPAYMENT
AND REPORTING EFFECTIVE JANUARY 30TH 2026 AND WILL TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
20 AND 21 TOGETHER. >> ITEMS 20 AND 21 ARE TO
RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN TO THE WISTERIA LANE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PROJECT ITEM 20 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
AND AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PROPERTY AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO ENTER INTO A
GROUND LEASE FOR REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY AND LOCATED
AT 105 WISTERIA LANE KNOWN AS THE BALBOA RESERVOIR BUILDING A
WITH BALBOA GATEWAY LP FOR A 75 YEAR TERM FOR THE LEASE AND 124
YEAR OPTION TO EXTEND WITH AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF 15,000
IN ORDER TO CONSTRUCT A 100% AFFORDABLE 158 UNIT MULTI
FAMILY RENTAL HOUSING DEVELOPMENT AFFORDABLE TO VERY
LOW AND LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS PLUS ONE MANAGER'S UNIT TO
APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE AS AN AMENDED AND RESTATED LOAN
AGREEMENT FOR 29.3 MILLION FOR A MINIMUM LOAN TERM OF 57 YEARS
TO FINANCE THE DEVELOPMENT AND CONSTRUCTION OF THE PROJECT
AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MR. RESOLUTIONS MR. PRESIDENT AND I WILL JUST 21
YES, MY APOLOGIES MEMBERS ITEM 21 THIS RESOLUTION IS TO
APPROVE FOR PURPOSES OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE OF 1986
AS AMENDED AND AUTHORIZED THE EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF A
MULTIFAMILY HOUSING REVENUE NOTE IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL
AMOUNT OF 112 MILLION TO FINANCE THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE
105 WISTERIA LANE AND NOW WE CAN TAKE THESE TO RESOLUTIONS
TOGETHER SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
22. ITEM 22 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
THAT APPROVES THE AIRPORT SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY
GOVERNING THE USE OF THE TRANSPORTATION NETWORK COMPANY
VIRTUAL QUEUE TECHNOLOGY THE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 23 ITEM 23 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR AND THE DEPUTY
DIRECTOR OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF VICTIMS RIGHTS TO SOLICIT
DONATIONS TO BENEFIT SURVIVORS VICTIMS OF CRIME FROM
INDIVIDUALS, NONPROFITS, PRIVATE ORGANIZATIONS
AND FOUNDATIONS FOR SIX MONTHS NOTWITHSTANDING THE BE HOSTED
PAYMENT ORDINANCE SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 24 ITEM 24 A
RESOLUTION TO URGE THE MAYOR TO ISSUE AN EXECUTIVE DIRECTIVE TO
ESTABLISH A CITYWIDE WOMEN'S ADVANCED MENT AND GENDER EQUITY
ACTION PLAN LED AND COORDINATED BY THE SAN FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT
ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN WITH FULL CROSS DEPARTMENTS, FULL
PARTICIPATION AND DEDICATED BUDGETARY SUPPORT TO ENSURE
EFFECTIVE IMPLEMENTATION. >> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 25 ITEM 25 RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE ADOPTION OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
SERVICES ACT ANNUAL UPDATE FOR FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 26. >> ITEM 26 THIS IS A MOTION TO
APPROVE THE MAYORAL REAPPOINTMENT OF ANNA VAN DIGNA
TO THE REDEVELOPMENT SUCCESSOR AGENCY OVERSIGHT BOARD FOR TERM
ENDING JANUARY 24TH, 2030 AND WILL TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
IS APPROVED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS
27 AND 28 TOGETHER. >> ITEMS 27 AND 28 ARE TWO
MOTIONS THAT APPROVE THE MAYOR'S NOMINATION FOR THE
APPOINTMENT TO THE TREASURE ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY
BOARD OF DIRECTORS. ITEM 27 APPROVES ERIC DOES
MULKEY TERM ENDING FEBRUARY 26TH 2030 AND ITEM 28 APPROVES
TIMOTHY KOJO MINTA TERM ENDING APRIL 28TH 2030.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTIONS
ARE APPROVED MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 29 AND 30
TOGETHER ITEMS 29 AND 30 ARE TWO MOTIONS THAT APPROVE THE
MAYOR'S NOMINATION FOR THE REAPPOINTMENT TO THE MUNICIPAL
TRANSPORTATION AGENCY'S BOARD OF DIRECTORS.
ITEM 29 APPROVES DOMINICA HENDERSON AND ITEM 30 APPROVE
STEPHANIE HINA FOR A TERM ENDING MARCH 1ST 2030.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTIONS
ARE APPROVED. >> AND THEN MADAM CLERK, I
THINK WE HAVE COMMITTEE REPORTS.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 30 FIVE.
>> ITEM 35 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY APRIL 6TH.
IT WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
ITEM 35 IS AN ORDINANCE THAT AMENDS THE ENVIRONMENT CODE TO
UPDATE THE CITY'S CLIMATE ACTION GOALS AND PLANNING
PROCESS AND TO UPDATE CITY DEPARTMENTS ROLES
AND RESPONSIBILITIES PERTAINING TO THE CITY'S CLIMATE ACTION
GOALS AND TO AFFIRM THE SEQUEL DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
AT NUMBER 36. >> ITEM 36 WAS CONSIDERED BY
THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY APRIL
6TH, 2026 AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED WITH A NEW TITLE TO
APPROVE THE APPOINTMENT ITEM 36.
IT NOW READS THE WORD REJECTING WAS STRUCK AND CURRENTLY READS.
>> MOTION TO APPROVE THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS RAFAEL MANDEL MEANS NOMINATION FOR THE APPOINTMENT
OF LILY WONG TO THE BOARD OF APPEALS FOR A TERM ENDING JULY
1ST, 2028. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
>> FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS MR. PRESIDENT IS YOU.
THANK YOU. I HAVE AN ITEM OF LEGISLATION
ONE AND TWO IN MEMORIAM. SO FIRST I'M INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION TO CLARIFY AND DEFINE WHAT CONSTITUTES
ELECTRICAL WORK UNDER THE SAN FRANCISCO BUILDING CODE AND TO
SPECIFY THAT THIS WORK MUST BE PERFORMED BY PROPERLY CERTIFIED
CONTRACTORS IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE CALIFORNIA LABOR CODE.
THIS CLARITY IS ESPECIALLY IMPORTANT AS SAN FRANCISCO
CONTINUES TO ADVANCE POLICIES AROUND BUILDING ELECTRIFICATION
AND MODERNIZATION AS WE TRANSITION MORE BUILDINGS
AND SYSTEMS TO ELECTRIC POWER, THE VOLUME AND COMPLEXITY OF
ELECTRICAL INSTALLATIONS WILL INCREASE AND HAVING A CLEAR
ENFORCEABLE DEFINITION OF ELECTRICAL WORK WILL BE
HELPFUL. THIS LEGISLATION ALIGNS OUR
DEFINITION OF ELECTRICAL WORK WITH THE REALITIES OF MODERN
CONSTRUCTION. SUPPORTS OUR ELECTRIFICATION
GOALS AND PROVIDES CLARITY FOR CONTRACTORS AND PROPERTY
OWNERS. I WANT TO THANK OUR DEPUTY CITY
ATTORNEY ROB COPPOLA FOR HIS WORK ON THE LEGISLATION.
>> I WANT TO THANK JOHN DOHERTY FROM IBEW LOCAL SIX FOR HIS
INPUT. I WANT TO THANK STAFF FROM THE
DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENT AND THE DEPARTMENT BUILDING
INSPECTION FOR THEIR FEEDBACK. AND I WANT TO THANK MY CHIEF OF
STAFF SOPHIE MARIE FOR ALL HER WORK ON THE ORDINANCE.
>> SECONDLY, COLLEAGUES, I AM ASKING THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S
MEETING IN MEMORY OF ANDREA SHORTER WHO DIED FAR TOO SOON.
ON MARCH 19TH, 2026 SHE WAS A TRUE FORCE AND A FRIEND.
SHE WAS BORN ON OCTOBER 14TH, 1965 IN INDIANAPOLIS, INDIANA
AND MOVED TO CALIFORNIA AS A TEENAGER GRADUATING FROM PARIS
UNION HIGH SCHOOL BEFORE EARNING HER DEGREE IN SOCIOLOGY
FROM WHITTIER COLLEGE. SHE BEGAN HER CAREER
IN RIVERSIDE COUNTY WORKING ON A SUCCESSFUL STATE ASSEMBLY
CAMPAIGN. >> THEREAFTER SHE MOVED TO SAN
FRANCISCO IN 1991. OVER THE NEXT DECADES, ANDREA
WOULD CARVE A ROLE FOR HERSELF AS ONE OF THE MOST INFLUENTIAL
POLITICAL STRATEGISTS AND PUBLIC POLICY VOICES IN THE
CITY. HER AREAS OF ADVOCACY INCLUDED
CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORM, VOTING RIGHTS, DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
PREVENTION AND MARRIAGE EQUALITY IN LEADERSHIP ROLES
WITH ORGANIZATIONS SUCH AS EQUALITY CALIFORNIA OUT AN
EQUAL WORKPLACE ADVOCATES THE NAMES PROJECT AIDS MEMORIAL
QUILT AND THE CENTER ON JUVENILE AND CRIMINAL JUSTICE.
SHE HELPED DRIVE SYSTEMIC REFORMS WHILE ALWAYS CENTERING
THOSE MOST IMPACTED. >> ANDREA SERVED ON A NUMBER OF
CITY AND NONPROFIT COMMISSIONS AND BOARDS INCLUDING CITY
COLLEGE'S BOARD OF TRUSTEES AND 20 YEARS ON THE COMMISSION
ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN WHERE SHE SERVED MULTIPLE TERMS AS
PRESIDENT. IN 2009 SHE WAS HONORED AS
GRAND MARSHAL OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PRIDE PARADE.
SHE WAS A TRUSTED POLIS, A TRUSTED ADVISOR AND STRATEGIST
TO MANY OF OUR MOST SUCCESSFUL SAN FRANCISCO POLITICAL LEADERS
INCLUDING VICE PRESIDENT KAMALA HARRIS, MAYORS WILLIE BROWN
AND LONDON BREED. GOVERNOR GAVIN NEWSOM.
SPEAKER EMERITA NANCY PELOSI AND CONGRESSWOMAN LATIFA SIMON
A CO-FOUNDER OF THE BAYARD RUSTIN LGBT COALITION.
ANDREA WAS DEEPLY COMMITTED TO BUILDING BRIDGES BETWEEN THE
LGBTQ AND BLACK COMMUNITIES, BELIEVING THAT PROGRESS DEPENDS
ON COALITION BUILDING AND SHARED PURPOSE ACROSS
IDENTITIES. BEYOND HER PROFESSIONAL
ACCOMPLISHED MOMENTS, ANDREA BROUGHT JOY, CREATIVITY
AND WARMTH TO THOSE AROUND HER. SHE LOVED MUSIC AND PLAYED
GUITAR EACH EVENING OFTEN WRITING SONGS TO SHARE WITH
FAMILY. SHE HAD STRONG OPINIONS ABOUT
POP CULTURE AS WELL AS POLITICS WHICH SHE SHARED FREELY OVER
MEALS WITH FRIENDS. SHE'S SURVIVED BY HER PARTNER
LUBOV SMITH, HER MOTHER KAREN BROTHERS LAWRENCE AND AARON,
HER NEPHEWS KHALEEL AND LUCAS AND A WIDE CIRCLE OF FAMILY
FRIENDS AND COLLEAGUES, SOME OF WHOM ARE HERE TODAY AND ALL OF
WHOM WILL MISS HER VERY, VERY MUCH REST IN PEACE AND POWER.
ANDREA SHORTER. MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING.
SECONDLY, I'M ALSO ASKING THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING
IN MEMORY OF BRIXTON. A GOLDEN RETRIEVER AND THERAPY
DOG WHO SERVED THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR MORE THAN 12
YEARS. BRIXTON WAS ADOPTED BY LINDA
GORDON WHO I THINK IS HERE ALSO.
AT SIX MONTHS OLD AND BEGAN HIS CAREER AS A THERAPY DOG JUST
TWO MONTHS LATER. HE WAS A FOUNDING MEMBER OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORTS WAG BRIGADE FROM ITS
LAUNCH IN 2013 GREETING TRAVELERS AND EASING PREFLIGHT
ANXIETY. OVER THE YEARS BRIXTON SPREAD
SMILES ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO. HE WORKED IN SCHOOLS FROM
KINDERGARTEN THROUGH COLLEGE AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY,
UC SAN FRANCISCO, LOWELL AND GEORGE WASHINGTON HIGH
SCHOOLS AMONG MANY OTHERS. HE FOSTERED A LOVE OF READING
IN YOUNG YOUNG SAN FRANCISCANS THROUGH THE PUBLIC LIBRARY'S
PUPPY DOG TALES PROGRAM. HE BROUGHT COMFORT TO MEDICAL
STAFF AT ZUCKERBERG GENERAL INTO ILL CHILDREN AND THEIR
FAMILIES AT FAMILY HOUSE. BRIXTON WAS A PROUD ALLY OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY AND COULD OFTEN BE
FOUND IN HIS SIGNATURE SUNGLASSES AND COLORFUL
OUTFITS. AT EVENTS INCLUDING PRIDE
OUTSIDE LAND'S HARDLY STRICTLY BLUEGRASS, BLUEGRASS AND THE
GIANTS OPENING DAYS, BRIXTON DIED PEACEFULLY ON CRISSY FIELD
SURROUNDED BY THOSE HE LOVED. LINDA GORDON DESCRIBED WHAT SHE
LEARNED FROM HER YEARS WITH BRIXTON HOW TO NOT TAKE LIFE SO
SERIOUSLY AND HOW LOVE CAN BE SHARED SO EASILY.
WE WANT TO EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO LINDA
AND BRAXTON'S MANY FANS. HIS LEGACY WILL LIVE ON THROUGH
THE COUNTLESS COUNTLESS SAN FRANCISCO'S WHOSE SAN
FRANCISCANS WHOSE LIVED LIVES HE IMPROVED.
REST IN PEACE, BRIXTON. >> MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A
BLESSING. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION TO CLOSE A LOOPHOLE THAT HAS LONG BEEN IN OUR
CITY'S HEALTH CODE REGARDING SMOKING IN OUTDOOR SPACES OF
BARS AND RESTAURANTS. ACCORDING TO THE U.S. SURGEON
GENERAL CENTERS FOR DISEASE CONTROL AND PREVENTION AND THE
WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION SECONDHAND SMOKE HAS NO LEVEL
OF SAFE EXPOSURE. THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION
RECOMMENDS THAT INDIVIDUALS SHOULD BE EXPOSED TO NO MORE
THAN 15 MICROGRAMS PER CUBIC METER OF FINE PARTICULATE
MATTER. AVERAGE OVER 24 HOURS.
SHIFT WORKERS, WAITERS. SERVICE PERSONNEL EVEN
IN OUTDOOR SPACES ARE STILL EXPOSED TO THE DAILY
ACCUMULATION OF SECONDHAND SMOKE.
IN 2022, AIR QUALITY MEASUREMENTS TAKEN BY U.S. SRF
RESEARCHERS IN SAN FRANCISCO'S BAR PATIOS DETERMINED THAT SIX
OF THE NINE PATIOS VISITED HAD PEAK READINGS IN THE EPA
UNHEALTHY AIR RANGE. ONE PATIO WAS FOUND TO BE
IN THE HAZARDOUS RANGE WHERE PEOPLE WERE SMOKING CIGARS.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEEN A LEADER IN PUBLIC HEALTH BY
PASSING STRONG PROTECTIONS FOR SMOKE FREE PLACES AND FIGHTING
AGAINST THE VAPING AND TOBACCO INDUSTRIES THAT PREYS HEAVILY
ON YOUNG PEOPLE AND COMMUNITIES OF COLOR.
OVER TIME OUR CODE HAS BECOME OUTDATED AND EVEN THE STATE HAS
PASSED STRONGER REGULATIONS. THIS LEGISLATION WILL ALIGN US
WITH AT LEAST 400 CITIES AND COUNTIES NATIONWIDE
INCLUDING SAN JOSE, OAKLAND AND MORE THAN 50 BAY AREA
CITIES THAT HAVE ORDINANCES PROHIBITING SMOKING IN BAR
AND RESTAURANT PATIOS. I WANT TO THANK MY CO-SPONSOR
SUPERVISOR SAUTER, THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH'S
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH TEAM FOR THEIR COLLABORATION THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE, THE SAN FRANCISCO MARIN MEDICAL SOCIETY
LGBTQ YOUTH MINUS TOBACCO AND OTHER PASSIONATE ADVOCATES
FOR THEIR TIRELESS EFFORTS TO CLOSE THIS LOOPHOLE.
I AM ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION ALONG WITH
SUPERVISORS CHEN WALTON AND SÖDER IN SUPPORT OF SENATE
BILL 1091, WHICH WAS AUTHORED BY CALIFORNIA SENATOR ANNA
CABALLERO. >> THIS BILL WOULD ESTABLISH A
STATE COMMUNITY ANTI DISPLACEMENT AND PRESERVATION
PROGRAM WHICH SEEKS TO TACKLE THE HOUSING AFFORDABILITY
AND HOUSING SHORTAGE CRISIS IN CALIFORNIA.
THIS CONTINUES TO BE ONE OF THE MOST URGENT AND PRESSING ISSUES
ESPECIALLY HERE IN OUR CITY AND IN THE BAY AREA.
THE BAY AREA AND CALIFORNIA ARE SOME OF THE MOST EXPENSIVE
PLACES TO LIVE IN THE ENTIRE WORLD.
RENTING STAYING AT LONG TERM RESIDENCE RESIDENCES AND THE
POSSIBILITY OF OWNING A HOME ARE OUT OF REACH FOR SO MANY
PEOPLE. >> HOWEVER, THIS ISSUE IS
DISPARATE, FORTUNATELY AFFECTING LOW INCOME
AND MODERATE INCOME RESIDENTS WHO ARE AT RISK THAT OF
DISPLACEMENT MORE THAN EVER. LAST YEAR TENANTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO EXPERIENCED MORE THAN 3740 EVICTIONS OVER A YEAR LONG
PERIOD THE HIGHEST NUMBER OVER THE LAST TEN YEARS.
THE COMMUNITY ANTI DISPLACEMENT AND PRESERVATION PROGRAM
CREATES A STATE FUND THAT WOULD FINANCE THE ACQUISITION
AND REHABILITATION OF EXISTING UNSUBSIDIZED RENTAL HOUSING.
THE ACQUIRED HOUSING WOULD THEN BE CONVERTED INTO LONG TERM
DEED RESTRICTED AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS WITH DISPLACEMENT
PROTECTION FOR CURRENT RESIDENTS.
THIS WOULD CREATE AFFORDABLE HOUSING FROM HOUSING UNITS
ALREADY AVAILABLE LIMIT COSTS AND BARRIERS THAT ACCOMPANY
CONSTRUCTION AND ENSURE THAT LONG TERM TENANTS DON'T GET
KICKED OUT OF THEIR HOMES. ADDITIONALLY, THIS BILL WOULD
REQUIRE THE CALIFORNIA HOUSING AND HOMELESSNESS AGENCY TO
GRANT PRESCRIBED FUNDS TO THE PROGRAM MANAGER TO SUPPORT THE
EXECUTION OF THIS PROGRAM. THE FUNDS WOULD ALSO ALLOW
PROJECT MANAGERS TO ISSUE GRANTS AND LOANS TO ELIGIBLE
BORROWERS INCLUDING NONPROFIT ORGANIZATION GRANTS, MISSION
DRIVEN HOUSING PROVIDERS AND LOCAL JURISDICTIONS.
CALIFORNIA IS IN NEED OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND WE ARE
HOPEFUL THAT THE COMMUNITY ANTI DISPLACEMENT AND PRESERVATION
PROGRAM WILL ALLOW PEOPLE TO LIVE WORK AND THRIVE REGARDLESS
OF INCOME. I HOPE TO COUNT ON YOUR SUPPORT
FOR THIS RESOLUTION AND THAT THE STATE WILL PASS THIS BILL.
THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
MR. PRESIDENT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL
ORDER. >> YES, THIS IS FOR THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND FIRST UP DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG, CAN YOU HOLD
ON FOR A MINUTE UNTIL THEY COME ON UP?
LIKE MOLLY BURKE HAS MANY FRIENDS.
>> >> OKAY, YOU CAN COME CLOSER .
OKAY. COLLEAGUES, I'M HONORED TO
RECOGNIZE MOLLY MURPHY BURKE FOR MORE THAN 35 YEARS OF
SERVICE TO HER COMMUNITIES AND TO MILLIONS OF RIDERS WHO
LIE ON BART EVERY DAY. MOLLY HAS BEEN A CONSTANT
AND TRUSTED PARTNER TO THIS BOARD AND TO NEIGHBORHOODS
ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO. FOR MANY OF US SHE HAS BEEN THE
PERSON WE CALL WHEN SOMETHING NEEDS TO GET DONE OR WHEN OUR
COMMUNITIES NEED TO BE HEARD. SHE HAS CONSISTENTLY SHOWN UP
WITH CLARITY, RESPONSIVENESS AND A DEEP UNDERSTANDING OF
BOTH THE SYSTEM AND THE PEOPLE IT SERVES THROUGH ARC OR HER
CAREER. >> MOLLY HAS HELPED LEAD
OUTREACH FOR MAJOR SYSTEM EXPANSIONS AND GUIDED PARTS
ENGAGEMENT THROUGH DIFFERENT ADMINISTRATIONS AND MOMENTS OF
CHANGE. SHE HAS PLAYED A ROLE IN SOME
OF THE SYSTEM'S MOST SIGNIFICANT MILESTONES BUT WHAT
TRULY DEFINES HER WORK IS HOW SHE HAS DONE IT.
MOLLY APPROACHES PUBLIC SERVICE WITH A STRONG SENSE OF
RESPONSIBILITY TO THE COMMUNITY .
SHE UNDERSTANDS THAT BEHIND EVERY PROJECT, EVERY STATION
AND EVERY DECISION ARE REAL PEOPLE WHETHER SUPPORTING
RESIDENTS THROUGH CONSTRUCTION IMPACTS OR WORKING WITH SMALL
BUSINESSES OR ENSURING CLEAR COMMUNICATION.
SHE HAS BUILT TRUST THROUGH CONSISTENCY AND FOLLOW THROUGH.
SHE ALSO BRINGS SOMETHING INVALUABLE TO HER ROLE AS LONG
TIME DAILY WRITER. SHE UNDERSTANDS THE SYSTEM FROM
THE PERSPECTIVE OF THE PEOPLE WHO DEPEND ON IT.
THAT PERSPECTIVE HAS SHAPED HER WORK AND HER AND STRENGTHENED
HER ABILITY TO CONNECT POLICY WITH LIVED EXPERIENCE HERE
IN THE SUNSET AND ACROSS THE WEST SIDE.
WE HAVE SEEN FIRSTHAND THE IMPACT OF HER PARTNERSHIP.
SHE KNOWS OUR COMMUNITIES. SHE LISTENS CAREFULLY AND SHE
WORKS TO MAKE SURE WE STAY INFORMED AND CONNECTED.
BEYOND HER PROFESSIONAL ROLE, MOLLY AND HER HUSBAND MARK HAVE
CONTRIBUTED MEANINGFULLY TO COMMUNITY LIFE HELPING BRING
PEOPLE TOGETHER AND SUPPORT SPACES THAT INCLUDE
STRENGTHENING NEIGHBORHOOD CONNECTIONS ESPECIALLY DURING
CHALLENGING TIMES. MOLLY THANK YOU FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP, YOUR PARTNERSHIP AND YOUR LASTING CONTRIBUTIONS
TO SAN FRANCISCO AND BEYOND. ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD,
CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR WELL EARNED RETIREMENT.
WE WISH YOU CONTINUED JOY GOOD HEALTH AND MANY NEW ADVENTURES
AHEAD. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WONG FOR YEAH. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
BEFORE MOLLY JUST BEFORE YOU SPEAK I JUST WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR WONG FOR DOING THIS IN MEMORIAM.
WE LOVE YOU. YOU HAVE BEEN IN ME BECAUSE I
FEEL MORE KNOW STILL THERE. I'M NOT GOING AWAY.
THIS IS SPECIAL COMMENDATION. >> WE BART HAS BEEN THROUGH A
ROUGH NUMBER OF YEARS. YOU HAVE BEEN SUCH A GREAT FACE
AND VOICE FOR THAT FOR BART PARTICULARLY I THINK IN THE
TOUGH TIMES. AND SO I'M IF IF SUPERVISOR
HUANG WAS NOT GOING TO DO THIS, I WAS GOING TO DO IT.
BUT I'M GLAD THAT HE DID SO. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> THANK YOU. OH, THIS IS JUST AN AMAZING
MOMENT FOR ME. I'VE BEEN IN THESE CHAMBERS
HUNDREDS OF TIMES AND LISTEN TO YOU AND BE YOU KNOW, REALLY
BEFORE I BEGIN I JUST REALLY WANT TO THANK THE BOARD BUT
MOSTLY ALL OF YOUR AIDES WHO HAVE BEEN TREMENDOUS.
THEY HAVE GOTTEN ME THROUGH MY JOB.
THEY ARE AMAZING PEOPLE OVER DECADES.
I MEAN SO MANY THAT I'VE KNOWN .
SO WITH THAT I'LL MAKE MY COMMENTS AND THANK YOU.
THANK YOU BOTH SO MUCH. GOOD AFTERNOON TO HONORABLE
MAYOR LURIE WHO MAY NOT BE IN THE ROOM BUT WHEREVER YOU
ARE I KNOW YOU'RE OUT THERE. PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN, MY FRIEND
AND DISTINGUISHED MEMBERS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS I WOULD LIKE TO BEGIN WITH A SPECIAL THANK YOU
TO DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR ALAN HUANG FOR INVITING ME HERE
TODAY AND FOR THIS WONDERFUL HONOR AND THANK YOU TO TIFF LEE
FOR YOUR COORDINATION IN YOUR KINDNESS TIFF.
YOU'RE AMAZING AND YOU MAKE THIS OFFICE HAPPEN.
I AM DEEPLY HONORED TO BE RECOGNIZED TODAY FOR MY 35
YEARS OF SERVICE WITH THE BART DISTRICT AND FOR DECADES IN BAY
AREA TRANSPORTATION A ATTENDING WITH ME TODAY IS MY FAN CLUB
ATTENDING OUR MEMBERS OF MY OWN FAMILY ALONG WITH MEMBERS OF MY
FAMILY, MY SISTERS CARRIE AND PEGGY ARE HERE THEY WHERE
ARE THEY? >> AND MY BROTHER UNFORTUNATELY
IS NOT HERE TODAY. HE IS SERVING THE CITY.
HE IS WORKING HARD FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
SO WE'LL MISS YOU, MIKE. ALSO WITH ME IS MY BROTHER
IN LAW FRANK KAGAN, MARRIED TO CARRIE AND MY COUSIN PAUL
MCCANN WHO REPRESENTS ALL OF MY COUSINS THROUGHOUT SAN
FRANCISCO AND THERE ARE HUNDREDS.
>> I ALSO WANT TO INTRODUCE SOMEONE WHO YOU ALREADY KNOW.
>> HE IS MY FAVORITE BART DIRECTOR DIRECTOR BEVAN DUFTY
FORMER DIRECTOR AND MY MANAGER AT BART WHO IS BRADLEY DUNN IS
A GREAT MANAGER AND I DO MISS HIM AND ALONG WITH MARK
NICHOLAS MY COLLEAGUE WHO TOOK OVER MY WORK WHEN I LEFT
IN FEBRUARY. >> AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST I
LOVE HER WITH ALL MY HEART. SHE IS MY COWORKER AND FRIEND
AND HAD DUCKWORTH SO WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO GO ON AND MOST
ESPECIALLY THANK MY HUSBAND MY HUSBAND HERE HE IS A HE HE
AND OUR TWO DAUGHTERS WHO LIVE IN CHICAGO AND CAN'T BE HERE
TODAY. THEIR NAMES ARE MAGGIE
AND MAUREEN BURKE. THEY HAVE BEEN A CONSTANT
SUPPORT THROUGHOUT MY CAREER AND I WANT TO RECOGNIZE MY MOM
AS WELL WHO IS HERE TODAY. THANK YOU, MAMA.
>> YOU WERE MY STRENGTH IN MY WISDOM OVER ALL THESE YEARS AS
A WORKING MOM AND YOU ALWAYS REMINDED ME THAT I WAS SETTING
A GOOD EXAMPLE FOR OUR DAUGHTERS.
>> IT HAS BEEN A TREMENDOUS PRIVILEGE TO REPRESENT BART
IN BOTH SAN FRANCISCO AND SAN MATEO COUNTIES THROUGHOUT MY
CAREER. BUT WORKING IN SAN FRANCISCO
HAS ALWAYS HELD A SPECIAL PLACE IN MY HEART BECAUSE THIS IS
WHERE MY STORY BEGAN. I PROUDLY COME FROM THE SUNSET
DISTRICT OF SAN FRANCISCO FROM A LARGE IRISH-AMERICAN FAMILY
WITH DEEP ROOTS THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
STANDING IN THIS CHAMBER TODAY IS ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL TO ME.
>> MY GREAT GRANDFATHER DANIEL CORNELIUS MURPHY IF YOU HAVEN'T
HEARD IT BEFORE, SERVED AS THE SHERIFF OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR
MANY YEARS I HAVE FELT HIS PRESENCE IN THESE HALLS OVER
TIME IT HAS MADE ME INCREDIBLY PROUD OF MY FAMILY HERITAGE
AND LEGACY IN THIS CITY. MY FATHER MICHAEL ANDREW MURPHY
,WHO PASSED AWAY IN 2023, WOULD HAVE BEEN PROUD TO SEE ME
STANDING HERE TODAY. SO I THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WANG AND ALSO MY UNCLE DAN WHO CARRIES THE NAME
DANIEL CORNELIUS MURPHY STILL TODAY IS LIVE LIVES IN NO
VALLEY AND IS THE PATRIARCH OF THE MURPHY FAMILY.
>> HE IS 90. MY CAREER IN TRANSPORTATION
BEGAN IN 1986 WHEN I TOOK A JOB IN SAN JOSE WORKING IN THE
EARLY DAYS FOR THE SOUTH SOUTH BAY LIGHT RAIL SYSTEM FOLLOWED
BY A STINT AT CALTRANS ON THE SIX 8024 INTERCHANGE.
THOSE EXPERIENCES ULTIMATELY LEE LED ME TO BART WHERE I
SPENT 35 INCREDIBLE YEARS. >> I AM PROUD OF THE WORK I
HAVE ACCOMPLISHED IN COMMUNITIES ACROSS THE BAY
AREA BUT NOTHING MEANS MORE TO ME THAN THE WORK ACCOMPLISHED
IN SAN FRANCISCO. FROM DOWNTOWN STATIONS WHERE I
LED OUTREACH ON BOTH BART CANOPY AND ESCALATOR PROJECTS
AT OUR FOUR DOWNTOWN STATIONS TO MY WORK IN THE MISSION
DISTRICT AT 16TH AND 24TH STREET STATIONS TO THE EAST
SIDE WALKWAY THE WALKWAY LEADING FROM OCEAN AVENUE TO
THE BART STATION ALLOWING STUDENTS TO GET TO AND FROM
CLASS. AND RECENTLY THE HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT AT BALBOA PARK AS WELL THE ONGOING NEIGHBORHOOD
OUTREACH IN GLEN PARK AND DALY CITY AND THE LIST GOES ON.
MY WORK IS NOT ABOUT COMMUNICATION.
IT WAS ABOUT LISTENING BECAUSE WHEN YOU LISTEN YOU LEARN
AND WHEN YOU LEARN YOU CAN BETTER SERVE.
>> I AM PROUD OF THE WORK ACCOMPLISHED THE MANY
COMMUNITIES THAT BART HAS TOUCHED AND EVEN THOSE
COMMUNITIES WHERE WE DO NOT DIRECTLY SERVE WE STILL IMPACT
. >> BART WAS NOT JUST A JOB FOR
ME IT WAS A TRUE PASSION A PASSION THAT BEGAN ON MAY 1ST,
1990 AND WILL COME TO A CLOSE NOW.
OVER THESE YEARS IT HAS TRULY BEEN A PLEASURE TO INFORM
AND EDUCATE THE PUBLIC ON BART'S EXPANSIONS,
MODERNIZATIONS, TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGES AND OUR CHALLENGING
PANDEMIC. >> IT WAS AN HONOR TO SUPPORT
SIX BART GENERAL MANAGERS WORK UNDER EIGHT SAN FRANCISCO
MAYORAL ADMINISTRATIONS AND I WILL NEVER FORGET THE BART
ANNIVERSARIES FROM OUR 20TH TO OUR 50TH.
EVEN THOUGH I LOOKED 28, I'LL ALWAYS BE PROUD OF THE EARLY
MISSION PLAZA RENOVATIONS WITH BEAVAN.
I HELPED IMPLEMENT THOSE AND ALWAYS REMEMBER THE MISSION
STREET GREAT PROJECT WHERE I WALKED BLOCK TO BLOCK TO BLOCK
KEEPING BUSINESSES INFORMED. >> MY MIND WILL RECALL THE
THOUSANDS OF TRACTION POWER UPGRADE MEETINGS TO DISCUSS
WHAT WAS HAPPENING UNDERNEATH MARKET STREET AND THE PROJECT
ACROSS 50 BART STATIONS WHERE WE REPLACED NEW FARE GATES
COMPLETE IT IN RECORD TIME AND PRIORITIZING THE RIDER
EXPERIENCE AND MY FEET WILL NOT SOON FORGET THE HUNDREDS OF
FAIRS AND FESTIVALS THAT I WORKED ACROSS THE BAY AREA
SHARING THE BART STORY THANKING LOYAL RIDERS AND ENCOURAGING
NEW ONES TO PLEASE COME ON BOARD.
I'M ALMOST THERE. >> BART HAS BEEN MY SECOND HOME
AND IT WILL REMAIN IN MY HEART FOREVER.
THIS IS WHERE I GET A LITTLE TEARY SO HOLD ON.
I AM DEEPLY GRATEFUL FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO SERVE THE PEOPLE
OF SAN FRANCISCO AND TO HAVE WORKED ALONGSIDE SO MANY OF YOU
TO IMPROVE TRANSIT RESOLVE ISSUES AND SUPPORT MAJOR
MOMENTS IN THIS CITY AND ACROSS THE BAY AREA.
>> AS I MOVED TO RETIREMENT I LOOK FORWARD TO TRAVELING WITH
MY HUSBAND SPENDING MORE TIME WITH MY FAMILY AND STAYING
ACTIVE IN OUR IRISH COMMUNITY THROUGH MUSIC, CULTURE
AND SERVICE. I LEAVE BART PROUD TO HAVE
LASTED LONGER THAN THE FLEET OF A, B AND C CARS.
>> I LASTED LONGER THAN THE BLUE CARPET YOU MIGHT REMEMBER.
I LASTED LONGER THAN THE FABRIC SEATS AND THE VINYL SEATS AND I
PLANNED LASTED LONGER THAN THE PAPER TICKET.
>> WOO HOO! SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANN DOLMAN .
YOU BOTH ARE IN MY HEARTS. AND THANK YOU MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND MY FRIEND UP THERE, ANGELA
CALVILLO. I'VE KNOWN YOU FOR YEARS.
THANK YOU ALL SO MUCH FOR THIS OPPORTUNITY TO SERVE THE PEOPLE
OF SAN FRANCISCO AND THE RELATIONSHIPS THAT EACH OF YOU
AND YOUR STAFF HAVE MEANT TO ME.
>> THANK YOU. A FEW ALSO COME AROUND HERE
FROM THREE. ONE MORE.
ONE MORE. OH, YOU GOT ONE, PLEASE.
>> OH YEAH. OH, THESE ARE MY BOOKS.
>>
ALL RIGHT, NEXT UP DISTRICT SEVEN SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT AT LUCERO.
IF YOU COULD COME UP, PLEASE. >> COLLEAGUES AT TODAY I AM
THRILLED TO RECOGNIZE AND HONOR LA CASA DE LAS MADRES ON THEIR
50TH ANNIVERSARY WHICH IS TRULY AN AMAZING MILESTONE.
YELLOW SAID WHOEVER IF YOU PUT MONEY ON YOUR BOARD WANTS TO
COME UP WITH YOU OR YOUR STAFF. THANK YOU.
THIS IS TRULY AN AMAZING MILESTONE THAT WE'RE
CELEBRATING HERE TODAY. LA CASA DE LAS MADRES BEGAN
IN 1974 WHEN A GROUP OF PASSIONATE WOMEN WERE
DETERMINED TO CREATE A PLACE OF SAFETY FOR SURVIVORS OF
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE. >> THESE WOMEN TIRELESSLY
RESEARCHED HOW INSTITUTIONS HANDLE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
INTERVIEWED LIVE FORESMAN OFFICIALS AND COLLECTED ALL THE
INFORMATION THEY COULD ON THE THEN CURRENT DATA AND SUPPORT
AVAILABLE TO SURVIVORS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE.
>> THEY FOUND THAT THERE WAS AN INSUFFICIENT AND WHOLLY
INADEQUATE AMOUNT OF RESOURCES FOR SURVIVORS AND THEIR KIDS.
THIS ENCOURAGED THESE PASSIONATE WOMEN TO DEVELOP
FUNDING PROPOSALS TO TESTIFY AT LOCAL HEARINGS ON MARITAL
VIOLENCE TO RAISE AWARENESS ON THE ISSUE.
>> IN 1976 LA CASA DE LAS MATTRESS WAS OFFICIALLY FOUNDED
AS AN ESTABLISHED ORGANIZATION. THEY THEY BEGAN PROVIDING FOR
CORE SERVICES WHICH INCLUDED A 24 SEVEN CRISIS HOTLINE
EMERGENCY SHELTER FOR WOMEN AND CHILDREN COMMUNITY SUPPORT
GROUPS AND PREVENTION EDUCATION EFFORTS.
>> OVER THE LAST 50 YEARS LA CASA DE LAS MADRES HAS SERVED
OVER 14,000 DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SURVIVORS.
>> THEY HAVE GROWN TREMENDOUSLY IN NOT ONLY THEIR REACH ACROSS
THE COMMUNITY AND CAPACITY TO SERVE BUT THE CRITICAL SERVICES
THEY PROVIDE PEOPLE. >> LIKE I SAID, THE LAS MADRES
HAS ALSO PLAYED AN ACTIVE ROLE IN REFORMING THE LEGAL SYSTEM
ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO AND REALLY ACROSS THE COUNTRY TO ENSURE
THAT THERE IS TRAUMA INFORMED TRAINING FOR LAW ENFORCEMENT
IN THAT CASA FOLKS ALSO WORK TO REMOVE BARRIERS TO SUPPORT FOR
SURVIVORS FACING FINANCIAL INSECURITY, IMMIGRATION STATUS
AND OTHER BARRIERS TO SUCCESS. >> LIKE I SAID, THE LAST MADRES
IS NOT ONLY AN ESSENTIAL SUPPORT AND RESOURCE FOR
COMMUNITY IN PROVIDING SHELTER AND HELP TO SURVIVORS, THEY
ALSO ARE ACTIVELY BUILDING A FUTURE WHERE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
IS ABOLISHED, WHERE SOME SURVIVORS ARE BELIEVED, WHERE
THEY ARE SUPPORTED AND HEALTHY RELATIONSHIPS ARE THE NORM.
WE ARE SO GRATEFUL TO LA CASA DE LAS MADRASAHS IMPACT AND SAN
FRANCISCO THEIR INFLUENCE ACROSS THE COUNTRY
AND CONTINUED DEDICATION TO ADVOCATING FOR SURVIVORS OF
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE. TODAY WE ARE JOINED BY FOUNDERS
STAFF VOLUNTEERS, SUPPORTERS AND SURVIVORS.
I AM SO HONORED TO COMMEND THE CASA DE LAS MATTRESS TODAY AT
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING.
LATER ON IN OUR AGENDA WE WILL OFFICIALLY PROCLAIM TODAY APRIL
7TH, 2026 AS LA CASA DE LAS MOTHERS DAY IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY SAN FRANCISCO. AND NOW I'LL TURN IT OVER TO
LUCERO TO SHARE A FEW WORDS. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
THANK YOU BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR THIS RECOGNITION.
MY NAME IS LAZARO ARIAS AND I HAVE THE HONOR OF SERVING AS
THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF LIKE AS WELL AS MY ADDRESS STANDING
WITH ME TODAY. OUR LEADERSHIP AS WELL AS OUR
FOUNDER AND BOARD MEMBER SONIA MERCADO THIS YEAR MARKS
ACTUALLY TODAY APRIL SEVENTH MARKS 50 YEARS OF LA CASA DE
LAS MATTRESS. 50 YEARS AGO A GROUP OF WOMEN
IN SAN FRANCISCO CAME TOGETHER WITH A SIMPLE BUT URGENT BELIEF
THAT NO ONE SHOULD HAVE TO CHOOSE BETWEEN STAYING
IN VIOLENCE OR HAVING NOWHERE TO GO.
FROM THAT BELIEF, LA CASA LAST MATTRESS WAS BORN.
>> SINCE THEN THOUSANDS OF SURVIVORS AND THEIR CHILDREN
HAVE COME TO LA CASA AND SOME OF THE MOST DIFFICULT MOMENTS
OF THEIR LIVES SEEKING SAFETY, SUPPORT AND A CHANCE TO BEGIN
AGAIN. AND WHAT THEY FIND IS NOT JUST
SHELTER. THEY FIND SOMEONE WHO ANSWERS
THE PHONE SOMEONE WHO BELIEVES IN THEM, SOMEONE WHO WALKS
ALONGSIDE THEM AS THEY REBUILD THEIR LIVES.
THIS RECOGNITION IS NOT JUST ABOUT LA CASA.
IT REFLECTS THE CITY'S LONG STANDING COMMITMENT TO
SURVIVORS AND THE PARTNERSHIP THAT MAKE THIS WORK POSSIBLE
EVERY DAY. EARLIER TODAY WE GATHERED ON
THE STEPS OF CITY HALL TO MARK THIS MILESTONE NOT JUST TO
CELEBRATE BUT TO REAFFIRM OUR SHARED COMMITMENT TO SURVIVORS
AND THE WORK AHEAD BECAUSE EVEN AS WE CELEBRATE, WE KNOW THAT
THE WORK IS FAR FROM OVER. TOO MANY SURVIVORS STILL FACE
BARRIERS TO SAFETY WHETHER IN HOUSING, ECONOMIC STABILITY
OR ACCESS TO CARE. AND IT IS OUR SHARED
RESPONSIBILITY TO ENSURE THAT OUR SYSTEMS ARE RESPONSIVE,
COORDINATED AND CENTERED ON DIGNITY AND HEALING.
SO TODAY WE ACCEPT THIS COMMENDATION NOT ONLY WITH
GRATITUDE BUT WITH RENEWED COMMITMENT TO PREVENTION TO
EQUITY AND TO ENSURING THAT EVERY SURVIVOR IN OUR CITY HAS
ACCESS TO SAFETY AND SUPPORT. THANK YOU FOR THIS HONOR
AND FOR STANDING WITH LIKE OURSELVES MOTHERS AND THE
COMMUNITIES THAT WE SERVE
. >> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK,
LET'S GO BACK TO ROLL CALL. NEXT UP, SUPERVISOR SAUTER TO
INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK
AND THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE ONE
RESOLUTION. IT'S A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF
H.R. 2410 WHICH IS THE REVITALIZING DOWNTOWNS AND MAIN
STREETS ACT. >> THIS BIPARTISAN BILL
AUTHORED BY U.S. REPRESENTATIVES MIKE CASEY
AND JIMMY GOMEZ WOULD PROVIDE A FEDERAL TAX CREDIT TO
FACILITATE THE CONVERSION OF OFFICE AND OTHER COMMERCIAL
BUILDINGS INTO HOUSING. IT'S NO SECRET THAT WE'VE BEEN
FOCUSED ON THIS WORK HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
BE IT THE 2024 PASSAGE OF PROP C OR A RECENT ESTABLISHMENT OF
THE DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION FINANCING DISTRICT.
>> BUT WE WELCOME ALL SUPPORT FROM OUR FEDERAL PARTNERS
AND THIS NEW FEDERAL TAX INCENTIVE MODELED AFTER THE
HISTORIC HISTORICAL PRESERVATION TAX CREDIT WOULD
HELP OFFSET PROHIBITIVE COSTS. SO THESE PROJECTS CAN
CONTRIBUTE TO EASING THE HOUSING SHORTAGE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE REST OF THE UNITED STATES.
LAST MONTH IN WASHINGTON, D.C. ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR MELGAR, WE
HAD THE CHANCE TO SPEAK WITH REPRESENTATIVE GOMEZ'S TEAM
ABOUT THIS BILL AND GIVE FEEDBACK TO IMPROVE ITS IMPACT
FOR SAN FRANCISCANS. SO I WANT TO SUPPORT.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR HER CO-SPONSORSHIP
OF THIS RESOLUTION AS WELL. I APPRECIATE REPRESENTATIVE
GOMES STEADFAST WORK IN HOUSING .
IN 2023 HE LAUNCHED THE CONGRESSIONAL RENTERS CAUCUS
THE FIRST TIME SUCH A BODY HAD EXISTED TO GIVE VOICE TO
RENTERS ACROSS THE COUNTRY AT THE HIGHEST LEVELS OF
GOVERNMENT. >> IT IS MY HOPE THAT WE CAN
SUPPORT THIS BILL TO SHOW THAT SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS AS MANY
TOOLS AS POSSIBLE TO CREATE NEW HOUSING AND WE EMBRACE IDEAS
FROM ALL PARTNERS TO DO SO. AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUPERVISOR
CHERYL SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
AFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO THE SAFETY,
DIGNITY AND BELONGING OF PACIFIC ISLANDER COMMUNITIES
AND CONDEMNING THE HATE VIOLENCE AND TARGETED THREATS
THEY HAVE FACED. PACIFIC ISLANDERS HAVE ALWAYS
BEEN A PART OF THIS CITY. THEIR HISTORY HERE IS ROOTED
IN RESILIENCE, CULTURAL CONTRIBUTION, LABOR
AND COMMUNITY BUILDING AND YET THEIR COMMUNITY HAS BEEN
SUBJECTED TO A PATTERN OF TARGETED THREATS AND FALSE
NARRATIVES DESIGNED TO DIMINISH THEIR PRESENCE AND UNDERMINE
THE LEGITIMACY OF THEIR INSTITUTE ACTIONS HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THIS IS UNACCEPTABLE.
NO COMMUNITY SHOULD HAVE TO FIGHT FOR THEIR RIGHT TO EXIST
AND THEIR OWN CITY. THIS AFTERNOON THE PACIFIC
ISLANDER COMMUNITY AS WELL AS SEVERAL MEMBERS FROM COMMUNITY
MARCHED TO THE STEPS OF CITY HALL AND HOSTED A RALLY AT
CIVIC CENTER PLAZA TO SAY LOUD AND CLEAR THAT THEY WILL NOT BE
ERASED. THIS RESOLUTION IS THE BOARD'S
ANSWER TO THAT CALL AND WE STAND WITH SAN FRANCISCO'S
PACIFIC ISLANDER COMMUNITY. I WANT TO THANK MY CO-SPONSORS
SUPERVISORS CHIN CHEN DORSEY AND WONG.
>> I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION ALONG WITH MY
CO-SPONSOR SUPERVISOR MELGAR AS WELL AS SUPERVISORS CHIN CHEN
DORSEY AND WONG. A RESOLUTION DECLARING APRIL
11TH THROUGH APRIL 17TH AS BLACK MATERNAL HEALTH WEEK HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. THIS YEAR MARKS THE 10TH
ANNIVERSARY OF THE BLACK MAMAS MATTER ALLIANCE.
AND THIS WEEK MATTERS MORE THAN EVER.
THE DATA WE ARE PRESENTED WITH IS NOT IMPROVING FAST ENOUGH.
BLACK BIRTHING MOTHERS MAKING UP JUST 4% OF BIRTHS IN SAN
FRANCISCO BUT ACCOUNT FOR 50% OF PREGNANCY RELATED DEATHS.
RATES OF VERY PREMATURE BIRTHS AMONG BLACK BABIES.
THOSE BORN AT 32 WEEKS EARLIER INCREASED BY 71% BETWEEN 2016
AND 2024, RISING FROM 2.1% TO 3.6% OF BIRTHS.
THAT IS THEY CONTINUE CRISIS WHILE OUTCOMES FOR BLACK
BIRTHING PARENTS AND THEIR BABIES HAVE BEEN DECLINING.
AND THAT'S THE INVESTIGATION FOUND THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS
UNDERSPENT ITS BUDGET TO ADDRESS MATERNAL INEQUITIES BY
AT LEAST $8 MILLION SINCE 2021, RETURNING THE HIGHEST PORTION
OF ITS PRENATAL EQUITY INITIATIVE FUNDS BACK TO THE
STATE. WE CANNOT TALK ABOUT COMMITMENT
WHILE LEAVING MONEY ON THE TABLE.
THAT WAS SUPPOSED TO BE DEDICATED TO REDUCING BLACK
PREGNANCY RELATED DEATHS NATIONALLY.
WHILE MATERNAL MORTALITY RATES HAVE DECLINED FOR WHITE,
HISPANIC AND ASIAN WOMEN, BLACK WOMEN'S RATES HAVE HELD STEADY
OR WORSENED WITH BLACK WOMEN DYING AT MORE THAN THREE TIMES
THE RATE OF WHITE WOMEN. THE CENTER FOR DISEASE CONTROL
CONFIRMED THAT THE MATERNAL MORTALITY RATE DECREASE FOR
EVERY RACIAL GROUP EXCEPT BLACK WOMEN IN SAN FRANCISCO.
WE ARE IN FACT ONE OF THE WORST EXAMPLES.
THESE DISPARITIES ARE ROOTED IN SYSTEMIC RACISM.
THEY ARE ALSO ROOTED IN DISINVESTMENT.
FEDERAL RESTRUCTURING UNDER THE CURRENT ADMINISTRATION HAS
HALTED COMMUNITY BASED MATERNAL HEALTH GRANTS.
ELIMINATING THE WHITE HOUSE BLUEPRINT FOR ADDRESSING THE
MATERNAL HEALTH CRISIS AND LAID OFF MOST STAFF IN THE CDC'S
DIVISION OF REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH.
THAT MEANS THE PRESSURE ON CITIES LIKE OURS TO STEP UP IS
EVEN GREATER. >> THE GOOD NEWS IS THAT
SOLUTIONS EXIST RIGHT HERE AND WE JUST NEED TO INVEST
IN THEM SO THAT THEY HAVE ADEQUATE RESOURCES TO ADDRESS
THIS PROBLEM. OUR RESOLUTION AFFIRMS SAN
FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO THE HEALTH SAFETY AND JOY OF BLACK
BIRTHING MOTHERS. EVERY PERSON IN THIS CITY
DESERVES A JOYFUL, HEALTHY PREGNANCY.
AND COLLEAGUES, MY LAST ORDER OF BUSINESS TODAY IS AN
IN MEMORIAM FOR ANDERSON J.B. WILLIAMS.
JB WAS A NATIVE SON BORN IN HUNTERS POINT IN 1958,
PASSED AWAY SUNDAY NIGHT. HE GRADUATED FROM MISSION HIGH
SCHOOL, SERVED HIS COUNTRY IN THE ARMY, CAME HOME, STARTED
A FAMILY AND BUILT A LIFE ROOTED IN THIS CITY.
FOR 40 YEARS J.B. WAS A BARBER AND IF YOU KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
A GREAT BARBER, YOU KNOW IT IS NEVER JUST ABOUT THE HAIRCUT.
FOR THREE DECADES AFTER OPENING THE SHOP ON LELAND AVENUE, J.B.
GAVE FREE HAIRCUTS TO STUDENTS WHO EARNED A 3.0 GPA WHO SHOWED
PROGRESS ON THEIR REPORT CARDS, WHO WALKED ACROSS A GRADUATION
STAGE, WHO SHOWED UP TO PROM. HE BELIEVED IN YOUNG PEOPLE
BEFORE THEY BELIEVED IN THEMSELVES.
>> J.B. USED TO SAY THAT BEING A BARBER MEANT HELPING TURN
BOYS INTO MEN. TEACHING HYGIENE, SELF-RESPECT
,PRIDE AND DIGNITY. >> HE UNDERSTOOD THAT IT TAKES
A VILLAGE TO RAISE A CHILD AND HE WAS HONORED TO BE A PART
OF THAT VILLAGE. WE WERE THE ONES WHO WERE
HONORED RECENTLY MY LEGISLATIVE A CHIEF OF STAFF PERCY BIRCH
AND I HAD THE PLEASURE OF HONORING HIM AT THE VETERANS
HOSPITAL. WE HAD ALWAYS PLANNED TO HONOR
HIM HERE IN THE CHAMBER BUT WE GOT NEWS THAT HIS TIME WOULD BE
SHORT SO WE WANTED TO MAKE SURE THAT WE TOOK THE TIME TO DO
THAT WITH COMMUNITY AND SO WE BROUGHT THE HONOR AND COMMUNITY
TO HIM. HE WAS LOOKING FORWARD TO
CELEBRATING 30 YEARS OF BUSINESS WITH THE BLOCK PARTY
ONLY ONE AVENUE AND WE'RE STILL GOING TO MAKE SURE THAT THAT
HAPPENS. >> THIS THE LEAST WE CAN DO FOR
A MAN WHO GAVE SO MUCH OF HIMSELF TO SO MANY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. RAISING AND MENTORING OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE AND BEING A BARBER SLASH PSYCHOLOGIST TO SO MANY.
REST IN POWER J.B. SAN FRANCISCO WOULD NOT FORGET YOU.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR WONG.
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHIN. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING AND MEMORIAM FOR
JOHN ALBERT LING. JOHN ALBERT KING PASSED AWAY
LAST WEEK AT 79 AFTER DECADES OF ADVOCACY AS ONE OF THE MOST
PASSIONATE AND INFLUENTIAL AFFORDABLE HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY CHAMPIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> YOU KNOW THAT HE WAS A FORCE OF NATURE IN A CITY WHEN EVEN
HIS FOLLOWERS DIDN'T WAIT TO ANNOUNCE HIS PASSING ON LINE.
MANY KNOW JOHN BURLING AS THE PRESIDENT OF TENANTS AND OWNERS
DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION, ALSO KNOWN AS TOM COLE.
HE JOINED THE GROUP IN 1978 WHEN HE AND I STARTED
CONSTRUCTION ON ONE OF ITS FIRST SENIOR HOUSING BUILDINGS
. >> TODAY TACO OWNS ABOUT 1000
UNITS OF LOW INCOME HOUSING IN THE SOUTH TO MARKET WHERE
JOHN DEDICATED HIS LEGACY ENSURING THAT THERE IS A PLACE
FOR LOW INCOME FAMILIES, SENIORS AND ARTISTS TO THRIVE
AS THEY CONTINUE TO FACE GENTRIFICATION AND REAL ESTATE
SPECULATION. AFTER JOINING TACO AL BURLING
WORKED ON THE 1980S PROP M PROPOSITION AD CAMPAIGN THAT
FOUGHT EXCESSIVE OFFICE DEVELOPMENT IS SHAPED SAN
FRANCISCO'S SKYLINE TODAY SLOWED DOWN THE LOSS OF OUR LOW
INCOME HOUSING STOCK AND AIMED TO PROTECT THE CITY'S CHARACTER
AGAINST UNCONTROLLED REDEVELOPMENT.
JOHN SAW VALUE AND THE ESSENTIAL ROLE OF ART SPACES,
LIGHT INDUSTRIAL FACILITIES AND CULTURAL PRESERVATION
INFRASTRUCTURE AND GOT PROPOSITION X TO PASS WHICH
PROTECTED THOSE SPACES REQUIRING DEVELOPERS TO FIND
NEW SPACE AND PAY FOR RELOCATION ESPECIALLY WITHIN
THE CENTRAL SOMA PLAN. JOHN IS AN ELDER EARLY ADOPTER
OF DEVELOPMENT AGREEMENT THAT PUTS COMMUNITY TENANTS
AND SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS IN THE DRIVER'S SEAT.
>> IF IT WERE NOT FOR JOHN YOUR BOY NOT GARDENS AS THAT WE SEE
TODAY WOULD BE A PRIVATIZED ASSETS AND THE EASTERN
NEIGHBORHOOD PLAN WOULDN'T HAVE HAPPENED.
COMMUNITY BENEFITS REQUIREMENTS FOR DEVELOPERS LIKE PARKS,
HEALTH CLINICS, LIBRARIES AND PEDESTRIAN SAFETY PLANS.
I WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT TO SHARE WHAT MAYOR OUR OPPONENTS
WROTE ABOUT JOHN FROM THEIR TIME WORKING TOGETHER TO
COMPLETE MOSCONE CENTER. THIS IS FROM MAYOR ART AT
KNOLLS. JOHN ALBERT LANE WILL BE
REMEMBERED AS A FIERCE, BRILLIANT CHAMPION FOR THE POOR
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND IN THE SOUDER MARKET IN PARTICULAR.
HE WAS ONE OF THE FIRST ADVOCATES I MET WHEN I CAME TO
SAN FRANCISCO IN 1966 FOR A JOB AS A SOCIAL WORKER AS SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC HOUSING. HE BLEW ME AWAY WITH HIS ONE OF
A KIND BLEND OF ORGANIZING STRATEGY FINANCIAL ACUMEN
AND OF COURSE BAD LANGUAGE RESERVED FOR POWERFUL PEOPLE.
IN 1988 THE MOSCONE CONVENTION CENTER WAS PERIODICALLY
REFERRED TO AS THE LONGEST STALLED URBAN RENEWAL PROJECT
IN AMERICA. JOHN ALBERT KING WAS AN
IMPORTANT PART OF A CITYWIDE GROUP OF ADVOCATES LED BY
LEADERS LIKE SUSIE BERRYMAN, SUE HESTER, CALVIN WALSH, DOUG
INMAN AND OTHERS WHO ACCEPTED MY INVITATION TO FINALLY
COMPLETE THE NEW CONVENTION CENTER WE NEEDED TO COMPLETE
FOR OUR CITY. YOUNG UP AND COMING IDEA
IDEALISTIC AND AGGRESSIVE JOHN ALWAYS INSISTED THAT EVERY PART
OF THE COMMUNITY THE ELDERLY CHILDREN, FAMILIES BE
CONSIDERED IN ALL SORT OF MARKET PLANNING.
AND HE AND THE COMMITTEE WERE RIGHT HENCE IN ADDITION TO THE
CUSTOMARY CONVENTION FACILITIES ,MOSCONE CENTER IS THE ONLY
CONVENTION CENTER IN AMERICA THAT INCLUDES A WONDERFUL MERRY
GO AROUND FOR CHILDREN, A SUPERB INDOOR ICE SKATING
FACILITY FOR SAN FRANCISCO YOUTH AND ADULTS.
AS JOHN CONTINUED TO GROW INTO A TOP TIER LOW INCOME
AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPER, HE INVENTED NEW
STRATEGIES TO SUPPORT TACKLE AIMS AND OBJECTIVES.
JOHN CONVINCED US DISTRICT STREET'S REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT
REFLECTED THE POWER OF COMMUNITY VISION FOR OUR CITY
AND THE SOUND MARKET IN PARTICULAR.
AND HE WAS RIGHT. THE PROJECT HAS REVERSE THE
HISTORICAL DISPLACEMENT OF REDEVELOPMENT AND PROVED TO BE
ONE OF THE BEST IN OUR CITY WITH ATTRACTIVE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING, COMMUNITY CENTERS, PARKS AND A SCHOOL.
JOHN WAS NEVER AFRAID TO SPEAK THE TRUTH TO POWER AND THIS IS
WHAT I SAY AS A SUPERVISOR AND WHO HAS WORKED WITH HIM AS
A LEGISLATIVE AIDE AND ALSO THEN AGAIN AS SUPERVISOR.
I SAY THAT JOHN WAS NEVER AFRAID TO SPEAK TRUTH TO POWER
AND THE CRITICS THAT CALL HIM A POWER BROKER KINGMAKER OR
OBSTRUCTIONIST REMINDS ME THE SAME WAY THAT PEOPLE COULD
CRITICIZE ROSE PAC SAME JOHN AL BURLING.
EVERYTHING THAT HE DID WAS TO EMPOWER THE COMMUNITY.
HE BELIEVE IN A CITY THAT IS SUPPORTED BY EVERYDAY WORKING
CLASS PEOPLE. HE DID NOT LIVE IN A LIFE OF
LUXURY AND CHOSE TO REINVEST EVERY PENNY INTO COMMUNITY FUND
WAYS TO UPLIFT TENANTS VOICES AND TO COMPETE WITH AND REFUTE
MORE TIME MILLION DOLLAR SPECIAL INTEREST POLITICAL
MESSAGING. AND SO FOR THAT I SAY JOHN
ALBERT KING REST IN POWER. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. I ALSO WANT TO EXPRESS MY DEEP
CONDOLENCES FOR THE PASSING OF JOHN KING.
I DIDN'T KNOW JOHN PERSONALLY BUT I DO KNOW THAT HIS
CONTRIBUTION TO COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT, AFFORDABLE HOUSING
AND ANTI DISPLACEMENT WAR IN SAN FRANCISCO IS
CONSIDERABLE. MANY PROJECTS IN SAN FRANCISCO
HAS BEEN TRANSFORMED IT FOR THE BETTER BECAUSE OF HIS ADVOCACY
. SAN FRANCISCO TAKES PRIDE
IN THE LEGACY OF OUR COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT MOVEMENTS AND THIS
WEEK WE LOST A COMMUNITY WARRIOR.
NEXT I WANT TO INTRODUCE TWO HEARINGS COLLEAGUE.
>> LAST MONTH I HELD A HEARING ON THE CONDITIONS FOR WOMEN
IN CUSTODY OF SAN FRANCISCO JAILS.
THE COMMUNITY TEST TESTIMONY WAS INCREDIBLY POWERFUL BUT
ALSO VERY HARD TO STOMACH. >> COUNTLESS FORMERLY
INCARCERATED WOMEN RECOUNTED THE ELEVATED EXPERIENCES IN THE
JAILS. THEY DETAILED MEMORIES OF
TRAUMA AND ABUSE. MANY WOMEN IN PARTICULAR I SAID
THAT THEY WERE RELEASED FROM THE JOUST AT HOURS AFTER
EVENING SOMETIMES AS EARLY AS 2 A.M. WITHOUT CLOTHING
CONNECTIONS TO A SAFE PLACE TO SLEEP OR ACCESS TO A WRAP
AROUND SERVICES NEEDED TO KEEP THEM STABILIZED IN THEIR
TRANSITIONS. FOR MANY THIS MEANS BEING
RELEASED BACK TO AN ABUSER'S. WE ALSO HEARD STORIES OF WOMEN
BEING RELEASED FROM HOSPITALS AND OTHER FACILITIES WITHOUT
CONNECTION TO SAFE TO A SAFE SHELTER.
THIS IS UNACCEPTABLE. SAN FRANCISCANS DESERVE PUBLIC
SAFETY AND SYSTEM THAT ADHESIVE TO MINIMUM STANDARDS OF HUMANE
CARE. I'M CALLING FOR A HEARING ON
THE SYSTEMS AND CASE MANAGEMENT THAT OUR CITY PROVIDES TO
AND HOW STATE HOUSING INSECURE WOMEN.
I'M GRATEFUL THAT MAYOR HAS SIGNED ON TO THEM.
THE WOMAN'S AGENDA BUT WE NEED TO DO MORE.
WHEN WE KNOW THAT WOMEN ARE MORE LIKELY TO EXPERIENCE ABUSE
ESPECIALLY WHEN UNHOUSED IT WOMEN CARRY THEIR OWN COMPLEX
NEEDS AROUND SAFETY, MENTAL, BEHAVIORAL AND PHYSICAL HEALTH
AND MORE AND WOMAN EXPERIENCES AN ARRAY OF TRAUMA AT DIFFERENT
LEVELS OF A CITY AND IT'S OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO ANALYZE IF
THE SYSTEMS THAT WE PUT IN PLACE ARE FLEXIBLE
AND ROBUST ENOUGH TO PROVIDE THE DIGNITY, SERVICES
AND SAFETY REQUIRED. >> WE NEED TO UNDERSTAND THE
SHELTER SYSTEM AND THE POLICIES THAT ARE THAT ARE SET IN PLACE
BY THE DEPARTMENT THAT RELEASE OR TRANSITION WOMEN FROM CITY
HOLDS. WE ALSO NEED TO UNDERSTAND THE
SHELTER SYSTEM AS A WHOLE WHERE THERE ARE CHALLENGES, WHERE WE
ARE SUCCEEDING TO CONNECT WOMEN TO SAFE SPACES AND WE AND WHERE
WE NEED TO EXPEND. >> NEXT I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A
HEARING ON FAMILY AFFORDABILITY .
WE ARE FACING A MASSIVE STRUCTURAL DEFICIT
AND DIFFICULT DECISION NEEDED TO BE MADE.
AT THE SAME TIME FAMILIES HAVE BEEN SOUNDING THE ALARM ABOUT
HOW UNSUSTAINABLE THEIR FAMILY BUDGETING DECISIONS HAVE BEEN
BECOME. FOR ME OUR VALUES ARE BEST
REPRESENTED BY THE BUDGET COMMITMENTS WE MAKE
AND SERVICES THAT WE PROVIDE TO THE WORKING FAMILY AND ABOUT
AND VOLUNTEER WHOLE POPULATION THAT MAKES SAN FRANCISCO RUN
AND ENDURE INCREDIBLE HARDSHIP TO SURVIVE IN OUR CITY.
THIS HEARING WILL ADJUST TWO THINGS FIRST, WE WILL ANALYZE
THE IMPACT OF PROPOSED BUDGET CUTS FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF
HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT ON VULNERABLE
COMMUNITIES INCLUDING LOW INCOME INDIVIDUALS
AND IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES. SIX.
SECOND, IT WILL CONSIDER THE ROLE THAT COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATION HAVE PLAYED IN MAINTAINING HOUSING
STABILITY. WORKFORCE PARTICIPATION
AND ACCESS TO ESSENTIAL SERVICES.
I RECOGNIZE THIS PROPOSAL CUTS AND SET IN STONE BUT WHAT
KURNIA ON THE TABLE WILL ESSENTIALLY LONG-LASTING
ORGANIZE ASIAN WHO PROVIDE ESSENTIAL WORK TO FIGHT AGAINST
IT. THAT THIS PLACEMENT OF
COMMUNITY OF COLOR AND WORKING FAMILY CBOS OUR COURT TO OUR
SOCIAL SAFETY NET THE CASE MANAGEMENT AND CONNECTION TO
SERVICES HAS PROTECTED COUNTIES, FAMILY
AND COMMUNITIES FROM BEING PUSHED INTO HOMELESSNESS OR
FORCED OUT OF OUR CITY. AND EACH BUDGET YEAR WE ASK
CBOS TO DO MORE WORK FOR LESS MONEY.
NOW WE ARE CUTTING THEIR BUDGETS AT A TIME WHEN WORKING
FAMILIES RELY ON THE MOST AT A TIME WHEN WORKING FAMILIES RELY
ON THEM MOST. AND THIS WILL FORCE MULTIPLE
CBO CLOSURES AT A TIME WHEN WE ARE FACING UNRELIABLE STATE
AND FEDERAL SUPPORT. DISCUSSION THIS DISCUSSION WILL
BE DIFFICULT BUT IT IS NECESSARY.
AND THE REST I WILL SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO PROHIBIT THE SALE AND DELIVERY
OF UNCERTIFIED LITHIUM ION BATTERIES AND POWERED MOBILITY
DEVICES IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THIS MEASURE IS INTENDED TO PREVENT DANGEROUS AND FAST
MOVING FIRES BEFORE THEY START PARTICULARLY IN DENSE
RESIDENTIAL BUILDINGS WHERE A SINGLE BATTERY FAILURE CAN
THREATEN DOZENS OF RESIDENTS. >> WE HAVE SEEN FIRSTHAND THE
CONSEQUENCES OF THESE INCIDENTS.
THE RECENT FIRE AT 50 GOLDEN GATE DISPLACED MORE THAN 130
RESIDENTS AND REQUIRED A LARGE EMERGENCY RESPONSE.
FIRES LIKE THIS SPREAD QUICKLY PRODUCE INTENSE HEAT AND ARE
EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO EXTINGUISH.
>> BUT THESE INCIDENTS ARE NOT ISOLATED.
>> LITHIUM ION BATTERY FIRES ARE INCREASING ACROSS THE CITY
WHERE THERE WERE OVER 120 BUILDING FIRES IN THE LAST FIVE
YEARS CAUSED BY LITHIUM ION BATTERIES AND WITH A
SIGNIFICANT CONCENTRATION IN DISTRICT FIVE IN THE
TENDERLOIN WHERE RESIDENTS OFTEN LIVE IN MULTI-UNIT
HOUSING WITH LIMITED FIRE SEPARATION.
>> ACCORDING TO THE FIRE DEPARTMENT, MANY OF THESE FIRES
ORIGINATE FROM UNCERTIFIED REPLACEMENT BATTERIES USED
IN E-BIKES SCOOTERS AND OTHER POWERED MOBILITY DEVICES OFTEN
PURCHASED ONLINE AND STORED OR CHARGED INSIDE SMALL LIVING
SPACES. THIS ORDINANCE TAKES A
PREVENTATIVE APPROACH. IT PROHIBITS THE SALE OFFER OR
DELIVERY OF POWER MOBILITY DEVICES AND REPLACEMENT LITHIUM
ION BATTERIES THAT ARE NOT CERTIFIED TO RECOGNIZE YOU ALL
SAFETY STANDARDS. OUR CODE SHOULD KEEP UP WITH
THE STATE OF TECHNOLOGY. ANYONE IN SAN FRANCISCO
SHOULDN'T HAVE TO BE WORRIED ABOUT PURCHASING UNSAFE
BATTERIES OR BEING DISPLACED BY A FIRE DUE TO A NEIGHBOR
CHARGING ONE OF THESE. THEY SHOULD TRUST THAT THEY ARE
PURCHASING SAFE AND CERTIFIED BATTERIES.
IT ALSO GIVES THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT CLEAR AUTHORITY
TO ENFORCE THIS LAW AND INCLUDES THE ABILITY TO
ISSUE CITATIONS AND PENALTIES FOR VIOLATIONS ENSURING
ACCOUNTABILITY. IT ALSO GIVES THAT AUTHORITY TO
THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE TO GO AFTER BAD ACTORS THAT MAY BE
VIOLATING THE SAME LAW AS WELL BY ENSURING ONLY CERTIFIED
BATTERIES ARE SOLD IN SAN FRANCISCO, WE CAN SIGNIFICANTLY
REDUCE THE RISK OF CATASTROPHIC FIRES AND PROTECT TENANTS,
FIRST RESPONDERS AND SURROUNDING BUILDINGS.
>> I WANT TO THANK OUR DRAFTING OF CITY ATTORNEYS HUGO HERRERA
AND SARAH FABIAN FOR THEIR THOUGHTFUL COLLABORATION AND I
WANT TO THANK OUR PARTNERS AT THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
DEPARTMENT FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP AND EXPERTISE INCLUDING CHIEF
DAN CRISPIN, FIRE MARSHAL LAW ASSISTANT FIRE MARSHAL GOWER
AND ADRIAN SIMS. THEIR INSIGHT INTO HOW THESE
FIRES START, HOW THEY SPREAD AND HOW THEY IMPACT RESIDENTS
AND FIREFIGHTERS WAS CRITICAL IN SHAPING A POLICY THAT IS
BOTH PRACTICAL AND ENFORCEABLE .
I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY CHIEF OF STAFF SAM LOGAN FOR HER
DILIGENCE ON THIS ISSUE AND FOR HELPING SHAPE THIS LEGISLATION.
>> THIS PROPOSAL WILL HELP PREVENT DISPLACEMENT, PROTECT
RESIDENTS AND ADDRESS A GROWING FIRE SAFETY RISK BEFORE ANOTHER
BUILDING IS IMPACTED. I WANT TO THANK THE WORDS OF
CHERYL FOR HIS EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AND RESPECTFULLY
SUBMIT THIS ORDINANCE AND ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I AM TODAY
SUBMITTING A HEARING REQUEST TO ADDRESS ONGOING POLICE STAFFING
CHALLENGES IN THE SOUTHERN POLICE DISTRICT.
SIMPLY STATED SOUTHERN IS NOT STAFFED AT LEVELS THAT REFLECT
ITS WORKLOAD OR ITS COMPLEXITY WHEN SCRUTINIZING POLICE CALL
VOLUME RESPONSE TIMES POPULATION DENSITY AND THE
CONCENTRATION OF COMMERCIAL AND NIGHTLIFE ACTIVITIES.
AS MANY OF MY CONSTITUENTS ROUTINELY, ROUTINELY, ROUTINELY
DO. IT HAS BECOME EVIDENT THAT
SOUTHERN IS STRETCHED FAR TOO THIN.
FAR TOO OFTEN EVEN AS SFPD IS CITYWIDE RECOMMENDED STAFFING
LEVELS SOAR SIGNIFICANT INCREASES THIS LAST YEAR.
SOUTHERN IS FAILING TO KEEP PACE WITH OTHER DISTRICTS THAT
FACE SIMILAR AND IN MANY CASES LESSER DEMANDS.
ACCORDING TO THE 2025 S.F. P.D. STAFFING ANALYSIS, SOUTHERN
PATROL OFFICERS RESPOND TO 390 CALLS PER OFFICER THE SECOND
HIGHEST WORKLOAD IN THE CITY AND ITS SECTOR PATROL IS
CURRENTLY STAFFED AT ONLY 78% OF ITS RECOMMENDED LEVEL.
WHILE OTHER DISTRICTS MEET OR EVEN EXCEED THEIR RECOMMENDED
NUMBER, THIS IMBALANCE HAS REAL CONSEQUENCES.
IT MEANS LONGER RESPONSE TIMES ,FEWER OPPORTUNITIES FOR
PROACTIVE POLICING INCREASED STRAIN ON THE OFFICERS WHO ARE
ASSIGNED THERE KNOW PUBLIC SAFETY IMPERATIVE WHETHER IT'S
POLICE POLICING, DRUG MARKETS RESPONDING TO VIOLENT CRIME OR
ENFORCING TRAFFIC LAWS IS WELL-SERVED BY AN UNDERSTAFFED
STATION. IT ALSO MAKES MORE DIFFICULT TO
BUILD THE KIND OF CONSISTENT COMMUNITY BASED PRESENCE THAT
RESIDENTS AND BUSINESSES IN DISTRICT SIX EXPECT
AND DESERVE. MANY OF MY CONSTITUENTS ARE
VOICING SERIOUS CONCERNS TOO THAT THE EXISTING CHALLENGES
WILL BE EXACERBATED LATER THIS YEAR WHEN SOUTHERN POLICE
DISTRICT EXPANDS TO TAKE ON EVEN MORE TERRITORY THAT
INCLUDES MARKET STREET. DURING THE POLICE REDISTRICTING
PROCESS I WAS CLEAR THAT THE COMMUNITY AND DEPARTMENT HAVE
EXPECTATIONS THAT INCREASED CALL VOLUMES WILL COME WITH
COMMENSURATE INCREASE IN ADDITIONAL OFFICERS.
DISTRICT SIX STAKEHOLDERS DESERVE TRANSPARENCY ABOUT S.F.
PD'S PLAN TO NOT ONLY INCREASE STAFFING TO MEET THE NEW
WORKLOAD BUT ALSO TO ADDRESS SYSTEMIC UNDERSTAFFING THAT HAS
PLAGUED THIS DISTRICT BEFORE ITS BOUNDARIES WERE EXPANDED TO
INCLUDE THE MARKET STREET CORRIDOR.
EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD DESERVES A LEVEL OF POLICE SERVICE THAT
MATCHES ITS NEEDS AND I YIELD TO NO ONE IN THE WORK THAT I
HAVE DONE MUCH OF IT UNSUCCESSFUL TO INCREASE POLICE
STAFFING CITYWIDE. BUT RIGHT NOW I DON'T BELIEVE
SOUTHERN IS GETTING THE LEVEL OF SERVICE COMMENSURATE WITH
ITS NEEDS. I'M COMMITTED TO WORKING WITH
THE DEPARTMENT AND OTHERS TO DEVELOP A STRATEGY THAT CLOSES
THAT GAP IN A MEANINGFUL AND LASTING WAY.
MY CONSTITUENTS DESERVE NOTHING LESS.
SECOND, I ALSO WANT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO PRESIDENT
MANDELL FOR HIS BEAUTIFUL IN MEMORIAM FOR ANDRE SHORTER.
THERE ARE SO MANY LGBTQ PLUS SIBLINGS I RECALL FONDLY
THROUGHOUT THE YEARS BUT ESPECIALLY DURING THE NINE YEAR
LEGAL BATTLE FOR MARRIAGE EQUALITY.
THAT WAS A ROLLER COASTER RIDE THAT BEGAN IN 2004 WITH
MAYOR GAVIN NEWSOM'S ISSUANCE OF MARRIAGE LICENSES TO SAME
SEX COUPLES. IT INCLUDED MANY WINS
AND LOSSES INCLUDING WINNING MARRIAGE EQUALITY RIGHTS TO
THEMSELVES ONLY TO LOSE IT JUST MONTHS LATER WITH PROPOSITION
EIGHT AND THEN YEARS LATER TO FINALLY STRIKE DOWN PROP EIGHT
AND SET THE STAGE FOR MARRIAGE EQUALITY NATIONWIDE.
THESE ARE BATTLES THAT WERE PARTICULARLY EMOTIONALLY
FRAUGHT FOR THOSE OF US WHOSE OWN RIGHTS WERE AT STAKE
IN THESE CASES. AND THROUGH IT ALL I WILL NEVER
FORGET THAT WE SUPPORTED AND SUSTAINED ONE ANOTHER
AND I'LL NEVER FORGET ANDREA SHORTER.
MY CONDOLENCES TO HER AND HER HER FAMILY AND LOVED ONES
AND FRIENDS AND I WOULD ASK TO BE INCLUDED AMONG THOSE
MEMORIALIZING HER. AND THIRD AND FINALLY, I WOULD
ALSO LIKE TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO SUPERVISOR CHAN
FOR HER LOVELY MEMORIAL FOR JOHN ALBERT KING.
ALTHOUGH OTHERS KNEW HIM BETTER THAN I DID, I WOULD BE REMISS
AS THE DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR NOT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE OUTSIZED
ROLE JOHN OBERLIN PLAYED IN SHAPING NEIGHBORHOODS I
REPRESENT AND FAR MORE IMPORTANTLY SERVING RESIDENTS
AND FAMILIES. I REPRESENT COUNTLESS HUNDREDS
OF HOMES LIKELY WOULD NOT BE MY CONSTITUENTS TODAY BUT FOR THE
PASSIONATE ADVOCACY THAT WAS JOHN ALBERT LING'S LIFE WORK AS
A DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR I HAVE COME TO APPRECIATE TODD
COE FOR BEING WELL-MANAGED AND FORGING COOPERATIVE
RELATIONSHIPS WITH WITH ITS NEIGHBORS.
I HAVE ALSO COME TO KNOW MANY TODD COE RESIDENTS AS FRIENDS,
NEIGHBORS AND FELLOW PARISHIONERS AT ST PATRICK'S
CHURCH. I THINK OUR FORMER COLLEAGUE
AARON PESKIN SAID IT BEST WHEN HE CALLED JOHN THE CONSCIENCE
OF YERBA BUENA AND ON THE OCCASIONS I HAD TO TALK WITH
HIM I TOO VALUED HIS COMMITMENT TO SOCIAL JUSTICE AND TO
ENSURING THAT HIS RESIDENTS WERE ALWAYS WELL SERVED.
IN HIS UNMATCHED INSTITUTIONAL MEMORY ABOUT SAN FRANCISCO, ITS
POLITICS NOT JUST YERBA BUENO BY THE WAY, BUT ALSO TREASURE
ISLAND. SO MY CONDOLENCES TO JOHN
ALBERT LING'S FAMILY MEMBERS AND LOVED ONES AND I WOULD ASK
TO BE INCLUDED AMONG THOSE MEMORIALIZING HIM AS WELL.
>> AND THE REST I SUBMIT NOTED. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR DORSEY MR. PRESIDENT SAYING NO NAMES
ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW
BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK AND I
WOULD ALSO LIKE TO BE ADDED TO THAT JOHN L BURLING AND NOTED
THANK YOU WAS A IDEA FACTORY RELENTLESS IN HIS EFFORT TO
FIND SOURCES FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND TO PUSH THE CITY TO
PRODUCE HOUSING FOR FOUR FOR ALL OF OUR RESIDENTS SO THANK
YOU MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER THE 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER ITEMS 31 THROUGH 34 COMPRISE
THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE DE FACTO
DENIAL OF A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR THE PROPOSED
PROJECT AT 524 THROUGH 526 VALLEJO STREET AND FOUR DASH
FOR A SAN ANTONIO PLACE TO LEGALIZE THE MERGER OF THREE
DWELLING UNITS ON SECOND AND THIRD FLOORS INTO ONE
DWELLING UNIT AND TO REINSTATE ONE DWELLING UNIT ON THE GROUND
FLOOR WITHIN AN EXISTING FOUR UNIT RESIDENTIAL BUILDING
LOCATED WITHIN RM-1 ZONING DISTRICT TELEGRAPH HILL NORTH
BEACH RESIDENTIAL AS SEWARD'S SPECIAL USE DISTRICT THE
PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHICS AS SUCH AND 40 X HEIGHT AND BULK
DISTRICT ITEM 32 THAT IS THE MOTION TO APPROVE THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DECISION TO DE FACTO DENY THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION. ITEM 33 IS THE MOTION TO
DISAPPROVE THE COMMISSION'S DECISION THAT WOULD BE TO A TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS WHICH ARE THE SUBJECT MATTER OF
ITEM 34 WHICH IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF
FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THE BOARD'S DECISION CONCERNING THE
SIU AUTHORIZATION. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
AS YOU DESCRIBED WE HAVE BEFORE US A HEARING ON THE APPEAL THE
DE FACTO DENIAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 524 TO 526 VALLEJO STREET AND 4-442
FOR A SAN ANTONIO PLACE. AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD
WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO APPROVE OR DISAPPROVE THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DE FACTO DENIAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT.
SINCE THE APPELLANT IS ALSO THE PROJECT SPONSOR, WE WILL HEAR
FROM THE APPELLANTS AT THE BEGINNING OF THE HEARING
AND UNLESS THERE ARE OBJECTIONS WE'RE GOING TO PROCEED AS
FOLLOWS. WE'RE GOING TO GIVE UP TO TEN
MINUTES TO THE APPELLANT FOR THEIR PRESENTATION AND THEN
WE'RE GOING TO HEAR PUBLIC COMMENT UP TO TWO MINUTES PER
SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL.
THEN WE WILL GIVE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT UP TO TEN MINUTES
FOR THEIR PRESENTATION. THEN WE WILL HEAR PUBLIC
COMMENT IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL AGAIN UP TO TWO MINUTES
PER SPEAKER. THEN FINALLY WE'LL GO BACK TO
THE APPELLANTS FOR UP TO THREE MINUTES OF REBUTTAL UNLESS
THEIR OBJECTIONS SUPERVISOR SLATER'S IN THE QUEUE BUT I
DON'T THINK HE'S OBJECTING TO THAT METHOD.
>> MAY IT MATTER OF PROCEEDING SO SINCE THERE ARE NO
OBJECTIONS THE PUBLIC HEARING WILL PROCEED AS INDICATED
AND IS NOW OPEN. >> AND SUPERVISOR SAUDER, THANK
YOU PRESIDENT VANDEMAN YOU KNOW THIS PROPERTY SITS ATOP
TELEGRAPH HILL IN MY DISTRICT AND IT IS A COMPLEX ONE AS I
THINK WE'LL FIND OUT. SO BEFORE WE BEGIN THE
PROCEEDINGS I WANTED TO BRIEFLY SHARE SOME BACKGROUND AND LAY
OUT SOME FACTS. I FIRST WANT TO EMPHASIZE WHY
THIS IS BEFORE US. IT IS BECAUSE THE PLANNING
COMMISSION WRESTLED IMMENSELY WITH THIS PROJECT.
IT WAS A TIE VOTE 3 TO 3 WHICH MEANS IT IS DE FACTO DENIED.
AND WHY IT IS BEFORE US TODAY FOUR DIFFERENT COMMISSIONERS
IN THAT MEETING USED THE EXACT SAME WORD TRAGIC TO DESCRIBE
THE SITUATION TO THE FAMILY BEFORE US TODAY.
>> THEY SAID THE SITUATION WAS QUOTE NOT FAIR AND THAT THEY
ARE THE VICTIM TWICE REMOVED AND THAT THEY ARE NOT AT FAULT
HERE. ONE COMMISSIONER SAID THAT THE
CASE HAD THEM PARTICULARLY SICK .
ONE COMMISSIONER EVEN SUGGESTED THIS CASE HAD HER RECONSIDERING
HER SERVICE ON THE PLANNING COMMISSION ITSELF.
SHE SAID QUOTE I CANNOT CONTINUE TO SIT HERE
AND REFLECT ON OTHER PEOPLE'S DESTINY, DISAPPOINTMENT
AND DESTRUCTION OF DREAMS WHEN WE NEED TO PUT THE BRAKES ON
EARLIER. I'M EXHAUSTED.
I AM HURT. I AM DISAPPOINTED.
AND THAT SAME COMMISSIONER SAID THAT QUOTE THIS ISSUE SHOULD
NOT BE CONSIDERED BY US AND POINTED FINGERS ELSEWHERE.
COMMISSIONERS EXPRESSED THAT WE SHOULD BE SPENDING OUR TIME
GOING AGAINST THE DEVELOPER THE REAL BAD ACTOR HERE.
TWO OWNERS AGO WHO GOT EVERYONE INTO THIS MESS.
ONE SAID AT BEST QUOTE OUR HANDS ARE TIED.
HERE'S WHAT ALL OF THAT MEANS. IT MEANS THAT THE PLANNING
COMMISSION WAS DESPERATELY LOOKING FOR SOMEONE ELSE TO
MAKE THE RIGHT DECISION HERE. AND THAT IS NOW THE OPPORTUNITY
THAT WE HAVE AS A BOARD. IT IS OUR JOB AS SUPERVISORS TO
NOT ONLY CONSIDER THE CODE BUT ALSO CONSIDER OUR CONSTITUENTS
AND HOW THEY ARE IMPACTED BY THE CODE.
WHEN THE CODE DOES NOT WORK THE WAY WE HOPE AND EXPECT IT WILL
SOME BRIEF FACTS TO KEEP IN MIND AS WE PREPARE TO HEAR
FROM THE APPELLANTS AND PLANNING TODAY.
WE'RE NOT HERE TODAY BECAUSE OF ANY ACTIVATIONS, NOT BECAUSE OF
ANY DANGER, NOT BECAUSE OF ANY BUILDING VIOLATION FROM THESE
OWNERS. WE ARE HERE TODAY SOLELY
BECAUSE A FEW YEARS AGO AN ANONYMOUS NEIGHBOR MADE A
COMPLAINT ABOUT ACTIONS THAT HAPPENED UNDER THE DIRECTION OF
SOMEONE WHO OWNED THIS HOME IN 2010.
>> THAT SOMEONE IS NOT HERE. THEY'RE OFF THE HOOK.
AND YET WE'RE ALL HERE TO TRY AND CLEAN UP THE MESS.
SOME BASIC FACTS ABOUT THIS BUILDING AND PROPERTY THE
STRUCTURE WAS BUILT IN 1909 AS A TWO UNIT HOME.
WE'RE GOING TO HEAR ABOUT FOUR UNITS TODAY.
BUT IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THE FOUR UNITS DO NOT EXIST TODAY.
AND IT'S UNCLEAR IF FOR CODE COMPLIANT UNITS HAVE EVER TRULY
EXISTED HERE. AND AS FOR THE FAMILY, THERE
HAVE NEVER BEEN FOUR UNITS THREE UNITS OR TWO UNITS UNDER
THIS FAMILY'S OWNERSHIP. >> THE MERGER FROM TWO OWNERS
AGO INCLUDED TWO UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNITS OR YOU TWO USE.
IT'S UNCLEAR FOR CODE COMPLIANT UNITS HAVE EVER ACTUALLY
PHYSICALLY EXISTED IN THIS BUILDING OVER ITS 119 YEARS
STANDING. THE TWO YOU TWO USE REFERENCED
IN 2010 LISTING WERE REFERENCED IN A 2010 LISTING SAYING THAT
TOILETS FOR THOSE UNITS WERE LOCATED OUTSIDE THE UNIT IN A
BACKYARD SHED. THEY SHARED A KITCHEN AND THAT
THERE WERE NO WRITTEN LEASES. THE MERGER IN QUESTION HAPPENED
UNDER A PREVIOUS OWNER IN THE EARLY 20 TENS.
THAT PREVIOUS OWNER IS A SERIAL VICTOR AND IS FLOUTED THE RULES
FOR DECADES. HE IS THE TRUE BAD ACTOR HERE
AND I WISH WE WOULD PUT OUR RESOURCES TOWARDS HOLDING HIM
RESPONSIBLE. A FAMILY BEFORE US HAS NO
CONNECTION TO THAT DEVELOPMENT, TO THAT DEVELOPER OR THE MERGER
. THE PROPERTY WAS SOLD TO
SOMEONE ELSE BEFORE THE FAMILY FOR A FIVE YEAR PERIOD AND THEN
IT WAS SOLD TO THIS FAMILY. SO TO SUMMARIZE WHAT'S BEFORE
US TODAY IS A FAMILY OF FOUR ASKING FOR APPROVAL TO ADD A
NEW UNIT OF HOUSING. THEY'RE NOT ASKING TO CONVERT A
HOME. THAT ACTION WAS TAKEN TO OWNERS
AGO. THEY'RE NOT ASKING TO GET OFF
WITHOUT TAKING ANY RESPONSIBILITY.
SO ANYTHING WE WEIGH TODAY COMES WITH IMMENSE WORK AND A
PRICE TAG IN THE MILLION DOLLAR PLUS RANGE.
THEY'RE ASKING TO RETURN THEIR HOME TO WHAT IT WAS FOR THE
VAST MAJORITY OF ITS ENTIRE HISTORY.
A TWO UNIT HOME. AND I THINK I'LL LEAVE IT THERE
FOR NOW AND LET THE PROCEEDINGS BEGIN.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT, FOR. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
OH, LET'S HEAR FROM THE APPELLANTS FOR UP TO TEN
MINUTES. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
>> MY NAME IS CAITLIN HOLLOWAY AND THAT'S MY HUSBAND BEN
RAMIREZ. WE ARE THE HOMEOWNERS AT 524
VALLEJO STREET. BEFORE WE BEGIN, WE WANT TO
THANK THE MEMBERS OF THIS BOARD AND YOUR STAFF FOR WHO HAVE
TAKEN THE TIME TO MEET WITH US TO BETTER UNDERSTAND THE
DETAILS OF THIS CASE. WE ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT. WE APPRECIATE THE EFFORT THEY
PUT INTO THIS PROCESS. I WANT TO START BY SAYING
SOMETHING THAT I FEAR ISN'T OBVIOUS.
WE ARE NOT HERE IN OPPOSITION OF THE CITY TO HOUSING POLICY
OR TO THE GOALS THAT MANY OF YOU ARE WORKING TOWARDS.
BEN AND I SHARE IN THESE GOALS. WE HAVE SUPPORTED THEM AS
MEMBERS OF THIS COMMUNITY FOR MANY YEARS AND WE COME HERE
TODAY AS PARTNERS IN THIS CONVERSATION NOT AS ADVERSARIES
. WE ARE HERE BECAUSE THE
SITUATION COULD NOT BE FULLY RESOLVED THROUGH A STANDARD
PROCESS. A 3 TO 3 TIE VOTE AT THE
PLANNING COMMISSION LED TO A DE FACTO DENIAL.
DEMONSTRATING THE COMPLEXITY OF THIS CASE A LARGE PART OF THE
CONTENTION HERE IS BECAUSE THIS CASE HAS BEEN REDUCED TO A
DECISION ON MERGING UNITS. THAT FRAMING IS INCOMPLETE
AND FOR THOSE THAT HAVE READ THE FACTS LEADS TO A VERY
CONFLICTED POSITION DRIVE BLINDLY FOR A CITY MANDATE THAT
I SUPPORT OR DO I VOTE WITH THE FACTS A SET OF FACTS OF
INDIVIDUAL CASE THAT MAY NOT LEAD TO THE CONCLUSION I WANT.
>> I BELIEVE A MORE NUANCED FRAMING OF THAT DECISION TODAY
WILL ALLOW US TO BETTER ASSESS THE APPROPRIATE PATH FORWARD.
THIS IS NOT A CASE ABOUT REMOVING HOUSING.
THIS IS A CASE ABOUT A FOUR UNIT DESIGNATION THAT WAS NEVER
LAWFULLY GRANTED WAS NEVER PHYSICALLY BUILT AND CANNOT BE
FEASIBLY CONSTRUCTED UNDER THE CURRENT CODE.
THIS IS ALSO A CASE ABOUT ACCOUNTABILITY.
WHETHER THE CITY WILL CONTINUE TO ENFORCE THAT DESIGNATION AT
THE EXPENSE OF A FAMILY OR FIND A PROPORTIONAL PATH FORWARD.
>> OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS WE HAVE WORKED WITH THE CITY
THROUGH THIS PROCESS TRANSPARENTLY IN GOOD FAITH
AND THROUGH THE PROPER CHANNELS WHEN FRAMED STRICTLY AS A
POLICY ISSUE IT PUTS EVERYONE IN THIS ROOM ON THE DEFENSE BUT
FRAMED AS A CONVERSATION ABOUT ACCOUNTABILITY.
WE'RE ABLE TO HAVE AN APPROPRIATE DIALOG ABOUT REMEDY
. AND SO THROUGH THESE YEARS WHAT
WE'VE ULTIMATELY UNCOVERED IS THIS THE FOUR UNIT PERMIT AT
THE CENTER OF THIS CASE SHOULD NEVER HAVE BEEN ISSUED AS THE
UNITS IT AUTHORIZED WERE PHYSICALLY NEVER CONSTRUCTED.
WHAT WE ARE ASKING FOR IS A RESOLUTION THAT REFLECTS THE
REALITY OF WHAT EXISTS ACKNOWLEDGES HOW WE GOT HERE
AND DOES NOT RESULT IN THE PERMANENT DISPLACEMENT OF OUR
FAMILY. WITH THAT AS CONTEXT, HERE'S
WHAT THE RECORD ACTUALLY SHOWS. BUILT IN 1907, THIS BUILDING
FUNCTIONED AS A TWO UNIT PROPERTY FOR NEARLY 80 YEARS.
IN THE MID 1980S TWO UNAUTHORIZED UNITS WERE ADDED
AT THE REAR OF THE HOME. IN 2010 DEVELOPER PETER
ISKANDER PURCHASED THE PROPERTY .
IN 2012, DUBAI'S OWN RECORD MANAGEMENT DIVISION REVIEWED IT
AND ISSUED A WRITTEN DETERMINATION LEGALLY TWO UNIT
BUILDING. THAT SAME YEAR A ZONING REVIEW
NOTED NO CHANGE TO UNIT COUNT. ODDLY, EIGHT WEEKS LATER WITH
NO NEW APPLICATION, NO PUBLIC HEARING TO EXPAND THE UNIT
COUNT, GBI ISSUED A PERMIT FOR A FOUR UNIT BUILDING AT THE
REQUEST OF THE DEVELOPER. THIS FOUR UNIT APPROVAL SITS AT
THE VERY CENTER OF THIS ENTIRE CASE.
THE ARCHITECTURAL AND STRUCTURAL EVIDENCE ALONG
WITH THE CITY'S OWN PERMIT RECORDS OVERWHELMINGLY SHOWS
THAT THE FOUR UNIT LAYOUT IN THOSE APPROVED PLANS WERE
NEVER ACTUALLY CONSTRUCTED. DESPITE THE PAPER DESIGNATION
OF FOUR UNITS, THE BUILDING WAS COMPLETED WITH ONE KITCHEN
AND A CONTIGUOUS LAYOUT. AND HAS FUNCTIONED AS A SINGLE
FAMILY HOME FROM THAT POINT FORWARD.
DESPITE THIS FACT DEBATE ISSUED IN 2016 THE CERTIFICATE OF
FINAL COMPLETION IN ACCEPTING THE BUILDING IN IS AS BUILT
CONDITION NOT IN ITS APPROVED ON PAPER CONDITION IN ITS AS
BUILT CONDITION AND THAT CONDITION DID NOT REFLECT A
FOUR UNIT APARTMENT BUILDING A GAPING HOLE CONNECTING TWO
UNITS WITH AN OPEN FLOATING STAIRS A SHOWER BUILT IN PLACE
OF AN ELEVATOR SHAFT, A STAIRWELL BUILT IN REVERSE
CONFIGURATION AND YET NO VIOLATIONS AND NO DEVIATION FOR
PLAN WERE NOTED. AT THIS POINT THE HOME WAS
AND LISTED FOR SALE BY THE DEVELOPER ACROSS SEVERAL MLS
REAL ESTATE LISTING PAGES AS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME.
THE MISALIGNED STRUCTURAL COMPONENTS CLEARLY PHOTOGRAPHED
AND DOCUMENTED AND THEN ALMOST A FULL YEAR AFTER THE PUBLIC
LISTINGS WERE PUBLISHED ADVANCED PACHTER CONDUCTED FIVE
FINAL INSPECTIONS ON THE PROPERTY TOP TO BOTTOM.
SAME CONDITION, SAME CONTIGUOUS LAYOUT.
THIS WAS ONE MONTH BEFORE THE PROPERTY WAS SOLD TO THE NEXT
OWNERS FOR A NEARLY $4 MILLION PROFIT TO THE DEVELOPER.
THE NEXT TWO OWNERS LIVED IN THE HOME FOR FOUR YEARS AS A
SINGLE FAMILY RESIDENCE. WE PURCHASED THE HOME IN 21
INHERITING EXACTLY THE SAME LAYOUT AFTER NEARLY A DECADE
FROM THE DEVELOPER'S REMODEL. SHORTLY AFTER MOVING IN WE WERE
TOLD WE HAD TO REINSTATE FOUR UNITS.
THE CITY'S CURRENT ENFORCEMENT POSITION THAT A FOUR UNIT
BUILDING EXISTS WAS UNLAWFULLY REMOVED IS DIRECTLY
CONTRADICTED BY THE CITY'S OWN RECORDS AT EVERY STAGE OF THIS
PROPERTY'S HISTORY. IT IS ALSO BUILT ON A
FOUNDATION THAT WAS NEVER LEGALLY ESTABLISHED.
THE 2013 PERMIT THAT CREATED THE FOUR UNIT DESIGNATION WAS
ISSUED WITHOUT A PUBLIC HEARING CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
OR NEIGHBORHOOD NOTIFICATION. THAT SAN FRANCISCO PLANNING
CODE REQUIRES FOR CHANGES TO A BUILDING UNIT COUNT THE
DESIGNATION THE CITY ENFORCING TODAY WAS NEVER SUBJECTED TO
THE PUBLIC PROCESS. THE CITY NOW DEMANDS FOR US
RESOLVE. >> GIVEN THOSE FACTS, HERE'S
THE PROBLEM. WHEN THIS ISSUE SURFACED WE DID
EXACTLY AS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT SUGGESTED.
WE HIRED EXPERIENCED ARCHITECTS AND ENGINEERS TO REINSTATE THE
FOUR UNITS. HOWEVER, AFTER YEARS OF GOOD
FAITH EFFORT WE LEARNED THAT IT CANNOT BE DONE IN COMPLIANCE
WITH IN THE POLICIES AT PLAY. THE PENDING PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S OWN STAFF REPORT CONFIRMS THAT OUR LOT IS
UNDERSIZED FOR FOUR DWELLING UNITS UNDER PLANNING CODE
SECTION 209.2 THE MAXIMUM ALLOWABLE DENSITY FOR THIS LOT
IN THE ROOM ONE DISTRICT IS 2.4 UNITS NOT FOR 2.4.
A FOUR UNIT DESIGNATION THAT THE CITY IS NOW ENFORCING
EXCEEDS WHAT THE PLANNING CODE ALLOWS FOR THIS PROPERTY.
IT IS BY THE DEPARTMENT'S OWN FINDING LEGAL NONCONFORMING
AND THIS IS THE CODE TODAY AND MORE NOTABLY THIS WAS THE
CODE IN 2013 WHEN THE DEVELOPER'S PERMITTED WAS
ISSUED WHICH MEANS THE FOUR UNIT PERMIT AT THE CENTER OF
THIS ENTIRE CASE WAS NOT JUST IMPROPERLY PROCESSED, IT WAS
FUNDAMENTALLY PROHIBITED BY THE ZONING CODE IN EFFECT AT THE
TIME IT WAS GRANTED A FOUR UNIT APPROVAL ON THE SLOT SHOULD
HAVE NEVER BEEN ISSUED. IT COULD NOT HAVE SURVIVED
PUBLIC REVIEW PROCESS THAT WAS SKIPPED BECAUSE THE DENSITY
MAPS WOULD HAVE REJECTED IT OUTRIGHT.
THE ENTIRE ENFORCEMENT ENFORCEMENT ACTION THE
VIOLATION THE C A REQUIREMENT THE HEARING WE ARE IN RIGHT NOW
ALL RESTS ON A PERMIT THAT WAS UNLAWFUL FROM THE DAY IT WAS
CREATED. >> IN OTHER WORDS, IF WE
APPLIED TO BUILD FOUR UNITS ON THIS PROPERTY TODAY WE WOULD BE
DENIED AND IN 2013 WE WOULD HAVE BEEN DENIED THEN TWO
AND YET UNDER SECTION 317 WE ARE BEING TOLD THAT WE CANNOT
REDUCE THE UNIT COUNT. BUT YOU CANNOT LOSE SOMETHING
THAT WAS NEVER BUILT AND WAS NEVER LAWFULLY PERMITTED TO BE
BUILT. FORCING 1.6 ADDITIONAL UNITS
INTO A BUILDING THAT CANNOT SUPPORT THEM DOES NOT PRODUCE
HOUSING. IT PRODUCES SUBSTANDARD, UNSAFE
LIVING CONDITIONS THAT WOULD NOT MEET THE CITY'S SOUND
QUALITY STANDARDS AND WE BELIEVE THAT IS ULTIMATELY WHY
PLANNING DIRECTED US TO PURSUE THE SEA RAY THESE UNITS THAT
ISKANDER PROMISED TO BUILD HAVE NEVER EXISTED.
>> NO ONE HAS EVER LIVED IN THEM.
NO ONE IS BEING DISPLACED BY THEIR REMOVAL FROM A
SPREADSHEET. THE ONLY PEOPLE POTENTIALLY AT
RISK OF BEING DISPLACED HERE ARE US THE FAMILY BEING TOLD TO
CONSTRUCT THEM. WHEN WE ASKED WHETHER WE COULD
EXPAND THE BUILDING ENVELOPE TO MAKE FOUR UNITS VIABLE
AND COMPLIANT, THAT FLEXIBILITY WAS NOT AVAILABLE.
WE DID NOT CREATE THIS CONTRADICTION.
IT WAS CREATED WHEN A FOUR UNIT PERMIT WAS ISSUED ON A LOT THAT
COULD NEVER LAWFULLY SUPPORT FOUR UNITS NOT UNDER TODAY'S
CODE AND NOT UNDER THE CODE IN EFFECT WHEN THE PERMIT WAS
GRANTED. WE ARE NOT HERE BECAUSE WE
DISAGREE WITH THE POLICY. WE ARE HERE BECAUSE THE POLICY
APPLIED TO THE REALITY OF THIS PROPERTY PRODUCES AN INHERENT
GRIDLOCK AND WE ARE ASKING THIS BOARD TO SIMPLY HELP US FIND A
WAY THROUGH. I'VE TALKED A LOT ABOUT
ACCOUNTABILITY TODAY AND I WANT TO OPENLY OWN OUR PORTION OF
IT. WE PURCHASED THIS HOME KNOWING
IT CARRIED A MULTI UNIT DESIGNATION ON PAPER THAT DID
NOT MATCH THE REALITY OF WHAT WE ARE MOVING INTO.
THAT WAS OUR DECISION. WE MADE IT WITH POOR ADVICE
LIMITED UNDERSTANDING, CONFLICTING CITY RECORDS
AND THE KIND OF OPTIMISM THAT MANY FIRST TIME HOMEBUYERS
IN SAN FRANCISCO ARE TO SOME DEGREE GUILTY OF.
WE UNDERSTAND NOW THE IMPLICATIONS OF THAT CHOICE.
WE OWN THAT FULLY AND WE ARE READY TO ACCEPT OUR FAIR SHARE
OF THE CONSEQUENCE OF THAT DECISION AND YET WE ARE THE
ONLY PARTY IN THIS ENTIRE CHAIN THAT HAS BEEN ASKED TO OWN
ANYTHING AT ALL. THE DEVELOPER WHO BOUGHT OUT
TENANTS OBTAINED FOUR UNIT APPROVAL THAT VIOLATED THE
ZONING CODE AT THE TIME WAS ISSUED AND THEN BUILT SOMETHING
ENTIRELY DIFFERENT MADE $4 MILLION IN PROFIT AND THEN
WALKED AWAY. HE HAS FACED NO CONSEQUENCE
FROM ANY CITY AGENCY FOR WHAT WAS BUILT OR RATHER WHAT WAS
NOT BUILT AT THIS ADDRESS OR ANY OF HIS OTHER PROPERTIES.
GBI, THE AGENCY THAT CONDUCTED 21 FIELD INSPECTIONS AND ISSUED
A CFC FOR A BUILDING THAT DID NOT MATCH THE APPROVED PLANS
HAS GIVEN NO EXPLANATION FACE NO CONSEQUENCE IN CONNECTION
WITH THIS PROPERTY. THE PRIOR OWNERS LIVED IN THE
HOME FOR FOUR YEARS AS A SINGLE FAMILY RESIDENCE AND THEY SOLD
IT AT A PROFIT AND MOVED ON. EVERYONE UPSTREAM EITHER
PROFITED OR FACED NO CONSEQUENCES.
THE FULL WEIGHT OF THE SITUATION HAS LANDED ON THE
ONLY PEOPLE WHO HAVE COME FORWARD ENGAGED IN THE PROCESS
AND TRIED TO MAKE IT RIGHT. WE WANT THE RECORD TO BE CLEAR
ABOUT WHAT A VOTE AGAINST US PRODUCES TODAY BECAUSE IT DOES
NOT PRODUCE WHAT THE FRAMING SUGGESTS.
A VOTE AGAINST US DOES NOT PRODUCE REAL HOUSING BECAUSE IT
CANNOT SUSTAINABLY HAVE FOUR COMPLIANT UNITS ON THE PROPERTY
AND IT DOES NOT HOLD BAD ACTORS ACCOUNTABLE.
THE DEVELOPER IS NOT HERE BEFORE YOU.
HE IS NOT HERE BEFORE YOU. THE ONLY PEOPLE BEFORE YOU ARE
THE ONES WHO HAVE FOLLOWED THE RULES.
A VOTE AGAINST US PRODUCES AN OUTCOME THAT EVERYONE
IN OPPOSITION REFUSES TO ACKNOWLEDGE.
THE PERMANENT DISPLACEMENT OF OUR FAMILY AT A SIGNIFICANT
AND DEVASTATING FINANCIAL LOSS. OUR TWO BOYS AGED EIGHT AND 11
LEAVE THE NUMBER NEIGHBORHOOD THEY'VE GROWN UP IN.
THEY LEAVE GARFIELD ELEMENTARY ,A PUBLIC SCHOOL THAT HAS SEEN
ENROLLMENT DROP NEARLY 10% FOR THE LAST TWO YEARS IN A
DISTRICT THAT IS ALREADY LOSING CHILDREN AND FAMILIES AT AN
ALARMING RATE DUE TO THE LACK OF FAMILY SIZED HOMES IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. THAT IS WHAT THIS VOTE DECIDES
NOT A HOUSING POLICY IN THE ABSTRACT NOT UNIT COUNTS IN A
SPREADSHEET. IT DECIDES WHETHER A FAMILY
THAT HAS BEEN A PART OF THIS COMMUNITY FOR 23 YEARS HAS
SUPPORTED ITS SCHOOLS AND ITS NEIGHBORS AND ITS SMALL
BUSINESSES GETS TO STAY. WE ARE NOT BEING ASKED TO BE
EXCUSED FROM RESPONSIBILITY. WE'VE TAKEN MORE RESPONSIBILITY
FOR THIS SITUATION THAN ANYONE ELSE INVOLVED.
WE ARE ASKING THAT RESPONSIBILITY BE SHARED
PROPORTIONATELY AMONG EVERYONE WHO CONTRIBUTED TO IT RATHER
THAN BE PLACED ENTIRELY ON THE PEOPLE VERSUS REMOVED FROM ITS
CREATION. AND IN THE ABSENCE OF THAT WE
ARE HUMBLY ASKING FOR PARTNERSHIP IN FINDING A
SOLUTION THAT WORKS FOR THE CITY AND FOR OUR FAMILY.
WE ARE ASKING THIS BOARD TO LEGALIZE A CONDITION THAT HAS
DOMINANTLY IN THE STUDENTS PROPERTY FOR OVER A CENTURY
REMEDY A DESIGNATION THAT WAS UNLAWFULLY GRANTED IN 2013
AND RETURN IT TO TWO UNITS. IF THIS BOARD BELIEVES A
DIFFERENT BETTER A BETTER PATH THAT SERVES THE CITY SCHOOLS,
WE'RE OPEN TO THAT CONVERSATION.
WE ARE HERE TO COLLABORATE AND WE HOPE THIS BOARD WILL
GIVE US THE OPPORTUNITY TO DO THAT.
WE WANT TO WORK WITH YOU ON A SOLUTION THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
US. >> THANK YOU.
I DON'T SEE ANY QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES SO WE WILL OPEN UP
PUBLIC COMMENTS SPECIFICALLY FOR THOSE WHO WOULD LIKE TO
SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL. MADAM CLERK, YOU WANT TO CALL
FOR THE FIRST SPEAKER? WE WANT TO WELCOME YOU IF
YOU'RE HERE IN THE CHAMBER AND YOU'D LIKE TO SUPPORT THE
APPELLANT PLEASE COME ON UP TO THE PODIUM.
>> THIS IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK IN A MOMENT FURTHER ON
DOWN THE HEARING THERE'LL BE AN OPPORTUNITY FOR THOSE WHO ARE
IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT. >> WELCOME.
WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS MOLLY JONES. I AM A SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT
AS WELL AS A BUSINESS OWNER AND I'VE LIVED HERE FOR OVER
HALF OF MY LIFE BEFORE SAN FRANCISCO I ACTUALLY GREW UP
IN STOCKTON WITH CAITLIN AND BEN WHO I HAVE KNOWN FOR
OVER 40 YEARS. >> ONCE WE ALL KIND OF FINISHED
SCHOOL WE SET OUR SIGHTS ON SAN FRANCISCO.
IT WAS OUR DREAM TO ALL LIVE HERE.
WE DID SO RIGHT AFTER MULTIPLE MULTIPLE JOBS BETWEEN ALL OF US
AS THIS CITY IS EXPENSIVE BUT IN OUR 20S WE WORKED HARD TO BE
ABLE TO LIVE THE DREAM OF BEING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
CAITLIN AND BEN PICKED NORTH BEACH FROM THE VERY BEGINNING.
THEY LOVED THE NEIGHBORHOOD. THEY HAVE SUPPORTED THE
RETAILERS THERE THROUGHOUT THEIR 20 PLUS YEARS OF LIVING
HERE. THEY ATTEND COMMUNITY EVENTS
THERE. >> YOU KNOW SAN FRANCISCO, A
LOT OF THE AREAS HERE IS FULL OF GENERATIONAL WEALTH BUT WITH
CAITLIN AND BEN THIS HAS BEEN 30 PLUS YEARS OF SAVINGS
AND PLANNING TO BE ABLE TO OWN THEIR VERY FIRST HOME IN THEIR
NEIGHBORHOOD OF NORTH BEACH THAT THEY ABSOLUTELY LOVE.
I UNDERSTAND WHILE YOU GUYS ARE REVIEWING ALL OF THIS, YOU'RE
REALLY LOOKING AT POLICIES. BUT I WANTED TO KIND OF GIVE
YOU AN IDEA OF WHAT I'M LOOKING AT AS WELL TOO.
I'M LOOKING AT TWO LITTLE BOYS WHO GET TO GO TO THEIR
NEIGHBORHOOD SCHOOL WHO GET TO LIVE BY THEIR BEST FRIENDS, A
HOME THAT IS ABLE TO, YOU KNOW, OPEN THEIR DOORS AND HOLD
NEIGHBORHOOD GATHERINGS AND TO REALLY ALWAYS HAVE THEIR DOOR
OPEN. BUT IF THIS FAILS, ALL OF THAT
IS GOING TO BE GONE. >> THEY'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
MOVE OUT DURING CONSTRUCTION AND THEY'RE NOT GOING TO BE
ABLE TO LIVE IN A CORNER OF THIS HOUSE WHEN THEY MOVE BACK
IN. >> THEY HAVE TWO PARENTS THAT
WORK FROM HOME CHILDREN AND THEY ALSO HAVE ELDERLY
PARENTS WHO ARE IN NEED OF ASSISTANCE.
>> THIS ISN'T NECESSARILY SOMETHING THAT'S UNFAIR.
>> IT'S REALLY INHUMANE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM THE NEXT SPEAKER WHO IS IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPEAL. WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON. I GO HOME.
MY NAME IS YAN SY. I'M A FIFTH GENERATION SAN
FRANCISCAN. A FATHER OF FOUR AND A NEIGHBOR
AND FRIEND TO THE HOLLOWAY RAMIREZ FAMILY IN NORTH BEACH.
I'M HERE TO CALL IN FAVOR OF THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION. I'VE KNOWN CAITLIN AND BEN FOR
TEN YEARS. WE STARTED OUR FAMILIES
TOGETHER. WE GREW OUR CAREERS TOGETHER
AND OVER THAT TEN YEARS AS WE'VE SEEN COUNTLESS FAMILIES
FLEE SAN FRANCISCO. I'VE SEEN KATELYN BEN GO THE
OTHER WAY PUTTING DOWN THOSE ROOTS NOT JUST THAT ACTUALLY
MAKING THEM REALLY FLOURISH. THEY HAVE BECOME LINCHPINS TO
OUR COMMUNITY MAKING COUNTLESS INVESTMENTS TO REVITALIZE THE
NEIGHBORHOOD, BECOMING COMMUNITY LEADERS AND MOST
IMPORTANTLY RAISING TWO AMAZING CHILDREN WHO I SHOULD MENTION
AS THE PARENT MENTIONED HAVE BEEN AN ASSET FOR US EVERY STEP
OF THE WAY RAISING THEM TO BECOME THE NEXT GENERATION OF
CIVIC MINDED, ENGAGED SAN FRANCISCANS AND IT'S THEIR
FAMILY AND FAMILIES LIKE MINE THAT THE FUTURE OF SAN
FRANCISCO RELIES. >> BUT WE KNOW THAT IT'S NOT
EASY TO RAISE A FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
WE HAVE NO ILLUSIONS ABOUT THAT .
BUT WHEN THERE ARE CHALLENGES THAT ARE PUT FORTH BY THE CITY
IN THE FORM OF ANTIQUATED REGULATIONS AND CODES AND AN
INABILITY TO MODERNIZE IN VIEW OF THESE SITUATIONS THAT MAKES
IT EVER MORE DIFFICULT TO KEEP THOSE ROOTS HERE.
THE PARENTS HAVE DONE EVERYTHING IN THEIR POWER TO
RECTIFY A SITUATION WHERE THEY WERE NOT ORIGINALLY A PARTY TO
AND I WOULD SAY THAT THE FAMILY THAT WE SEE SITTING HERE ARE
THE SORT OF FAMILIES THAT WE CANNOT AFFORD TO LOSE IF THEY
WERE TO LOSE AND HAVE FAMILIES LIKE THEIRS HAVE TO LOSE
BECAUSE OF SITUATIONS LIKE THESE WILL BE A SELF-INFLICTED
INJURY THAT THE CITY CANNOT AFFORD.
I URGE YOU TO SUPPORT THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC? PLEASE COME ON UP IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPEAL. >> GOOD AFTERNOON LADIES
MANDELMAN. MY NAME IS JENNIFER AND I'M A
SMALL BUSINESS OWNER HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND MY HUSBAND AND I BECAME FIRST TIME HOMEOWNERS SIX YEARS
AGO. >> I'VE LIVED IN THIS CITY FOR
12 YEARS AND I'VE CHOSEN TO STAY AND INVEST HERE BECAUSE I
BELIEVE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> AND THAT'S WHY I'M HERE
TODAY BECAUSE WHAT'S HAPPENING TO THIS FAMILY ISN'T JUST
COMPLICATED. >> IT'S WRONG.
A DEVELOPER GOT APPROVAL TO BUILD ONE THING, BUILT
SOMETHING COMPLETELY DIFFERENT AND WALKED AWAY WITH A
MULTIMILLION DOLLAR PROFIT. >> DB SIGNED OFF ON IT.
AND NOW BOTH ARE UNDER INVESTIGATION.
>> AND SOMEHOW THE ONLY PEOPLE PAYING THE PRICE ARE THESE
HOMEOWNERS WHO BOUGHT THIS PROPERTY IN GOOD FAITH AND HAVE
SPENT THE LAST FOUR YEARS TRYING TO FIX A PROBLEM THAT
THEY DID NOT CREATE. THAT IS NOT ACCOUNTABILITY.
THAT'S PUNISHING THE WRONG PEOPLE.
I FOLLOW THE RULES. >> I PAY MY TAXES.
I RUN A BUSINESS IN THIS CITY. AND I'M STANDING HERE ASKING IF
THIS IS HOW SAN FRANCISCO TREATS PEOPLE WHO DO EVERYTHING
RIGHT. THEN WHO IS THIS SYSTEM
ACTUALLY WORKING FOR? >> BECAUSE THIS FAMILY HAD
OPTIONS. >> THEY COULD HAVE FOUGHT YOU.
THEY COULD HAVE DRAGGED THIS OUT IN COURT.
THEY COULD HAVE WALKED AWAY. AND THEY DIDN'T.
THEY CHOSE TO WORK WITH THE CITY.
THEY CHOSE TO TRY TO FIX IT THE RIGHT WAY.
>> AND RIGHT NOW IT FEELS LIKE THEY'RE BEING PUNISHED FOR
THAT. THEIR PROPOSAL IS REASONABLE.
IT ADDS A RENT CONTROLLED UNIT. IT AVOIDS DISPLACEMENT.
IT ACTUALLY MOVES THIS SITUATION TOWARDS A REAL
SOLUTION. >> DENYING THIS APPEAL DOESN'T
FIX ANYTHING. IT JUST FORCES THIS FAMILY OUT
OF THEIR HOME AND LETS THE PEOPLE WHO ACTUALLY CAUSED THIS
WALK AWAY ON TOUCHED. >> SO I'LL LEAVE YOU WITH THIS.
IF DOING THE RIGHT THING LEADS TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
THANK YOU. IF YOU HAVE SOMETHING YOU'D
LIKE TO SUBMIT FOR THE RECORD WE'RE HAPPY TO TAKE THAT FOR
THE FILE. >> ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS
WHO'D LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED.
>> AND NOW WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM REPRESENTATIVES OF THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR UP TO TEN MINUTES.
>> ALL RIGHT. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SENIOR AND OUR PRINCIPAL PLANNERS FOR
SUPERVISOR DISTRICT THREE. SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND ACCOMPANIED TODAY BY COUNTY
ONE CODE ENFORCEMENT MANAGERS VERONICA FLORES, ACTING
LEGISLATIVE AFFAIRS MANAGER AND MATT GREANEY, DEPUTY
DIRECTOR, INSPECTION SERVICES FOR TBI.
>> ON DECEMBER 4TH, 2025 THE PLANNING COMMISSION CONDUCT TO
CONSIDER THE A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION REQUEST FOR THIS
PROPERTY. THE PROJECT PROPOSED TO
LEGALIZE THE MERGER OF THREE DWELLING UNITS ON THE SECOND
AND THIRD FLOORS INTO ONE UNIT AND TO REINSTATE 1 TO 2 UNITS
ON THE GROUND FLOOR. WE THINK WHAT'S LEGALLY AN
EXISTING FOUR UNIT BUILDING. THE PROJECT ALSO INCLUDED A
SMALL HORIZONTAL ADDITION AT THE PENTHOUSE LEVEL TO
ACCOMMODATE AN ELEVATOR. DURING THE HEARING A MOTION WAS
MADE TO DENY THE PROJECT. THE VOTE RESULTED IN A THREE
THREE TIE MEANING THE COMMISSION FAILED TO ACT UNDER
THE PLANNING CODE. FAILURE TO ACT CONSTITUTES A DE
FACTO DENIAL. MOVING ON TO THE APPEAL THE
APPELLANT PRESENTED SEVERAL CLAIMS AND THEY ARE CORE
ARGUMENT IS THAT THE BUILDING HAS LONG FUNCTIONED AS A SINGLE
FAMILY HOME AND THERE IS INSUFFICIENT EVIDENCE THAT THE
BUILDING WAS EVER FOR LEGALLY FOR LEGALLY BUILT UNITS.
>> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT DISAGREES WITH THAT ASSERTION.
>> THE DEPARTMENT DETERMINED THAT THERE IS SUBSTANTIAL
CONSISTENT EVIDENCE ACROSS MULTIPLE CITY AGENCIES
AND DOCUMENTS SHOWING THAT THE SUBJECT PROPERTY IS LEGALLY A
FOUR UNIT BUILDING. KEY EVIDENCE INCLUDES APPROVED
AND ISSUED BUILDING PERMIT PLANS SHOWING FOUR UNITS A 30
DAY NEIGHBORHOOD NOTIFICATION UNIT WAS COMPLETED BETWEEN
SEPTEMBER 9TH, 2011 TO OCTOBER 8TH, 20 11.
MULTIPLE INSPECTORS FROM THE FBI AND FIRE DEPARTMENT NOT
JUST ONE CONDUCTED SITE VISITS THROUGHOUT THE RENOVATION
PERIOD. >> TWO OFFICIAL THREE HOUR
REPORTS ISSUED IN 2017 AND 2020 BEFORE EACH SALE OF THE
PROPERTY AND LISTING FOR FAMILY TRAINING AS THE LEGAL UNIT
AND IN CLOSE THE STAIRWELL AND SECOND MEANS OF EGRESS
IN THE BUILDING WHICH TYPICALLY FOUND ONLY A MULTI FAMILY
BUILDING. >> ASSESSOR RECORDER DATA WHICH
IDENTIFIES AND ASSESSED THE PROPERTY AS A FOUR UNIT
RESIDENTIAL BUILDING. >> AND LASTLY TWO FORMER LONG
TERM TENANTS. WRITTEN STATEMENTS CONFIRMING
THE BUILDING OPERATED AS A FOUR UNIT RANK CONTROLLED PROPERTY
FOR OVER 30 YEARS INCLUDING INTO THE EARLY 20 TENS.
>> WHILE WE ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THE BUILDING APPEARS TO HAVE
FUNCTIONED AS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME IN MORE RECENT YEARS, THE
LEGAL STATUS NOT ITS CURRENT OCCUPANCY GOVERNS OUR
EVALUATIONS OF MERGERS THUS AUTHORIZING THE PROPOSED
PROJECT WOULD LEGALIZE AN UNAUTHORIZED MERGER RESULTING A
NET LOSS OF TWO RENT CONTROL UNITS THAT CONFLICT WITH THE
HOUSING ELEMENT AND LONGSTANDING CITY POLICY
DISCOURAGING THE REMOVAL OF EXISTING HOUSING.
>> SET A PRECEDENT. ENCOURAGE AND SIMILAR AFTER THE
FACT REQUEST. >> THEREFORE THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT RECOMMENDS THE BOARD UPHOLD THE COMMISSION'S DE
FACTO DENIAL AND DENY THE APPEAL.
THIS CONCLUDES THE DEPARTMENT'S PRESENTATION AND STAFF IS
AVAILABLE FOR QUESTIONS. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU SO
MUCH PRESIDENT. I HAVE QUESTIONS FOR YOU.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
SO DURING THE APPELLANT'S PRESENTATION THERE WAS A COUPLE
THINGS THAT WERE PUT OUT THAT WERE NOT CONSISTENT WITH WHAT I
READ IN THE VOLUMINOUS MATERIALS THAT RECEIVED ON THIS
APPEAL. >> AT THE FIRST ONE WAS THAT
TWO OF THE UNITS WERE UNPERMITTED.
>> AND I'M WONDERING IF YOU COULD, YOU KNOW, TELL US IF YOU
HAVE DOCUMENTATION THAT YOU KNOW, COULD MAYBE LEAD US TO
THINK THAT TWO OF THE UNITS WERE UNPERMITTED BECAUSE WHEN I
READ THE THREE HOUR REPORTS AND ALL OF THE OTHER
DOCUMENTATION IT SEEMED TO ME LIKE THEY WERE BOTH PERMITTED
IN TERMS OF THE PLANNING CODE AND THE BUILDING UP.
>> SURE. I'M HAPPY TO ANSWER THAT
QUESTIONS SO THAT TO YOU THESE ISSUES WERE INITIALLY FOUND
IN THE ENFORCEMENT CASE BACK IN 20 TENS AND SUBSEQUENTLY
THERE IS A BUILDING PERMIT APPLICATIONS SUBMITTED TO
LEGALIZE THOSE TWO UNIT USE. >> AND THROUGH THAT BUILDING
PERMIT APPLICATIONS THOSE TWO UNITS BECOME LEGAL TO ONLY
UNITS. AND THUS FAR THERE IS WE
BELIEVE THERE'S FOUR TOTAL 20 UNITS ON THIS PROPERTY.
>> AND SO WHEN WAS THAT LEGALIZATION?
WHAT DID THAT TAKE PLACE? >> THE D THE BUILDING PERMIT
APPLICATION WAS INITIALLY SUBMITTED IN 2011 AND IT WAS
FINALIZED. THE CERTIFICATE OF NO
COMPLETION WAS ISSUING MAY ON MAY 9TH, 2016.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
>> AND THE OTHER PIECE OF INFORMATION THAT THE APPELLANT
MADE IN THEIR PRESENTATION WAS THAT TODAY IT WOULD BE
IMPOSSIBLE TO BUILD FOUR CODE COMPLIANT UNITS.
AND SO IN THE DOCUMENTATION THAT I REVIEWED WITH THIS
APPEAL IT SEEMS LIKE RIGHT NOW THERE IS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME
ON THIS PROPERTY OF 3780FT2 DIVIDED BY FOUR.
THAT'S 945FT2 PER UNIT WHICH IS PRETTY GENEROUS.
THAT'S YOU KNOW, MORE THAN TWICE AS MUCH AS IS LEGALLY
REQUIRED. >> SO CAN YOU TELL US A LITTLE
BIT ABOUT WHETHER OR NOT THE DEPARTMENT THINKS THAT IT IS
POSSIBLE TO BUILD FOUR CODE COMPLIANT UNITS IN THIS
STRUCTURE WITHOUT ADDING BULK AND HEIGHT TO THE ENVELOPE?
>> I'M SO IN YOUR PACKET IN THE LAST TWO PAGES IS ACTUALLY
THERE IS PLANS THAT WERE SUBMITTED INTO I BELIEVE THAT'S
20/20 THREE BY THE APPELLANT PAGE TWO SHOWS HOW THE PLOT THE
PROPERTY CAN POTENTIALLY BE CONVERTED BACK TO FOUR UNITS.
>> UNFORTUNATELY BECAUSE THOSE PLANS ARE SUBJECT TO SB 1214
THE PROTECTED PLANS I WON'T BE ABLE TO SHARE IT OVER THE
PROJECTORS BUT IT DOES SHOWS THE POSSIBILITIES THAT HOW
THOSE UNITS CAN BE CONVERTED BACK TO FOUR UNITS.
>> AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT DID APPROVED THE THE PLANS AT
THAT TIME THE PLANS JUST NEVER BEING ISSUED.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
I APPRECIATE THAT. AND ONE LAST QUESTION.
YOU KNOW THIS MAY BE TOO MUCH FOR US AS YOU MAY REMEMBER, I
WAS ON THE PLANNING COMMISSION FOR MANY, MANY YEARS AND I
REMEMBER SEEING CASES VERY SIMILAR TO THIS ONE OVER
AND OVER AND OVER AGAIN, WHICH IS WHY THIS IS A POLICY ISSUE
AND NOT AN INDIVIDUAL ISSUE. I'M WONDERING IF YOU COULD TELL
US JUST BALLPARK HOW MANY OF THESE CASES DO WE SEE?
VERONICA FLORES PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF?
I DON'T HAVE A PERFECT NUMBER FOR YOU BUT WE DO SEE A HANDFUL
OF THESE AND THEY ARE ALWAYS AS YOU KNOW, VERY TOUGH HEARINGS
AND VERY INVOLVED DISCUSSIONS. I CAN CONFER WITH COLLEAGUES TO
SEE IF WE HAVE A BETTER ESTIMATE BUT WE WE SEE A
HANDFUL TO A DOZEN EVERY YEAR AND THAT'S IS THAT JUST BECAUSE
THAT'S WHEN THEIR THEIR COMPLAINT DRIVEN THESE ARE OUR
WORK AS YOU KNOW IS COMPLAINT DRIVEN SO AS IN THE CASE HERE
WE LEARNED ABOUT THIS PARTICULAR PROPERTY THROUGH A
SITE VISIT FROM AN ENFORCEMENT CASE.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MERRIMAN.
I HEARD SOMEONE SAY DURING PUBLIC COMMENT SOMETHING ABOUT
AN INVESTIGATION AND I'M WONDERING WHAT IS BEING
INVESTIGATED. I WASN'T QUITE CLEAR ON THAT.
SOMEBODY IN PUBLIC COME AND SAY SOMETHING ABOUT AN
INVESTIGATION THAT MAY BE HAPPENING.
>> SORRY. I'M MATT GREEN, THE DEPARTMENT
OF BUILDING INSPECTION. I DO KNOW WE'VE WRITTEN A
NOTICE OF VIOLATION AND WE ARE DOING AN INTERNAL INVESTIGATION
AS TO HOW WHAT MAY HAVE HAPPENED AT THE CFC.
AND WE'RE ALSO DISCUSSING WHETHER THIS IS EGREGIOUS
ENOUGH TO ADD THE DEVELOPER TO OUR EXPANDED COMPLIANCE CONTROL
LIST. >> AND WHEN DOES THAT DECISION
GET MADE? >> I'M WORKING RIGHT NOW WITH
OUR COMPLIANCE OFFICER BUT IT IS AFTER THIS HEARING LIKE I'M
NOT GOING TO. >> OH YES.
SORRY, JASON. AND I HAVE TO MAKE A DECISION
RIGHT HERE, CORRECT? YES.
BUT THIS WOULD BE ON THE DEVELOPER BACK IN 20 THAT THE
2016 SIGN OFF. >> THANK.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
I WANT TO ASK A LITTLE BIT MORE FROM DBA IF I MAY.
>> I GUESS YOU KNOW THIS THIS MAYBE MY FIRST QUESTION MIGHT
BE FOR DBA OR FOR PLANNING BUT I DO SEE CONFLICT HERE BETWEEN
THE INFORMATION YOU SHARED WITH THE ASSESSOR NOTING FOR UNITS
BUT THEN IN PARTICULAR THIS FOURTH UNIT OF FOR SAN ANTONIO
PLACE NOT EXISTING IN A MASTER ADDRESS REGISTRY NOT IN ANY
PERMIT RECORDS, NOT IN ANY PROPERTY TAX RULES, NO VOTER
REGISTRATION FILES RELATED TO THE PROPERTY NOT RELATED TO ANY
CENSUS OR POSTAL DATABASE. >> CAN YOU HELP SQUARE THAT UP
? >> I'M SORRY.
WHAT ARE YOU LOOKING AT? SUPERVISORS ARE I THINK MY
QUESTION IS IS THIS FOURTH UNIT?
FOR ME THERE'S PRETTY GOOD EVIDENCE THAT THERE WERE I MEAN
THERE'S EVIDENCE THAT THERE WERE TWO UNITS HERE THAT WERE
AUTHORIZED AND THEN THERE'S TWO ADDITIONAL UNITS WHICH WERE
IN THE BACK WHICH WERE UNAUTHORIZED FOR A NUMBER OF
YEARS IN A STORAGE SHED. IT'S MY UNDERSTANDING THAT THAT
STORAGE SHED HAS SINCE BEEN DEMOLISHED.
SO THIS CURRENT PROPERTY THAT STILL STANDS TODAY HAS NEVER
HAD FOUR UNITS. I THINK THAT'S A FACT.
THIS FOURTH UNIT FEELS LIKE IT'S ITS EXISTENCE
AND HABITATION IS RESTS ON PRETTY THIN ICE.
AND I'M TRYING TO UNDERSTAND BECAUSE IT SAYS FOUR UNITS
IN THE ASSESSOR ROLE BUT THE FOUR SAN ANTONIO PLACE DOESN'T
EXIST IN ANY OF THESE OTHER DATABASES THAT WE LOOK AT THAT
I MENTIONED. I'M JUST WONDERING IF YOU HAVE
MORE TO SQUARE UP THAT DISCREPANCY AND THAT CAN GO TO
TBI OR TO PLANNING? >> WELL, I WOULD DISAGREE THAT
THERE'S NEVER FOUR UNITS THERE. WE HAVE THE FIRE DEPARTMENT
INSPECTED THE PROPERTY IN FEBRUARY OF 2016 FOR THE
SPRINKLER SYSTEM. THEY CONFIRMED THERE WAS FOUR
UNITS A SEPARATE FIRE INSPECTOR WAS BACK OUT THERE IN APRIL OF
2016, CONFIRMED THE FOUR UNITS AND THEN OUR BUILDING INSPECTOR
WAS THERE IN MAY OF 2016 CONFIRMED FOUR UNITS AS TO THE
ADDRESS THE PERMIT IN QUESTION HERE WAS THE BUILDING WAS
ORIGINALLY A LEGAL TWO UNIT BUILDING AND THAT THE PERMIT
IN QUESTION FROM 2011 WAS TO LEGALIZE THE EXISTING THE TWO
ILLEGAL THE EXISTING TWO THE TWO EXISTING ILLEGAL UNITS FOR
A TOTAL OF FOUR UNITS. >> THE ADDRESS THAT I THINK
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT A THREE HOUR REPORT WAS FOR SAN ANTONIO
PLACE AND FIVE FOR TWO SIX MY WHOLE STREET HAS TWO ADDRESSES
ON IT IS THAT WHAT YOU'RE JUST. >> THAT'S RIGHT.
YES. YES.
I YOU KNOW I'M NOT I'M NOT SURE ABOUT THAT ABOUT THE SAN
ANTONIO. >> I DID TRY TO FIND DIG THAT
ADDRESS UP MYSELF. I COULDN'T FIND AND I THINK
THAT'S COMPLETELY FAIR BECAUSE IT'S IT APPEARS TO BE A MYSTERY
TO ME AS WELL. >> I WANT TO ASK YOU PLEASE.
>> YEAH. COULD I COULD I ALSO SPEAK TO
KELLY WONG, CODE ENFORCEMENT MANAGER AT THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT? >> SO IN THE 2011 PERMIT SET
YOU WILL SEE THE NUMBER FOUR AND FOUR A WHICH I BELIEVE IS
REFERENCING THE ONES THE FOUR A SAN ANTONIO PLACE IN THE
DRAWINGS YOU WILL SEE THAT THE UNIT FOUR AND A UNIT FOR A ARE
OUTLINED IN ADDITION TO 524 AND 526 VALLEJO STREET.
>> THANK YOU. AND THAT'S THE 2011 IS THAT
RIGHT? >> THAT'S CORRECT.
2011 02049686. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. AND THEN THE I THINK ANOTHER
YOU KNOW CRITICAL PIECE HERE IS THE THE 2016 ACTION WHICH IS
TVI SIGNING A CERTIFICATE OF FINAL COMPLETION IN 2016.
BUT IT'S MY UNDERSTANDING THAT WITHIN 45 DAYS OF THAT
CERTIFICATE BEING SIGNED AND THE HOME IS LISTED FOR SALE
AS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME AND WE KNOW THAT YOU CAN'T DO THAT
SORT OF WORK WITHIN A MONTH CONVERTING A FOUR UNIT HOME
INTO A SINGLE FAMILY HOME IN A MONTH.
AND I'M JUST LEFT WITH A LOT OF QUESTIONS ABOUT THAT TIMELINE
AND I'M JUST LOOKING FOR ANY GUIDANCE OR THOUGHTS OF HOW
SUCH A SERIES OF EVENTS COULD HAPPEN BECAUSE IT STRIKES ME AS
THAT IS AT THE HEART OF THIS IS DID THAT WORK ACTUALLY HAPPEN
AND THE VALIDITY OF THAT CERTIFICATE OF COMPLETION
IN 2016 AND THAT'S A THOUGHT AND A QUESTION I SHARE YOUR
CONCERN AS WELL. >> THAT DOES SEEM LIKE A QUITE
QUICK TURNAROUND LET'S SAY IT'S IMPOSSIBLE BUT IT IS A QUICK
TURNAROUND. I WILL SAY THERE IS THREE
SEPARATE INSPECTORS THERE WITHIN A TWO MONTH PERIOD, TWO
FIRE INSPECTORS AND ONE BUILDING INSPECTOR WHO
CONFIRMED THAT THERE WAS A FOUR UNIT BUILDING AT THE TIME.
OKAY. SO KELLY WONG, I JUST WANT TO
ALSO ADD TO THE RECORD THAT DURING OUR SITE VISITS AND OUR
CODE ENFORCEMENT INVESTIGATIONS WE OFTEN DO FIND WE RECEIVE
COMPLAINTS FOR A MERGER BECAUSE OF REAL ESTATE LISTINGS
AND SOMETIMES THE LISTINGS ARE NOT ACCURATE.
SO WE HAVE INVESTIGATED MERGER COMPLAINTS AND ACTUALLY
CONFIRMED THAT THE MERGERS DID NOT OCCUR.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
AND THEN ONE LAST QUESTION. >> CAN YOU GIVE A SENSE TO WITH
THIS PARTICULAR DEVELOPER YOU KNOW, THE SCOPE OF ANY
INVESTIGATION AT THE MOMENT OR WHAT MIGHT BE CONSIDERED YOU
KNOW, HOW MANY OTHER PROPERTIES THEY APPEAR TO HAVE WORKED ON
ANY VIOLATIONS, ANYTHING TO HELP ILLUSTRATE THAT?
I KNOW OF AT LEAST ONE OTHER PROPERTY WHO ARE CURRENTLY
TRYING TO GAIN ACCESS TO IT FOR AN INVESTIGATION.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN I JUST WANT
A CLARIFICATION TO HELP ME UNDERSTAND THE PHOTO THAT
IN YOUR PRESENTATION INDICATED THERE ARE FOUR SEPARATE
ELECTRICAL METERS AND THAT'S FROM YOUR VISIT IN 2020 TO WHY
IS THAT IMPORTANT? >> LIKE WHAT DOES THAT WHAT
DOES THAT PHOTO ACTUALLY INDICATE IT AND WHAT DOES THAT
MEAN? COULD YOU ELABORATE?
>> I BELIEVE IT IS FOUR SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS, ONE
FOR EACH UNIT AND THEN YOU SEE A FIFTH METER THERE FOR THE THE
HOUSE METER WHICH WOULD BE THE COMMON LIGHTS AND SUCH.
>> SORRY SAY THAT ONE MORE TIME.
IT WAS NOT CLEAR. >> I'M SORRY.
SO YOU SEE THERE'S FOUR UNITS IN THE VERTICAL LINE THERE.
THOSE ARE FOUR UNITS FOR EACH ONE FOR EACH SPECIFIC UNIT.
AND THEN OFF TO THE RIGHT THERE'S ANOTHER METER THERE
THAT WOULD BE CALLED THE HOUSE METER FOR COMMON LIGHTS
AND STUFF LIKE THAT. >> BUT BUT WHY IS IT IMPORTANT
TO SHOW THAT THERE ARE FOUR SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS?
BECAUSE IT SEEMS TO INDICATE THAT THERE'S FOUR SEPARATE
UNITS. >> I SEE.
AND AND THIS WAS AND THAT SORRY.
AND THEN I'M TRYING TO I'M KIND OF CONFUSED ABOUT THE TIMELINE
IN THAT IT WAS INDICATED IN YOUR VISIT FOR 2022 AND THAT
WHAT YOU'RE SAYING IS THAT THIS WORK THAT IS SHOWS THAT THERE
ARE FOUR IS THIS AFTER THE NEW OWNER OCCUPIED THIS SPACE OR IS
IT BEFORE I'M TRYING TO I'M KIND OF I'M SORRY I'M TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND BETTER WHAT WHY THIS IS CRITICAL TO INCLUDE AS FOR
SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS AND BECAUSE I'M TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND THERE SEEMS TO BE A DEBATE HERE THAT WHETHER THE
CURRENTLY THE OWNER KNOWS OR KNOWINGLY OR NOT KNOWINGLY THAT
THERE WERE FOUR UNITS AND I'M TRYING TO UNDERSTAND BOTH
IN THE TIMELINE AND IN YOUR PRESENTATION HERE IT SEEMS TO
ME AND PLEASE CORRECT ME IF I'M WRONG AND I MISUNDERSTAND THE
CRITICAL PHOTO OF THIS OR INCLUDED THIS.
IS THAT WHAT YOU'RE TRYING TO PRESENT TO US IS THAT IT SEEMS
LIKE IT WAS CLEAR TO ANYONE INCLUDING THE OWNERS ARE
CURRENTLY OCCUPYING THE SPACE THAT THERE WERE FORMERLY FOUR
UNITS BECAUSE IN ORDER FOR IT TO ACTUALLY HAVE FOUR IT'S IT'S
BECAUSE THAT THAT IS WHY YOU WOULD REQUIRED TO HAVE FOUR
SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS BECAUSE YOU HAVE FOUR
INDEPENDENT UNITS RESIDENTIAL UNITS IN THAT ONE SPACE.
>> IS THAT CORRECT? A CORRECT.
THANK YOU. SO SO WHAT YOU'RE SAYING HERE
IS THAT YOU'RE SHOWING TO US AS AN EVIDENCE THAT BOTH BE AT THE
DEVELOPER OR INCLUSIVE OF THE PERSON THAT THE THE THE OWNERS
ARE OCCUPYING THIS I'M SORRY I'M JUST PARAPHRASING BECAUSE I
WANT TO MAKE SURE I CLEARLY UNDERSTAND WHAT I AM ASKING.
BUT WHAT I AM SEEING HERE IS ACCORDING TO THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND THE BUILDING INSPECTION DEPARTMENT AFTER
YOUR INSPECTION AND VISIT OR AFTER PLANNING DEPARTMENT VISIT
HERE IS THAT IT'S THERE'S A CLEAR EVIDENCE THAT THE CURRENT
OCCUPANT KNOWS THAT THERE WERE FOUR SEPARATE RESIDENTIAL UNITS
BECAUSE BASED ON THE SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS THIS IS KELLY
WONG PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND I MY ANSWER IS YES FROM THE 2013
SPRINKLER PERMIT AND THEN ANOTHER 1 IN 2015 FOR THE
SPRINKLER MONITORING SYSTEM WHICH WAS INSPECTED BY THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT, THEY WOULD HAVE THE ACTUALLY ON THEIR PERMITS THEY
SHOW THAT THERE ARE FOUR UNITS THANK YOU.
>> AND THAT THERE IF IF WERE THERE ANY RECORDS BECAUSE IF
YOU REQUIRE FOUR SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS IT DOES
INDICATE AND YOU WOULD HAVE PREVIOUS UTILITY BILLS INDICATE
FOR INDIVIDUAL HOUSEHOLDS OCCUPYING THAT SPACE CORRECT?
I'M JUST KIND OF CURIOUS IF THERE WAS EVER EVEN SUCH
EVIDENCE. NONE NONE WERE SUBMITTED TO THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT. THANK YOU.
I SEE. SO AND SO THAT MEANS IT DOESN'T
NECESSARY IT HAS TO BE A RESIDENTIAL UNITS IT COULD AS
INDICATED BY SUPERVISOR SOUDER ASSEMBLY A STORAGE UNIT WOULD
IT BE THEN REQUIRED TO HAVE A ELECTRICAL METER?
NO. A COMMON STORAGE UNIT WOULD BE
ON ONE OF THE UNITS METERS AND GET A SEPARATE METER LIKE
IF IF THE STORAGE SO SORRY LET ME BACK UP.
IF THE STORAGE UNIT WAS ATTACHED TO ONE OF THE UNITS IT
WOULD BE ON THAT UNIT'S METER. BUT IF IT WAS SORT OF A COMMON
USE STORAGE ROOM IT WOULD BE ON THAT COMMON HOUSE METER THAT
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU
PRESENT GENTLEMAN I'M STILL CONFUSED ABOUT THE 2016 SIGN
OFF AND THE TIMING WITH THE FOUR OR WITH BASICALLY DB BEING
IN THERE AROUND THE TIME WHERE IT IS BEING MARKETED AS A
SINGLE FAMILY HOME I DON'T REALLY UNDERSTAND.
IT SEEMS LIKE THERE WERE INSPECTIONS AFTER 2016 AND 217
IS AS WELL. WE'RE BASICALLY SUGGEST LIKE
ARE WE SAYING THAT THE LISTINGS MAYBE WERE JUST A LIE?
>> I'M JUST CONFUSED AS TO WHY DBA WOULD HAVE BEEN IN THERE
MULTIPLE TIMES SIGNING OFF ON PERMITS IF THE PERMITS WERE FOR
FOUR UNITS AND THE HOUSE WAS NOT WELL FOR THE 20 2011 PERMIT
THAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT, THERE WAS MULTIPLE INSPECTIONS
THROUGHOUT THE WHOLE WELL I'M TALKING ABOUT THE 2016 RIGHT.
>> YOU SAID IN 2016 THE FOUR UNITS WERE LEGALIZED.
>> RIGHT. THAT WAS UNDER THE 2011 PERMIT.
>> THAT WORK WAS COMPLETED IN MAY OF 2016.
SO SO YOU WOULD SIGN OFF ON A PERMIT IN 2016 WITHOUT
INSPECTING THE BUILDING IN 2016?
NO, NO, I SAID THEY INSPECTED THE BUILDING.
>> WELL, THAT THAT'S WHAT I'M ASKING YOU.
RIGHT. LIKE IT SEEMS TO ME THAT
IN 2016 AND THEN I THINK THERE WERE OTHER PERMITS THAT WERE
INSPECTED IN 2017 AND I JUST I'M CONFUSED AS TO WHY THIS
WASN'T CAUGHT BACK THEN THAT SIMILARLY THAT'S WHEN THE THE
SHIFT FROM FOUR UNITS TO ONE SINGLE FAMILY HOME HAPPENED.
>> AND I'M JUST I JUST DON'T UNDERSTAND HOW WE WE MISSED
THAT OR IF THAT'S NOT SOMETHING WE WOULD HAVE LOOKED FOR
THERE'S KIND OF DON'T GET HOW THIS GOT PASSED 2017 I GUESS SO
THERE WAS A COMPLAINT ABOUT WORK BEYOND THE PERMIT.
THE BUILDING INSPECTOR WHO INSPECTED THAT IT WAS REFERRED
FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND WE BASED ON THE E MAILS
FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT WE THOUGHT THAT THE COMPLAINT WAS
ABOUT THE ROOF DECK AND THE INSPECTOR THE RAILING ON THE
ROOF SPECIFICALLY AND THEN THE INSPECTOR DID VERIFY FROM THE
STREET THAT IT MATCHED THE APPROVED PLANS FOR THE ROOF
RAILING AND THERE WEREN'T INSPECTIONS IN 2017 ABOUT A
FIRE SPRINKLER SYSTEM OR ANYTHING ELSE THAT I ASSUME
WOULD REQUIRE SOMEONE TO GO INSIDE THE BUILDING.
>> OH, THE 27 THE FIRE PERMIT. SO UNFORTUNATELY THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT'S COMPUTER SYSTEM IS A LITTLE SLACK.
IT TAKES A LITTLE LONGER FOR THE PERMITS TO BE ACTUALLY
COMPLETED. I HAVE THE INSPECTION HISTORY
WHEN THEY ACTUALLY WENT OUT THERE THEY DID THE INSPECTION
ON TO 18 2016 FIRE FIRE SPRINKLER FINAL PENDING WATER
FLOW AND THEN A 4 OR 516 WATER AND TAMPER SWITCHES TESTED
AND THEN THE SUPERVISE THE FIRE SPRINKLER FLOW AND SUPERVISOR
SYSTEM WAS FINAL. >> SO BASICALLY WHAT WHAT I'M
HEARING IS IT SEEMS LIKE THE DEVELOPER WHEN THEY FIRST
MARKETED THIS PROPERTY AS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME WAS
ESSENTIALLY LYING IN THE MARKETING MATERIALS.
>> YES. SO ALSO THERE'S A THREE HOUR
REPORT THE HOUSING CODE REQUIRES THAT THE SELLER
PROVIDES A THREE HOUR REPORT REPORT OF RESIDENTIAL RECORD
WHICH LISTS THE YOU KNOW, THE LEGAL USE OF THE PROPERTY
AND THE ENTIRE PERMIT HISTORY OF THE PROPERTY.
>> SO THEN WHY ARE WE GOING AFTER THIS BAD ACTOR HERE?
LIKE IF WE HAVE A DOZEN OF THESE EVERY YEAR HOW MANY
PEOPLE GET DINGED FOR BEING TOTAL?
>> I'LL DEFER TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR THE QUESTION.
WE DON'T HAVE SPECIFIC NUMBERS BUT WE DO FIND SOMETIMES THAT
CURRENT PROPERTY OWNERS ARE ABIDING VIOLATIONS BY PRIOR
PROPERTY OWNERS. BUT THAT BECOMES ALSO A PRIVATE
MATTER BECAUSE IT'S A BUSINESS TRANSACTION OF PURCHASING A
PROPERTY AND PERHAPS THE PRIOR OWNER DID NOT DISCLOSE ACCURATE
INFORMATION TO THE CURRENT PROPERTY OWNER BUT WE WOULD
ALSO NEVER KNOW WHAT THAT PRIVATE AGREEMENT WOULD BE.
>> BUT IF IT'S PRETTY CLEAR THAT A PREVIOUS OWNER DID A
PREVIOUS OWNER DID UNPERMITTED WORK AND THEN PROFITED ON IT,
IS THAT IS THAT A CIVIL LEGAL MATTER FOR COMMITTING FRAUD ON
THE DISCLOSURES? IT'S NOT IT'S NOT A CRIMINAL
MATTER FOR DEFRAUDING THE CITY BECAUSE IT WOULD BE A CIVIL
MATTERS IF IT'S LIKE FALSE DISCLOSURES OF DOCUMENTATIONS
AND I PLEASE SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THE MICROPHONE.
>> THANK YOU. IT WILL BE A CIVIL MATTERS LIKE
FAILURE TO DISCLOSE TO TO THE CURRENT PROPERTY OWNERS ABOUT
ALL THE DOCUMENTATIONS THAT IT IS A FOUR UNIT BUILDING.
ALL RIGHT. I'M NOT COMFORTABLE WITH US NOT
GOING AFTER THESE CLEAR BAD ACTORS HERE FROM, YOU KNOW, 15
YEARS AGO. >> BUT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU. I WANT TO RETURN TO THE
QUESTION OF THE 2016 PERMIT THAT WAS SIGNED OFF ON BY IDBI
. >> CAN YOU SHARE THE INSPECTOR
WHO WORKED ON THAT PERMIT ARE THEY UNDER INVESTIGATION FOR
ANY OTHER PERMITS THAT THEY SIGNED OFF ON OR OTHER WORK
THAT THEY DID? >> NO, NONE OF THEM NOT AT THIS
TIME, NO. >> HAVE THEY BEEN UNDER
INVESTIGATION IN THE PAST? YES.
>> YOU TELL ME MORE ABOUT THAT OF YOU'RE NOT SURE THAT I CAN
THAT IT'S AN INTERNAL IT WAS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT WE THE
INDIVIDUAL WHO SIGNED OFF ON THIS PERMIT IN 2016 HAS BEEN
UNDER INVESTIGATION AND SO THIS CONTINUES TO MAKE THIS 2016
SIGN OFF WHICH IS THE CRUX OF SO MUCH OF THIS IS REALLY,
REALLY DIFFICULT FOR US TO CONSIDER.
>> WE MAY HAVE WE MAY HAVE MALINTENT FROM THE DEVELOPER OR
WE MAY HAVE MALINTENT FROM SOMEONE WHO SIGNED OFF ON THE
THE PERMITS HERE. >> BUT A LOT OF THIS BEFORE US
HINGES ON THIS 2016 CERTIFICATION WHICH I'M NOT
COMFORTABLE UNDERSTANDING WHAT ACTUALLY HAPPENED AND THERE'S A
LOT THAT IS UNCLEAR HERE. I KNOW THERE'S MORE TO PROCEED
HERE. I JUST WANT TO QUICKLY RUN DOWN
ONE MORE LINE OF QUESTIONING IF I MAY.
I WANT TO ASK A LITTLE BIT MORE ABOUT IF WE WERE TO REJECT THIS
. I THINK THE UNDERSTANDING IS
THAT THIS THEN PUTS THE FAMILY BACK ON A PATH HERE TO TO
REQUIRE THAT THEY DO FOR UNITS AT THIS SITE.
>> CAN WE LEARN A LITTLE BIT MORE ABOUT WHAT THAT WOULD
ENTAIL? WOULD THOSE FOUR UNITS BE RENT
CONTROLLED? WOULD THEY BE OCCUPIED BY
SOMEONE ELSE? WHAT WOULD BE REQUIRED IF WE
WERE TO REJECT THIS AND GO DOWN THE PATH OF FOUR UNITS THEY
WILL NEED TO THE BUILDING WILL NEED TO BE CONVERTED BACK TO
FOUR UNITS. >> WE CANNOT DEFINITE SAY THOSE
UNITS ARE RENT CONTROLLED BUT BASED ON THE RECORDS WE HAVE WE
CAN IT'S THOSE UNITS ARE LIKELY RENT CONTROLLED AND WOULD THEY
BE REQUIRED TO BE OCCUPIED BY SOMEONE ELSE NOW WE DO NOT
CONTROL WHO WOULD LIVE THERE. THE THE PLANNING CODES ARE
REGULATED PER PROPERTY NOT INDIVIDUALS.
THE TENANTS OR THE OWNERS WHO LIVE THERE.
>> AND I THINK THERE'S A QUESTION OF IF THESE CAN JUST
PHYSICALLY BE CONSTRUCTED OR IF THEY CAN BE APPROVED AND I
THINK MAYBE THAT'S CHANGED THEIR TIME.
BUT I MEAN AT THIS POINT WOULD YOU BE ABLE TO APPROVE FOUR
UNITS ON THIS SITE OR WOULD THAT NECESSITATE AN ADDITIONAL
STRUCTURE? RIGHT.
WE THERE'S THIS THIS UNIT IN THE BACK THAT HAS KIND OF
BEEN A QUASI STORAGE UNIT WHERE THESE UDAS MAY HAVE EXISTED.
WOULD IT BE AN AUXILIARY CONSTRUCTION REQUIRED?
>> DO WE KNOW YET? THERE IS A BUILDING PERMIT
APPLICATION CURRENTLY SUBMITTED?
IT'S UNDER OUR 2023 RECORD AND PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS
ALREADY APPROVED TO REVERT THE BUILDING BACK TO FOUR UNITS
AND I THINK MAYBE LATER WE WANT TO HEAR FROM THE FROM THE
OWNERS JUST TO HEAR ABOUT THOSE PLANS AS WELL BECAUSE I KNOW
THERE'S SOME THINGS YOU CAN'T SHARE.
>> THAT'S ALL FOR NOW. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. I THINK THAT IS IT FROM
COLLEAGUES. SO WE WILL INVITE MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC WHO WISH TO SPEAK IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL TO
LINE UP. THEY HAVE ALREADY DONE THAT.
EACH WILL HAVE UP TO TWO MINUTES.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU WANT CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE FIRST
SPEAKER? >> WELCOME.
COME ON UP TO THE FIRST FOR SPEAKER.
WELCOME. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. >> WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON. STEPHEN TORRES FROM THE SAN
FRANCISCO TENANTS UNION. THE SAN FRANCISCO TENANTS UNION
STANDS WITH THIS COALITION OF ORGANIZATIONS TO EMPHASIZE OUR
STRONG OPPOSITION TO THE C I C U A AT 524 OR 526 VALLEJO
STREET AND FOR FOR A SAN ANTONIO PLACE WE URGE THE BOARD
TO DENY THE APPELLANT'S PROPOSAL TO ALLOW THE CONTINUED
USE OF THE PROPERTY AS A 3713 SQUARE FOOT LUXURY HOME.
>> THERE IS A LOT OF INTRICATELY WOVEN
MISCHARACTERIZE ATIONS BEING PRESENTED BY THE APPELLANTS BUT
LET'S BE CLEAR THAT THESE ARE ATTEMPTS TO OBFUSCATE WHAT IS
FACT. THIS WAS AN ILLEGAL DEMOLITION
OF RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING AND NOW THE OWNERS OF THIS
PROPERTY WANT TO BE TOLD THEY CAN KEEP IT AS A LUXURY SINGLE
FAMILY HOME AND MAYBE AN ANCILLARY CLOSET OR TWO TO TICK
THE BOX. >> THIS PORTENDS A DANGEROUS
PRECEDENT IN LEGITIMIZING ILLEGAL DEMOLITIONS OF THIS
KIND AS ALREADY HAPPENING ACROSS THE CITY.
THIS BODY SHOULD PERHAPS BE LOOKING FOR WAYS TO STRENGTHEN
THE ABILITY TO ENFORCE AGAINST THESE INSTEAD OF SPENDING ANY
TIME DEBATING WHAT IS BEFORE YOU.
I WILL REMIND YOU THAT THIS BODY THAT MANY OF YOU
VEHEMENTLY VOWED THAT THERE WOULD NOT BE RAMPANT
DEMOLITIONS IN THE CONTEXT OF THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN AND HAVE
PLEDGED YOUR COMMITMENT TO PROTECTING DESPERATELY NEEDED
RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING. THIS IS AN OPPORTUNITY TO PUT
YOUR REPUTATION WHERE YOUR MOUTH IS AND MAKE IT CLEAR THAT
NO ILLEGAL DEMOLITIONS CONVERSIONS OR WHATEVER YOU
WANT TO CALL IT WILL STAND. >> MANY HAVE CITED FLEXIBILITY
AS THE WORD OF THE DAY WHEN IT COMES TO HOUSING.
BUT WHO IS THE FLEXIBILITY FOR THE WORKING CLASS AND MOST
VULNERABLE OF SAN FRANCISCO OR THE WEALTHY AND BEST CONNECTED?
WILL YOU JOIN YOUR COLLEAGUE IN UPLIFTING DEMOLITIONS?
OR LOOK FOR WAYS TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO HOUSING WHOLE
AFFORDABLE AND ACCESSIBLE? >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, STEPHEN TORRES FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. >> FRED SHERMAN ZIMMER FROM
HOUSING RIGHTS COMMITTEE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I WOULD HOPE THAT TENANTS MATTER TO THOUSANDS OF TENANTS
IN THE CITY, LIVE IN UNITS THAT ARE OR WERE ILLEGAL AND LOTS OF
LANDLORDS DO UNPERMITTED WORK. AND I WOULD HAVE TO SAY LOTS OF
REALTORS LIE. >> THE LANDLORD WHO PUSHED OUT
THE LAST SET OF BUILDINGS LAST YEAR OF TENANTS LIVING IN THIS
BUILDING ESCANABA WAS A SERIAL VICTOR.
>> HE LIKE MANY OTHERS, KNEW HE COULD MAKE A LOT OF MONEY.
WE HAVE SEEN BEFORE WHETHER IT'S TAXES OR SHORT TERM
RENTALS. IF WE REWARD LANDLORDS
AND INVESTORS AND REALTORS IF YOU TELL THEM THEY CAN MAKE
MILLIONS YOU ENCOURAGE THE ELLIS ACT.
YOU ENCOURAGE THE HARASSMENT OF TENANTS.
>> IF I BUY A STOLEN CAR EVEN UNKNOWINGLY I STILL HAVE TO
GIVE IT BACK. >> WE RUN A CLINIC THAT OVER
5000 PEOPLE COME TO 5000 TENANTS COME IN DESPERATE
STATES YEAR AFTER YEAR WE HEAR STORIES OF PEOPLE HARASSED
AND EVICTED. WE WATCH THOSE WE LOVE PUSHED
OUT BY LANDLORDS OR REALTORS WHO ENCOURAGE THESE EVICTIONS.
>> DON'T TENANTS MATTER? DON'T WE PAY TAXES?
WE WOULD LIKE TO HAVE THE CHOICE TO STAY TOO.
AND IF YOU REWARD PEOPLE AND LET THEM MAKE MONEY YES
MAYBE THEY KNEW WHAT THEY WERE BUYING AND MAYBE THEY SHOULD
SUE THE PEOPLE WHO BOUGHT IT. >> BUT THESE TENANTS MATTERED
TO. >> THANK YOU, SHERIFF SHERBURN
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME MAGIC.
THANK YOU. YES.
IN OUR CURRENT ECONOMY SYSTEM, THE MORE MONEY YOU HAVE, THE
LESS YOU FEEL OBLIGATED TO FOLLOW THE LAWS OF THE LAND.
>> THESE LAWS AND REGULATIONS ARE SOCIAL CONTRACTS THAT WE
THE PEOPLE HAVE ENACTED TO PROTECT THE PLACES, PEOPLE
AND LIFESTYLE WE VALUE. >> ALL STUDIES AND EXPERTS
AGREE THAT THE HOUSING THAT IS NEEDED IS FOR OUR TEACHERS
MEDICAL WORKERS, ARTISTS, SERVICE WORKERS AND SO MANY
MORE WHO MAKE THIS GREAT CITY WHAT IT IS.
>> AND YET MARKET RATE HOUSING KEEPS BEING PROPOSED.
>> THIS COUPLE ALREADY KNOWS THAT THEY ARE VIOLATING
COMMUNITY AGREEMENTS AND THE PLANNING COMMISSION MADE THAT
CLEAR. >> I'M ASSUMING THEY'RE
APPEALING BECAUSE THEY CAN AFFORD TO PAY A LAWYER WHO
KNOWS HOW TO ATTEMPT TO CIRCUMVENT THE LAW TO MAKE THIS
CASE. THE BUILDING INSPECTOR MATT
GREEN HAS MADE IT CLEAR THAT THERE'S MORE INSPECTING
AND THINGS THAT NEED TO BE COMPLETED.
FROM MY UNDERSTAND ING UNLESS SOME POLITICIANS INTERFERE
HOPING TO GARNER SOME GOODWILL THAT LOOKS LIKE POWER AND MONEY
DOWN THE ROAD. THERE REALLY IS NO CASE HERE.
UPHOLD AND RESPECT OUR PLANNING COMMISSION SUPERVISORS DO YOUR
JOB, UPHOLD THE LAW AND HAVE THEM DO THE WORK NEEDED TO
RETURN THIS TO A FOUR UNIT BUILDING TO RESTORE ABOLISH THE
KIND OF HOUSING THAT WE NEED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU MAGIC FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. SUPERVISORS TRAYS OF
FLOUNDERING NORTH BEACH TENANTS COMMITTEE.
I ECHO WHAT MAGIC JUST SAID. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
AGAIN IT IS UNFORTUNATE THAT JOE PADILLA WILL NOT BE HERE.
HE IS THE FORMER TENANT AT FOUR B THE OFFICIAL THE OFFICIAL
POST OFFICE ADDRESS WAS FOR BE SAN ANTONIO PLACE.
>> HE WAS ONE OF THE TWO TENANTS IN THE REAR AND THERE
HAVE BEEN TWO LETTERS ALREADY THREE LETTERS SUBMITTED.
BUT A MAN BEHIND ME WILL BE READING JOE PADILLA'S LETTER
BECAUSE HE HAD TO LEAVE THE CITY LAST NIGHT BECAUSE HIS MOM
HAS HAD A STROKE SO DOWN IN CENTRAL CALIFORNIA.
>> SO HE WILL NOT BE HERE TODAY UNFORTUNATELY HE DID TRY TO
COME FOR THE LAST TWO SCHEDULED HEARINGS BUT SINCE THEY WERE
CONTINUED I WAS ABLE TO CATCH HIM BEFORE HE RAN OUT THE DOOR.
SO SO YOU WILL HEAR FROM THIS NEXT PERSON WHO WILL RECITE FOR
JOE AGAIN THIS THIS WAS A SITE OF FOUR FOR FOUR HOUSEHOLDS.
NOW IT IS FOR ONE HOUSEHOLD. THIS IS A POLICY ISSUE.
THIS IS THIS IS THE HISTORY OF THESE KIND OF ILLEGAL MERGERS
BEING DONE. THE OWNERS MAY NOT HAVE KNOWN
NOT HAVE DONE THAT. >> HOWEVER, THE CURRENT OWNERS
DID KNOW CONTRARY TO WHAT THEY STATED IN THE PLANNING
COMMISSION HEARING DECEMBER 4TH WE DIDN'T KNOW THEN YOU HEAR
LATER WELL, ACTUALLY THEY DID KNOW THERE WAS CLEARLY A
DECLARATION OF IT BEING A FOUR UNIT OR A MULTIFAMILY BUILDING
SO IT'S REALLY HARD TO HEAR THIS MISREPRESENTATION BUT WE
WANT TO BE SURE YOU UNDERSTAND THERE WERE FOUR UNITS THERE
AND WE ARE SO AFRAID OF IF THIS PASSES IT SETS A HORRIBLE
PRECEDENT. WE KNOW THAT THERE ARE FIVE
BUILDING OWNERS RIGHT NOW HOPING THAT THIS THAT YOU WILL
PASS THIS THAT YOU WILL THAT YOU WILL NOT DENY THE APPEAL
BUT YOU MUST YOU MUST NOT BE COMPLICIT IN ALLOWING THE
REMOVAL THE PERMANENT RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING THAT WE
HAVE. YOU CANNOT ALLOW THAT.
SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS LANCE CARNES AND I'M HERE TO READ THE STATEMENT BY
JOSEPH PADILLA WHO WAS CALLED OUT OF TOWN BECAUSE OF A
MEDICAL EMERGENCY. HE WRITES I LIVED IT FOR A SAN
ANTONIO PLACE STARTING IN 1990 WHEN I BECAME AWARE THAT THE
BUILDING WOULDN'T THAT THAT WOULD BE PLACED ON THE MARKET.
I MADE THE DECISION TO TRANSITION MY CURRENT ADDRESS
IN NO WAY VALLEY IN 2009. >> I CAN ATTEST THAT THERE WERE
FOUR INDIVIDUAL RENTAL UNITS AT 524 VALLEJO STREET TO FULL
FLATS IN THE FRONT AT AND FOUR A AND FOUR B SAN ANTONIO PLACE
WHICH WERE TWO FULLY FUNCTIONING AND LIVABLE STUDIO
APARTMENTS ATTACHED TO THE BACK OF THE BUILDING.
I LIVED IN ONE OF THE TWO IDENTICAL STUDIOS EACH OF WHICH
WAS COMPRISED OF TWO ROOMS A LIVING AREA BEDROOM AND A
SEPARATE FULL SIZE KITCHEN DINING AREA AND A BATHROOM.
EACH STUDIO WAS LARGER THAN THE 100FT2 REFERENCED IN THE
APPELLANT'S BRIEF THE STUDIOS INCLUDED FULL FUNCTIONING
METERED UTILITY SO WERE INTENDED AS DWELLING UNITS.
WHEN I MOVED OUT MY UNIT WAS IN A HABITABLE CONDITION AFTER
I LEFT IT WAS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT THE STUDIO WAS NEVER
REOCCUPIED AND I WAS USED AS A AND IT WAS USED AS A STORAGE BY
THE DEVELOPER IN ADDITION THERE WAS A SMALL LAUNDRY ROOM ON THE
ROOF AS WELL AS A TWO CAR GARAGE AND BASEMENT STORAGE.
I HOPE THAT MY ACCOUNT PROVIDES YOU WITH SOME FIRSTHAND
PERSPECTIVE AND ENCOURAGES STRONG STRONGER SCRUTINY OF
FUTURE HOUSING PROPOSALS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME
AND CONSIDERATION. >> JOHN JOSEPH G.
PADILLA THANK YOU LANCE AHRENS FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. THANK YOU.
MY NAME IS JERRY DE RATTLER. THE PROPERTY OWNERS APPEAL IS
BASED ON TWO FALSE CLAIMS. THE PROPERTY OWNERS CLAIM THAT
YOU KNOW IT'S FOR AND FOR A SAN ANTONIO PLACE ARE PHANTOM UNITS
THAT WERE NEVER CONSTRUCTED AS A FALSE CLAIM THAT IS REFUTED
BY A LETTER FROM JOHN GRANT WHICH IS IN THE BOARD PACKAGE.
MR. GRANT LIVED IN A UNIT FOR A RENT CONTROLLED UNIT FOR 17
YEARS. THE PROPERTY OWNERS SECOND
INITIAL CLAIM THAT THEY WERE UNAWARE THEY PURCHASED A FOUR
UNIT BUILDING WITH A SINGLE FAMILY FLOOR PLAN IS ALSO
FALSE. THE PROPERTY OWNERS RECENTLY
ACKNOWLEDGED THEY KNEW THE HOUSE WAS A MULTI UNIT BUILDING
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THE PLANNING COMMISSION DENIED THE
PROPERTY OWNERS Q APPLICATION FOR A VALID REASONS THE
CRITERIA FOR THE BOARD TO OVERTURN THE PLANNING
COMMISSION DECISION HAS NOT BEEN MET.
THERE WERE NO ERRORS IN INTERPRETING THE PLANNING
CODE AND THE ABUSE OF DISCRETION BY THE PLANNING
COMMISSION DID NOT OCCUR. IT WOULD BE WRONG FOR THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS TO LEGALIZE THE UNPERMITTED UNIT CONVERSIONS
IN A HOUSING CRISIS. IF THIS WERE TO HAPPEN THE
PUBLIC WOULD VIEW THE BOARD'S ACTION TO BE AMNESTY ON
UNPERMITTED READ UNIT MERGERS AND THERE WOULD BE HUNDREDS OF
PROPERTY OWNERS ASKING FOR THE SAME RELIEF.
IN SUMMARY TWO WRONGS DON'T MAKE A RIGHT THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HI. I'M A LIFELONG NORTH BEACH
RESIDENT. MY PARENTS MET IN NORTH BEACH
AND ALL OF MY SIBLINGS GREW UP THERE.
IN THE LAST SIX YEARS EVERYBODY'S BEEN PRETTY MUCH
PRICED OUT OF NORTH BEACH 13 EVICTIONS BETWEEN MY SISTERS,
MY PARENTS AND MYSELF BETWEEN VERITAS DEVELOPERS, PREDATORY
LANDLORDS, REAL ESTATE DEVELOPERS.
THERE'S JUST SINCE 2013 THERE'S BEEN A NUMBER OF ILLEGAL
EVICTIONS. I MEAN THE NUMBER OF SERVICE
PEOPLE THAT ARE PUSHED OUT OF NORTH BEACH ON A DAILY BASIS
OVER 200 PEOPLE I WANTED TO INVITE TODAY TO THIS EVENT HAVE
BEEN PUSHED OUT THERE CAREER SERVICE WORKERS THAT WORK
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND ONE WELL, I FEEL BAD FOR THE BUYER
AND I GET THAT THIS REALLY FOR YOU BUT IT SETS AN EXAMPLE THAT
OTHER PEOPLE ARE GOING TO CONTINUE TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF.
AND RIGHT NOW WE CONTINUOUSLY HAVE BULLDOZERS CIRCLING
WASHINGTON SQUARE PARK. WE HAVE THE THE VERY DAY
BUILDING WHICH WE'RE BATTLING EVERY DAY TO BE ABLE TO
PRESERVE. IT'S EMBARRASSING THAT OUR
REPRESENTATIVE ISN'T FIGHTING FOR US AND NORTH BEACH DOESN'T
RUN WITHOUT HOUSING FOR SERVICE WORKERS AND MAKE IT RIGHT NOW
MUDDYING THE WATER AND MAKING THIS LIKE INTENTIONAL RATHER
THAN SUPPORTING THE CONSTITUENTS THAT FEEL SO
STRONGLY THAT RENT CONTROLLED UNITS NEED TO BE SAVED
AND TAKING ANY UNITS AT ALL OFF THE MARKET SETS A VERY
DANGEROUS PRECEDENT. >> THANK YOU.
THANKS FOR COMING. SO THE NEXT WEEK A PLACE GOOD
AFTERNOON GEORGIA SHOOT ISH. THE ISSUES WITH THIS APPEAL ARE
VERY CLEAR. >> 524 526 FOR LEO STREET
AND FOR A FOR FOR SAN ANTONIO PLACE ARE IS ILLEGAL FOR UNIT
BUILDING. THE BOARD MUST DENY THIS APPEAL
AND HERE'S WHY. >> FIRST THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S RECOMMENDATION TO DENY THE SEAWAY AS A DECEMBER
4TH, 2025 HEARING CLEARLY STATES THAT THIS PROJECT
PROPOSED BY THE APPELLANTS WOULD NOT COMPLY WITH THE
HOUSING ELEMENT. SECOND, THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
CLEARLY RESPONDS TO THE FIVE ISSUES IN THEIR MEMO TO THE
BOARD DATED JANUARY 28TH 2026 ON PAGES FOUR THROUGH SIX THE
FIVE RESPONSES ARE EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD THAT THIS
BUILDING IS A FOUR UNIT BUILDING INCLUDING THE WRITTEN
TESTIMONY FROM FORMER TENANTS. >> THE DENIAL AT THE COMMISSION
HEARING FOR THE CIA WAS BASED ON THE OBJECTIVES AND POLICIES
OF THE HOUSING ELEMENT. >> THE THREE YOUR REPORT
UNEQUIVOCALLY STATES THAT THE BUILDING IS FOUR UNITS
AND SHOULD HAVE BEEN IN THE DISCLOSURE MEASURES AT THE TIME
OF SALE TO THE APPELLANTS. THE APPELLANTS PURCHASED A
LEGAL FOUR UNIT BUILDING THAT HAD BEEN ILLEGALLY MERGED.
EVEN IF IT APPEARED TO BE A SINGLE FAMILY HOME, THE
PROPOSAL PUT FORTH BY THE APPELLANTS WOULD ONLY REPLACE
ONE OF THE THREE LEGAL UNITS THAT WERE REMOVED.
>> SO THAT'S WHAT'S BEFORE YOU. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THINK FOR YOUR COMMENTS. SO THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ON TILE OUR ENTIRE WITH THE RECENT
EQUITY IN ALL PLANNING COALITION WE ARE STRONGLY
OPPOSED TO THE SEAWAY APPEAL AND URGE THIS BOARD TO DENY THE
PROPOSAL TO APPROVE THIS ILLEGAL CONVERSION.
>> WE SHARE THE DEEP CONCERNS THAT THE S.F. ANTI DISPLACEMENT
COALITION HAS SUBMITTED IN THEIR LETTER AND I ALSO WANT
TO STRONGLY EMPHASIZE THAT APPROVING THIS APPEAL
UNDERMINES THE CITY'S OWN POLICIES AND VIOLATES THE
HOUSING ELEMENT AND ITS STATED GOALS.
>> AS A STAFF REPORT LAYS OUT IN GREAT DETAIL THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL IS BASED ON THE
OBJECTIVES POLICIES OF THE HOUSING ELEMENT.
>> GIVEN ANYTHING SHORT OF RESTORING THE THREE LOST UNITS
WOULD RESULT IN A NET LOSS OF DWELLING UNITS AND CONCERTED
NEGATIVE PRECEDENT WHERE DEVELOPERS MAY MERGE DWELLING
UNITS WITHOUT AUTHORIZATION KNOWING THAT A MERGER IS LIKELY
TO BE APPROVED AND LEGALIZED AFTER THE FACT OF THIS PROCESS.
>> I ALSO WANT TO EMPHASIZE HOUSING ELEMENT IMPLEMENTATION
PROGRAM TO SPECIFICALLY THE IMPLEMENTING ACTIONS SECTION
2.4 PRESERVING RENTAL UNIT AVAILABILITY.
>> APPROVING THE CTA WOULD CLEARLY BE A DIRECT VIOLATION
OF THE SET OF ACTIONS AS THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS DISCUSSED
AT GREAT LENGTH JUST IN THE PAST YEAR ESPECIALLY
IN DELIBERATION OVER THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN AND THE TENANT
PROTECTIONS ORDINANCE. WE SHOULD BE DOING AS MUCH AS
POSSIBLE TO PRESERVE OUR EXISTING HOUSING STOCK
AND PROTECT HOMES AND TENANTS AND ACTIVELY CHALLENGE EFFORTS
SUCH AS THIS REQUEST THAT UNDERMINE THESE CRITICAL
POLICIES. >> WE URGE YOU ALL TO DENY THE
APPELLANT'S PROPOSAL THAT BOTH VIOLATES AND UNDERCUTS OUR OWN
CRITICAL HOUSING POLICIES AS WELL AS PREVENT SETTING A
DANGEROUS PRECEDENT THAT THREATENS TO DIMINISH OUR
HOUSING STOCK AND PUT TENANTS IN INCREASED RISK.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT WEEK A PLACE. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS
PETER STEVENS BUILD AFFORDABLE FASTER CALIFORNIA.
I THINK ONE THING WE CAN ALL AGREE ON IS THAT ISKANDER IS A
. >> COULDN'T PUT IT BETTER
MYSELF. BUT THE QUESTION BEFORE US
TODAY IS VERY VERY SIMPLE. >> WILL YOU THE BOARD CREATE A
PRECEDENCE OF PERFORMATIVE NEGLIGENCE IN OUR CITIES LAND
USE DOCTRINE? THAT'S WHAT'S HAPPENING HERE
TODAY IS THE ASSERTION THAT SOMEONE WHO WAS BLIND, DEAF
AND DUMB TO THE OBVIOUS ISSUES AND DISCLOSURES BUT MAGICALLY
SIGNED ON ALL THE PROPER DOTTED LINES IS A VALID DEFENSE
AGAINST OUR CITY CODES. IF SO, THEN WHAT ARE THE USE OF
CITY CODES? I KNOW THAT EACH OF YOU
UNDERSTANDS WHAT IS AT STAKE AND YOU HAVE IT IN YOU TO DO
THE RIGHT THING. >> THANK YOU ALL AND HAVE A
GOOD EVENING. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
I AM MEG HEISLER. I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO ANTI DISPLACEMENT COALITION TO VOICE OUR STRONG
OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL BEFORE YOU TODAY.
>> NOT TO BEAT A DEAD HORSE BUT PUBLIC RECORDS PROVIDE
UNEQUIVOCAL EVIDENCE THAT THE LAWFUL AND PERMITTED USE OF
THIS BUILDING WAS AND IS AS A FOUR UNIT APARTMENT BUILDING.
WE KNOW TENANTS LIVED IN THESE UNITS AND THAT FOUR RENT
CONTROLLED UNITS WERE ILLEGALLY DEMOLISHED.
>> THIS IS NOT CONJECTURE. THIS IS WHAT HAPPENED.
SO WHAT YOU'RE WEIGHING IS WHETHER OR NOT TO GRANT AN
EXCEPTION TO THE LAWS ON THE BOOKS AND APPROVE THE LOSS OF
RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING. WHILE NO DOUBT THERE ARE
DEVELOPERS SIZING UP TENANT OCCUPIED BUILDINGS IN EACH OF
YOUR DISTRICTS AND FANTASIZING ABOUT WHAT THEY CAN GET AWAY
WITH. >> THIS IS A POLICY DECISION.
THE STAKES IN THIS CASE EXTEND WELL BEYOND ONE FAMILY.
IF THE BOARD OVERRIDES THE FINDINGS OF PLANNING STAFF
AND THE PLANNING COMMISSION IT WOULD BE CREATING A SIGNIFICANT
NEW LOOPHOLE TO OUR EXISTING LAWS THAT PROTECT RENT
CONTROLLED UNITS. THE TENANTS WHO LIVE IN THEM
NOW AND THOSE WHO WILL NEED THEM THAT HOUSING IN THE FUTURE
AS THE CITY'S REAL ESTATE MARKET FOR SINGLE FAMILY HOMES
HEATS UP. THERE IS SIMPLY NO WAY FOR
TENANTS TO COMPETE AGAINST AN INDUSTRY OF DEVELOPERS
AND REALTORS THAT PROFIT OFF OF THEIR DISPLACEMENT CANNIBALIZE
RENTAL UNITS AND REPURPOSE THEM A SINGLE FAMILY HOMES TO BE
SOLD FOR MILLIONS. >> IN THIS CASE THERE ARE NO
COMPROMISES THAT WILL NOT SERVE TO UNDERMINE EXISTING
PROTECTIONS OF RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING AND EMBOLDEN
SPECULATORS. THIS BOARD MUST SEND AN
EMPHATIC MESSAGE THAT YOU WILL NOT SUPPORT THE DEMOLITION OF
RENT CONTROLLED UNITS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS NEXT WEEK.
PLEASE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SPEAKERS.
I'M SUPERVISORS. I'M MITCHELL.
I'M DIRECTOR OF THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING ALLIANCE AND WE WORK
WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO ANTI DISPLACEMENT COALITION.
AND I DO WANT TO NOTE THAT THIS IS A POLICY QUESTION BUT I ALSO
WANT TO JUST TALK ABOUT WHAT HAPPENED HERE.
>> THERE WERE FLASHING YELLOW WAIT, NO FLASHING RED LIGHTS.
OKAY. THIS WAS CLEARLY LEGALLY A FOUR
UNIT RATE CONTROLLED BUILDING FOR STARTERS AND IT HAS FOUR
SEPARATE STREET ADDRESSES THEN WE'RE LEARNING TODAY IT
APPARENTLY HAD FOUR SEPARATE ELECTRICAL METERS.
THE THREE ARE REPORT WHICH IS YOUR DISCLOSURE WHEN YOU BUY
PROPERTY THAT YOU NEED TO LOOK AT DISCLOSE THAT IT WAS A FOUR
UNIT BUILDING THE PROPERTY TAX RECORD AND THE PROPERTY TAX
BILL SAY THAT IT'S FOUR UNITS AND THEN EVEN TODAY YOU KNOW
WOULD BE A LITTLE BIT BETTER IF THEY WERE A LITTLE MORE
CONTRITE. BUT EVEN TODAY WE'RE KIND OF
HEARING THAT MAYBE THERE WERE NEVER REALLY ANY TENANTS THERE
BUT TENANTS FROM ALL FOUR UNITS HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED BY THE
NORTH BEACH TENANTS COMMITTEE AND THREE OF THEM HAVE BEEN
CONTACTED AND NOW WE'RE SORT OF TRYING TO ERASE THAT THEY EVER
EXISTED. >> PLEASE VOTE TO UPHOLD THE
PLANNING COMMISSION'S REJECTION OF MERGING FOUR OR RENT CONTROL
UNITS INTO A MEGA-MANSION THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HI. THANK YOU.
BOARD MY NAME IS RAMONA SCHMALTZ AND I'VE BEEN IN NORTH
BEACH ABOUT 20 YEARS AS A RENTER.
THIS CASE IS EMOTIONAL BECAUSE IT INVOLVES US TENANTS LOSING
MORE PRECIOUS AND INFINITE AND FINITE RENT CONTROLLED
HOUSING AND A VERY WEALTHY FAMILY WHO DOESN'T WANT TO LOSE
WHAT THEY HAVE. BUT TO SPEAK PLAINLY THIS
COUPLE KNOWINGLY BOUGHT STOLEN GOODS GOODS STOLEN FROM THE
RENTERS OF THE CITY. >> THE MAJORITY OF SAN
FRANCISCANS AND YOUR CONCERN AND YOUR CONSTITUENTS WERE THE
RENTERS. >> THIS COUPLE IS CRYING
AND ACTING LIKE THEY'RE BEING EVICTED FROM NORTH BEACH.
>> THEY'RE NOT EITHER. AND HOW ARE THE BULK OF THE
REMAIN IS ANOTHER MATTER. THEY CAN BUY A DIFFERENT HOUSE
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND THEIR KIDS CAN STILL ATTEND THE SAME
SCHOOLS. THEY JUST CAN'T KEEP THEIR
STOLEN GOODS. >> WE NEED LEADERS WHO DO RIGHT
BY RENTERS AND BY THE LAW. >> I'M NOT ASKING YOU TO PUNISH
THIS FAMILY FOR KNOWINGLY BUYING AN ILLEGAL MANSION.
>> THIS FAMILY WILL BE FINE. >> I'M REMINDING YOU THAT WE
HAVE TENANTS WHO ARE ON THE RECORD AS HAVING LIVED THERE
AND WERE SQUEEZED OUT BY WHATEVER WHAT OUR SUPERVISOR
CALLED THE REAL BAD ACTORS. >> BUT WE TENANTS OF NORTH
BEACH STRONGLY AGREE THAT KNOWINGLY BUYING ILLEGAL GOODS
MAKES YOU A BAD ACTOR. >> I'VE RENTED IN NORTH BEACH
FOR 20 YEARS AND I'VE SEEN THE SHADY WORK ALL TOO MUCH.
IT'S LIKE SUDDENLY FOUR METERS BECOMES TWO METERS AND I MEAN
I'VE SEEN A LOT. >> THERE'S YET ANOTHER EXAMPLE
JUST ONE BLOCK UP BELOW FROM WHERE WE ARE.
>> IF I WENT FROM WHERE THEY ARE MY FRIENDS AND FAMILY
IN NORTH BEACH THOUSANDS OF RENTERS ARE WATCHING TODAY
AND DOZENS OF THEM HAVE ALREADY EXPRESSED UTTER DISBELIEF THAT
THEIR REPRESENTATIVE ON THIS BOARD IS SIDING WITH A COUPLE
OVER ALL OF US EVEN WHEN THEY ARE IN THE WRONG.
>> WE YOU CANNOT SEND A MESSAGE THAT THIS IS OKAY.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
ONE OF THESE STATEMENT STATEMENTS IS TRUE.
WHEN THIS PLAN CAME THROUGH EITHER SOMEONE IN THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT WAS ASLEEP OR THEY WERE PAID OFF WITH THE HOPE
THAT THIS PROJECT WOULD SLIDE UNDER THE RADAR.
EITHER WAY, THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT OFFICIALS WHO
ALLOWED THIS EGREGIOUS MALFEASANCE TO GO THROUGH DO
NOT DESERVE THEIR PLACE IN OFFICE.
THE FACT THAT THIS PROJECT IS EVEN BEING CONSIDERED IS
INEXCUSABLE. THE OTHER TRUTH IS THAT OUR
SUPERVISOR IS A FESTERING SORE ACTIVELY WOUND IN NORTH BEACH
AND THE WOUNDS HE IS INFLICTING WILL HAVE A LEGACY OF
DESTRUCTION FOR THE ENTIRE CITY.
OUR SUPERVISOR DOESN'T CARE ABOUT NORTH BEACH.
HE DOESN'T CARE ABOUT HOUSING. HE ONLY CARES ABOUT REAL ESTATE
. BITING AT THE COATTAILS OF
WIENER AND LINING HIS POCKETS IN THE POCKETS OF HIS DEVELOPER
BUDDIES. IF THE DEVELOPMENT FOR THESE
WEALTHY, UNSCRUPULOUS AND CONSCIOUS AFFORDABLE HOME
DESTROYING ARROGANCE IS APPROVED AND ALLOWED TO PROCEED
FOR ANY REASON EVEN THE MOST RIDICULOUS LIE OF OVERSIGHT OR
WORSE WE DON'T KNOW WE COULD DO THAT.
YOU ARE SETTING A VERY DANGEROUS PRECEDENT AND IT
WOULD GIVE OUR SUPERVISOR EXACTLY WHAT HE WANTS TO TEAR
DOWN ALL RESTRICTIONS FOR DEVELOPMENT IN S.F. BECAUSE
THAT'S HIS GOAL. THAT'S THE END GAME FOR THIS
DEVELOPER, HIS DEVELOPER FRIENDS AND THAT'S WHAT
WEINER'S GREEDY POCKETS ALSO WANT HIM TO DO.
AND JUST TO REMIND YOU, WE ALL KNOW WHAT SIDE YOU WILL SIT ON
IN THE NEXT ELECTION AND IF YOU APPROVE THIS PROJECT YOU WILL
BE A LARGE CAUSE OF THE RUIN OF OUR BELOVED SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND SHAME WILL BE YOUR MIDDLE NAMES.
>> THANK YOU FOR COMING. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> WELL OKAY. MY NAME IS KEN FUJIOKA.
I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF CHINATOWN COMMUNITY CENTER AND I WANT TO
ADDRESS OR EMPHASIZE THE POINT THAT THE PLANNING STAFF RAISED
THAT APPROVING THIS TO YOU IS GOING TO CREATE A VERY DAMAGING
PRECEDENT AND WE'RE OUR ORGANIZATION COUNSELS TENANTS
ALL THE TIME THREATENED WITH BUYOUTS OF THREATENED
DEVELOPMENT. WE HAVE ONE RIGHT NOW WHERE WE
KNOW THE OWNERS ARE PLANNING TO MERGE THE UNITS AND THE OWNERS
ARE GOING TO ELICIT AND THEY'RE GOING TO THEY'RE GOING TO TRY
TO JAM IT THROUGH AND AND IN APPROVING THIS IT'S GOING TO
GIVE A SIGNAL THAT YOU CAN GO FORWARD AND DOING SUCH BEHAVIOR
AND GET AWAY AND SELL THE PROPERTY OFF AND LET SOMEONE
ELSE PAY A PRICE FOR SURE. AND I WANT TO GET TO THE OWNERS
SITUATION TOO. I, I FEEL FOR THEM BUT BUT WE
HAVE WE WE THE CONTACT WE ME THE THE CONSEQUENCE ISN'T JUST
THIS FAMILY AS SOMEONE ELSE SAID BEFORE BUT IT IS THERE ARE
600 BUYOUTS LAST YEAR A THREATENED BUYOUT MORE THAN
HALF OF THEM WENT THROUGH AND MOST OF THE TENANTS HAVE NO
BARGAINING POSITION BECAUSE THEY GET EVICTED, THEY GET LOST
AND THEY GO NOWHERE OR THEY LEAVE AS IN THIS CASE TWO OF
THE HOUSEHOLDS LEFT THE CITY AND SO THAT'S THE FIRST THING.
I ALSO WANT TO SAY THAT I'M REALLY TROUBLED BY THE ACTIONS
ATION BASED ON NO EVIDENCE THAT THERE WAS SOME KIND OF
MALFEASANCE ON THE PART OF STAFF IN THIS CASE WHETHER
STEVIE I OR PLANNING STAFF I MEAN WE HAVE FIRE PARTMENT
OTHERS FOLKS ALL WITNESSING THREE LET'S BLAME THE DEVELOPER
YES BUT WE ALSO NEED TO UPHOLD THE RULE THAT IF YOU BUY A FOUR
UNIT BUILDING THAT SAYS IT'S A LEGAL PERFORMING UNIT YOU THAT
THAT'S WHAT IT SHOULD STAY AND WE HAVE TO KEEP RENT
CONTROL HOUSING AVAILABLE FOR PEOPLE BECAUSE THOSE ARE THE
FOLKS WHO ARE LOSING OUT WHO ARE NOT BEING SPOKEN ABOUT
IN THE NARRATIVE OF THE OWNERS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS
WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL? ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED. AND LASTLY, WE'LL HAVE THE
APPELLANT COME OUT TO PRESENT A REBUTTAL ARGUMENT OF UP TO
THREE MINUTES. >> FIRST, THANK YOU TO THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR YOUR PRESENTATION.
WE KNOW THAT THIS HAS BEEN AN ARDUOUS PROCESS AND IT'S BEEN
FOR YEARS AND WE'RE REALLY, REALLY GRATEFUL FOR YOUR
PARTNERSHIP AND WE'RE SORRY THAT THIS HAS LANDED ON ALL OF
OUR PLATES. BUT COLLECTIVELY WE KNOW YOU'VE
SPENT A LOT OF TIME SO THANK YOU AND THANK YOU AGAIN TO THE
SUPERVISORS FOR CONSIDERING THE FACTS OF THIS CASE NO MATTER
THE OUTCOME. WE ARE VERY GRATEFUL FOR YOUR
TIME. I WANT TO CLARIFY A FEW POINTS
FOR THE RECORD BEFORE I HAND IT OVER TO STEPHEN TO OUR
ARCHITECT. THE FIRST IS THE ROOM ONE
DESIGNATION ALLOWS FOR 2.4 UNITS BASED ON A 1920 FOOT
SQUARE FOOT LOT. THIS IS BASED ON THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S OWN STAFF REPORT, NOT OUR INTERPRETATION OF THE
REPORT. SO PLEASE NOTE THAT THE 2017
INSPECTION INCLUDED BY DVI INCLUDED FIVE SIGN FINAL SIGN
OFFS INTERIOR AND EXTERIOR. THE NOTION THAT THIS INSPECTOR
ONLY VIEWED THE ROOF IS TROUBLING BECAUSE THE ELEVATOR
DOES NOT GO UP TO THE ROOF. THE INSPECTOR WOULD HAVE TO
COME THROUGH THE HOME AND WOULD HAVE DIRECTLY FACED BEEN
DIRECTLY FACED WITH THE MOST EGREGIOUS VIOLATION.
AS FOR THE 2022 DBI INSPECTION THAT INSPECTION NEVER OCCURRED
. THAT IS INCREDIBLY TROUBLING
FOR US AS THE HOMEOWNERS AS WE WERE LIVING AT THE PROPERTY AT
THE TIME. THE FIRST AND ONLY TIME DBA HAS
STEPPED FOOT INTO OUR HOME AFTER OUR PURCHASE WAS JUST A
FEW WEEKS AGO. ON PRECEDENT WE VERY MUCH
UNDERSTAND THAT CONCERN. WE ALSO UNDERSTAND THE CONCERNS
OF EVERYONE WHO SPOKE. HOUSING IS ABSOLUTELY A CRISIS
IN THIS COMMUNITY. THE POSITION HOWEVER, ONLY
WORKS IF THE SITUATION IS REPUTED REPEATABLE.
>> THIS IS NOT A PLAYBOOK OR A REPEATABLE FACT PATTERN AS
DEMONSTRATED BY ALL OF THE ERRORS FORCED ALONG THE WAY.
THIS IS A SOPHISTICATED DEVELOPER WHO UNDERSTANDS HOW
TO GAME AND OPERATE WITHIN THE SYSTEM INCLUDING INSTALLING
METERS AND OTHER THINGS THAT GIVE THE ILLUSION OF FOUR
COMPLETE UNITS. I'D LIKE FOR OUR ARCHITECT
STEPHEN TO TRY TO PLEASE GIVE A BIT MORE COLOR.
BUT IN THE MEANTIME THANK YOU AGAIN FOR YOUR TIME.
>> YOU HAVE A MINUTE AND 10S LEFT.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
HELLO. MY NAME IS STEPHEN SUTRO.
I'M THE ARCHITECT. I AM AN ARCHITECT HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND I WAS BORN AND RAISED HERE.
I WAS HIRED BY CAITLIN AND BEN WHEN THEY WERE NOTIFIED OF THE
PLANNING VIOLATION. I JUST WANT TO POINT OUT THAT
THE LISTING PHOTOS THAT WERE PART OF THE PACKET MATCHED
EXACTLY WHAT IS THERE TODAY. NO CHANGES HAVE OCCURRED
BETWEEN THE TIME THAT THOSE REALTOR PHOTOS WERE GENERATED
AND TODAY THE DEVELOPER GOT FOUR UNITS APPROVED AND THEN
ONLY BUILT ONE. THERE ARE MANY PHYSICAL
ELEMENTS IN THE BUILDING THAT ARE SIGNIFICANTLY DIFFERENT
THAN HIS APPROVED PLANS. THE MAIN STAIRCASE IS DESIGNED
TO SERVE MULTIPLE UNITS AS AN EXIT CORRIDOR.
IT HAS TO HAVE FIRE RATED WALLS AROUND IT.
INSTEAD IT'S BUILT AS A FLOATING STAIRCASE AND THAT
FLOATING STAIRCASE IS IN REALTOR PHOTOS THAT WERE
GENERATED AT THE TIME ONE MONTH AFTER INSPECTION.
THAT'S JUST IMPOSSIBLE. IT'S JUST SIMPLY IMPOSSIBLE.
I JUST WANT TO POINT OUT THAT IT PHYSICALLY COULD NOT HAVE
BEEN TRANSFORMED IN THAT QUICK OF A TIME FRAME.
SO THERE'S JUST A BIG DISCREPANCY HERE FROM WHAT WAS
APPROVED BY THE DEVELOPER AND WHAT WHAT WAS PURCHASED BY
THE OWNER JUST BEFORE CAITLIN AND BEN.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
>> THANK YOU. I THINK THE THING THAT I AM
MOST KIND OF CONFUSED AND CONCERNED ABOUT IS THIS
2016 SIGN OFF THAT LEGALIZED THE CHANGE FROM TWO UNITS TO
FOUR UNITS. >> AND YOU KNOW, BETWEEN THE
PHOTOGRAPHS OF THE APARTMENT WITH A FLOATING STAIRCASE WHICH
I CANNOT IMAGINE A DBA INSPECTOR WOULD HAVE SIGNED OFF
ON AS A STANDARD MEANS OF EGRESS NOR CAN I IMAGINE THAT
IT WOULD TAKE ONE MONTH OR 45 DAYS TO DEMOLISH A CENTRAL
EGRESS WITH FIRE RATED DOORS AND INSTALL A FLOATING
STAIRCASE. I DON'T KNOW WHAT CONTRACTOR
CAN GET THAT DONE ON TIME BUT PROBABLY NOT ONE AND AND THEN
ALSO THE FACT THAT THIS INSPECTOR WAS ALSO UNDER
INVESTIGATION AT TBI. HOW HOW AM I SUPPOSED TO SQUARE
ALL THOSE CIRCLES BEFORE ME? I DON'T KNOW.
I GUESS. YEAH.
YEAH. >> SURE.
YEAH. WELL, I THINK IT'S FAIR TO SAY
THAT INSPECTOR WAS UNDER INVESTIGATION.
>> HE WAS AN INVESTIGATOR FOR COMPLETELY UNRELATED MATTER.
>> SO HE WAS THOUGH. I'M SORRY.
HE WAS THOUGH MAYBE. YES, BUT.
>> BUT HE WAS. YES.
ALL RIGHT. >> YEAH.
LIKE I SAID, WE READ THE NOTICE OF VIOLATION.
WE'RE GOING TO BE REACHING OUT TO THE ISKANDER AND JUSTIN
PARKER WAS ANOTHER DEVELOPER INVOLVED TO SEE WHAT EXACTLY
HAPPENED HERE. I I IT DOES SOUND INCREDULOUS.
THIS HAPPENED IN 45 DAYS. I AGREE.
>> I'M TRYING TO LOOK BACK TEN YEARS AND IT SOUNDS INCREDULOUS
THAT THE PERMIT LEGALIZING THE FOUR UNIT MIX WAS ISSUED
PROPERLY. AND THAT'S I THINK THE CRUX OF
WHERE I'M STRUGGLING. YOUR EYES MAKE IT SEEM AS IF
MAYBE MY ANALYSIS WAS OFF WHEN YOU SAY THAT.
>> NO, NO. I JUST DON'T KNOW IF I'M
MISUNDERSTANDING. SHOULD I?
YOU'RE YOU SAY IT'S INCREDULOUS THE PERMIT WAS ISSUED.
RIGHT. THAT'S THAT'S ONE STAGE OF THE
PROBLEM IS ISSUED. AND THEN WE'RE ALSO TALKING
ABOUT THE END FIVE YEARS LATER WHEN THE THE JARVIS SIGNED OFF
IT WAS NOT SIGNED. >> THE ACCUSATIONS ARE THAT IT
WAS NOT BUILT ACCORDING TO THE APPROVED PLANS.
>> I I'M JUST I'M JUST TALKING ABOUT THE THE IT SEEMS TO ME
LIKE THE PERMIT FOR A FOUR UNIT LEGALIZATION WAS SIGNED OFF
IN 2016, RIGHT? CORRECT.
AND SO MAYBE I'M MISUNDERSTANDING HERE.
IS IT SUCH THAT THE WORK DID NOT WAS.
DOES THAT MEAN THAT THE WORK FOR A FOR YOU IN A BUILDING HAD
TO BE COMPLETED THEN OR IT COULD BE STARTED THEN
AND COMPLETED LATER? >> THAT WAS THE END OF IT.
>> THAT WAS WHEN THE WORK WAS SUPPOSED TO BE COMPLETED.
THE PERMIT WAS INITIALLY RIGHT .
AND SO IF THE WORK WAS COMPLETED THEN AND THEN 45 DAYS
LATER WE'VE GOT A FLOATING STAIRCASE THAT IS MAGICALLY
REPLACED. THAT'S WHAT I'M SAYING.
THAT'S THE CRUX OF WHERE I CANNOT I AM INCREDULOUS THAT
THAT 2016 LEGALIZATION WAS SIGNED OFF ON CORRECTLY.
THAT'S THAT'S WHAT I'M STRUGGLING WITH.
WE HAVE PEOPLE IN THE QUEUE BUT I DO HAVE A QUESTION.
I MEAN SO THERE'S ASSUMING THAT DBA INSPECTORS ARE DOING THEIR
JOB AND THAT THE FIRE INSPECTORS ARE DOING THEIR JOB,
THEY'RE LOOKING IN 2016 AND MULTIPLE TIMES THEY'RE
SAYING THERE'S FOUR UNITS THERE MLS.
>> I MEAN WHEN THIS THING IS LISTED REAL ESTATE INDUSTRY
SAYS THIS IS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME.
A FEW MONTHS, A COUPLE A MONTH AND A HALF LATER.
IS THAT IS THAT KIND OF WHAT WE THINK HAS HAPPENED HERE?
>> I GUESS I GUESS MY POINT IS LIKE YOU ALL CITY STAFF HAVE
NOTHING TO DO WITH WHAT A PRIVATE TRANSACTION WHAT PEOPLE
ARE SAYING IS THERE. WE KNOW THERE'S ESSENTIALLY A
SINGLE FAMILY HOME THERE NOW IN 2026.
WE THINK IF WE TRUST MULTIPLE INSPECTORS FROM DIFFERENT CITY
DEPARTMENTS GOING OUT IN 2016 THERE WERE FOUR UNITS BUT
THERE'S NOT NECESSARILY I MEAN MAYBE SOMEONE DIDN'T SEEN AN
INSANE AMOUNT OF UNAUTHORIZED WORK IN A MONTH AND A HALF TO
GET THIS THING CLOSER TO BEING A SINGLE FAMILY HOME AND THE
PRIOR OWNER BOUGHT SOMETHING THAT MAYBE WASN'T DIDN'T FEEL
EXACTLY LIKE FOUR UNITS OR MAYBE DIDN'T FEEL EXACTLY LIKE
ONE UNIT EITHER. >> AND THEN THERE'S MORE
UNAUTHORIZED WORK THAT HAPPENS SORT OF WHILE THAT PRIOR
PROPERTY OWNER OWNS. I MEAN YOU CAN COME UP WITH
NARRATIVES ABOUT WHAT HAS HAPPENED HERE THAT DON'T
REQUIRE, YOU KNOW, SOME HUGE MISTAKE BY CITY STAFF IN 2016.
RIGHT. MY THERE'S SOME NODDING GOING
ON OVER THERE. >> ALL RIGHT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
>> I JUST WANTED TO MAKE A FEW POINTS.
>> IT IS WE'VE RECEIVED A LOT OF INFORMATION AND NEVERTHELESS
THIS IS PRETTY STRAIGHTFORWARD TO ME.
I THINK THAT THIS IS NOT THE ONLY AREA OF THE CODE WHERE
SOMEBODY WHO PURCHASES A PROPERTY IS THEN RESPONSIBLE
FOR THE COMPLIANCE. WE WHEN WHEN YOU PURCHASE THE
PROPERTY YOU USUALLY ALTHOUGH IN A HOT REAL ESTATE MARKET YOU
SKIP THAT STEP. >> THERE IS AN INSPECTION
AND YOU PURCHASE THE ELECTRICAL THE PLUMBING, THE SEWER,
EVERYTHING THAT YOU KNOW IS TOUCHED BY OUR BUILDING
AND PLANNING CODES THAT THEN BECOMES YOUR LEGAL
RESPONSIBILITY WHICH IS WHY UNDER CALIFORNIA LAW IT IS
REQUIRED BEFORE A BROKER SIGNS OFF ON THE TRANSFER OF THE DEED
THAT THERE BE A THREE HOUR REPORT PULLED WHICH THERE WAS
IN THIS CASE. SO REGARDLESS OF WHETHER THE
LISTING SAID THAT OR THE OTHER THAT THROUGH YOUR REPORT THAT
SAYS FOUR UNITS WAS INCLUDED IN THE SALE OF THIS PROPERTY
AND THE BROKER WHO OVERSAW AND STAMPED THIS TRANSACTION
HAD TO VOUCH THAT THE LEGAL REQUIREMENTS FOR A TRANSFER OF
TITLE UNDER CALIFORNIA LAW WERE MET AND THAT INCLUDED THE THREE
HOUR REPORT THAT SAID IT IS A FOUR UNIT PROPERTY.
SO I JUST WANT TO POINT OUT A COUPLE OTHER THINGS.
LAST YEAR AT THIS BOARD PASSED LEGISLATION THAT I AUTHORED
DEALING WITH YOU TO USE WITH THE LEGALIZATION OF YOU TO USE
. WE CLARIFIED BECAUSE UNDER OUR
RENT CONTROL LAWS YOU TO USE OUR WRITTEN CONTROLLED AND WE
TREAT THEM AS UNITS REGARDLESS OF WHETHER THEIR UNPERMITTED
ARE PERMITTED. IT IS CLEAR TO ME THAT THESE
UNITS WERE PERMITTED BUT EVEN IF THEY WEREN'T BECAUSE THERE'S
BEEN THIS YOU KNOW, OVER YOU KNOW, WRITING CONJECTURE EVEN
IF THEY WEREN'T. WE HAVE LEGISLATION THAT DEALS
WITH HOW WE TREAT THESE THINGS AND WE TREAT THEM AS UNITS.
YOU KNOW, WE ARE REQUIRED TO DEAL WITH THEM A CERTAIN WAY.
TWO YEARS AGO WE ACTUALLY YOU KNOW, BEFORE THIS CURRENT BOARD
BUT WE ALSO PASSED LEGISLATION THAT I ALSO AUTHORED DEALING
WITH UNPERMITTED UNITS AND THE A PATH FORWARD FOR FOLKS WHO
DID NOT KNOW THAT THEY WERE UNPERMITTED WHEN THEY, YOU
KNOW, PURCHASED THEM AND ALLOWED A PATH FOR
INCORPORATED THEM INCORPORATING THOSE UNITS INTO THAT PRINCIPAL
HOME. >> SO THERE IS A PATH FOR DOING
THAT. BUT THAT WAS NOT THAT THAT'S
NOT WHAT IS IN FRONT OF US TODAY.
WHAT IS IN FRONT OF US TODAY IS OVERTURNING THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DETERMINATION IN THAT HAS A STANDARD WHICH I
THINK THAT THE CURRENT APPELLANT HAS NOT MET AS FAR AS
I'M CONCERNED BECAUSE I DON'T SEE ANY EVIDENCE I'VE HEARD
QUESTIONS I'VE HEARD YOU KNOW, SOME CONJECTURE ABOUT, YOU
KNOW, CITY STAFF ACTING ONE WAY OR ANOTHER.
>> THERE'S NO QUESTION IN MY MIND THAT THERE WAS A BAD ACTOR
HERE, A DEVELOPER WHO MARCHED FOUR UNITS ILLEGALLY AND TURNED
IT INTO A SINGLE FAMILY HOME. AND I CAN UNDERSTAND THAT A
FAMILY WANTS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME IN NORTH BEACH.
I WILL ALSO POINT OUT THAT WE HAVE AN OBLIGATION UNDER THIS
STATE LAW NOW TO DELIVER 84,000 UNITS OF HOUSING AND OVER THE
NEXT EIGHT YEARS AND THIS POLICY DECISION WILL HAVE AN
EFFECT ON THAT AND IT'S NOT ONE THAT I WANT TO PARTICIPATE IN.
I WILL ALSO NOTE THAT, YOU KNOW, WE HAVE ZONING FOR A
REASON. SO TWO THIRDS OF OUR HOUSING
STOCK IN SAN FRANCISCO ACTUALLY IS SINGLE FAMILY HOMES AND IT
IS NOT NORTH BEACH AND YOU KNOW, I UNDERSTAND WHY SOMEBODY
WOULD WANT TO HAVE A SINGLE FAMILY HOME IN NORTH BEACH
WHICH IS A VERY DENSE AREA. THAT'S NOT YOU KNOW, HOW WE
HAVE MADE THESE DECISIONS AND WE JUST FAMOUSLY WENT
THROUGH A VERY ARDUOUS PROCESS TO REVISIT THOSE ISSUES.
BUT IT WAS DONE DELIBERATELY AND WITH LOTS OF STUDY
AND INTERACTION WITH THE PUBLIC.
I AM NOT READY TO CHANGE THE POLICY OF THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF FRANCISCO WHEN IT COMES TO CODE COMPLIANCE ON THESE ISSUES
ON ILLEGAL MERGERS OF UNITS NOTWITHSTANDING THE HARDSHIP
FOR THIS FAMILY. I UNDERSTAND YOU KNOW WHERE
THEY'RE COMING FROM AND I, I DO WISH THAT PEOPLE HAD BETTER
TRAINING WHEN THEY ARE PURCHASING, YOU KNOW, THEIR
LARGEST ASSETS. I DID SPEND A BUNCH OF MY
CAREER DOING THAT HOMEOWNERSHIP TRAINING AND YOU KNOW WHAT?
YOU HAVE TO READ EVERYTHING BEFORE YOU SIGN IT.
IT IS A LEGAL RESPONSIBILITY THAT YOU'RE TAKING WHEN THAT
HAPPENS. NEVERTHELESS, THIS IS STILL A
VERY VALUABLE PROPERTY. I, I THINK THAT WE SHOULD KEEP
TO THE POLICY THAT WE'VE ALWAYS HAD AND I WILL BE VOTING TO
UPHOLD THIS DECISION. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. WE WILL CONTINUE OUR
DELIBERATIONS BUT THE CLERK HAS POINTED OUT TO ME THAT THERE'S
A LITTLE I PROBABLY WE SHOULD SAY AT THIS POINT THAT THE
PUBLIC HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU SO MUCH, PRESIDENT MENEM.
>> AND THIS IS PROBABLY WHAT I ALWAYS THINK IS THE WORST PART
OF OUR JOB TO HAVE FACILITIES DISPUTES.
I THINK WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT READING THE FINE PRINT PROBABLY
ONE OF THE THINGS I DIDN'T KNOW WE ACTUALLY WERE GOING TO HAVE
TO DO SERVING ON THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
BUT THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS THAT WE WE ARE PUT IN THIS
PREDICAMENT TO MAKE THESE DECISIONS AND SO I HAVE TO LOOK
AT THE FACTS THAT ARE PRESENTED.
>> I HAVE TO LOOK AT WHAT'S IN FRONT OF ME FROM ALL SIDES
AND I THINK A FEW THINGS THAT I'M STRUGGLING WITH HERE IS I
DON'T KNOW WHAT ELSE TO DO WHEN THE CITY ASSESSOR DEFINES AS
FOUR UNITS WHEN THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT DEFINES AS FOUR
UNITS, WHEN THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT DEFINES AS FOUR
UNITS AND THEN WHEN I SEE THAT WE WOULD LOSE NOT JUST A NET
LOSS OF TWO UNITS BUT VERY, VERY DEAR AND IMPORTANT FOR
WHAT I SEE IS ALSO A NET LOSS OF TWO RENT CONTROL UNITS.
THAT'S A HARD PILL TO SWALLOW TO TO NOT HAVE TO GO WITH THE
DECISION OF WHAT THE DEPARTMENT PUTS IN FRONT OF US AND THEN
AND IT'S YOU KNOW, I THINK THAT I DEFINITELY SYMPATHIZE WITH
ANYONE WHO IS PUT IN A POSITION TO MAKE A PURCHASE OF THIS SIZE
AND HAVE TO NOT BE ABLE TO MOVE FORWARD ON SOME OF THE THINGS
THAT THEY WANT TO DO. >> BUT MOST CERTAINLY WHEN I
HEAR FROM THE PROPERTY OWNER THAT THE ONE THING THEY DID
KNOW IS THAT THIS WAS LISTED AS A MULTI UNIT HOME AT THE TIME
OF PURCHASE. THAT'S ANOTHER THING THAT
ALIGNS WITH EVERYTHING THEY'RE PLANNING AS PRESENTED BEFORE US
ALONG WITH OTHER BODIES THAT MAKE DECISIONS ABOUT HOW WE
DESIGNATE SOMETHING AS TO BE IN IN THIS CASE TO BE FOR UNITS
. I DO SHARE ISSUES WITH
SUPERVISOR CHERYL IN TERMS OF GOING AFTER VIOLATORS AND BAD
ACTORS. THAT'S WHY I ASKED THE QUESTION
ABOUT WHAT INVESTIGATION IS GOING ON AND WHAT IS HAPPENING
IN THAT CASE. BUT LIKE SUPERVISOR MELGAR, I
CAN'T SEE WHY I WOULD NOT SUPPORT WHAT PLANNING IS PUT
BEFORE US PARTICULARLY BECAUSE OF THE FACT THAT A MATTER OF WE
RELY ON THESE FOLKS TO MAKE THESE ASSESSMENTS FOR SO MANY
DIFFERENT REASONS AND NOT JUST THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT, THE
CITY ASSESSOR, THE FIRE DEPARTMENT FOR ME THERE THERE'S
NO WAY WITH WAS PRESENTED IN FRONT OF ME.
>> I CAN I CAN GO AGAINST THAT DECISION I THINK SUPERVISORS
WANT. >> SUPERVISOR SAUTER IS THIS
YOUR YOUR WRAP UP BECAUSE I DO HAVE QUESTIONS AND OKAY SO OKAY
I DO HAVE I GUESS A COUPLE OF QUESTIONS FOR THE APPELLANTS IF
THEY COULD COME BACK UP AND I DON'T ASK THIS TO BE MEAN I
MEAN I HAVE A LOT OF SYMPATHY FOR YOUR PREDICAMENT AND I FEEL
BAD FOR YOU SO I WANT TO START BY THAT.
I THINK PEOPLE ARE SAYING UNKIND THINGS ABOUT YOU ARE NOT
DOING THEIR CAUSE ANY GREAT SERVICE BUT AND NOT TO ASSUME
TOO MUCH SOPHISTICATION FROM YOU AS BUYERS BUT YOU WHAT DID
YOU THINK WHEN YOU WERE BUYING THIS PROPERTY WHICH IS
DESCRIBED BY ADDRESSES FOR DIFFERENT ADDRESSES IN YOUR
TITLE REPORT WOULD HAVE YOU KNOW WOULD HAVE SHOWN THAT
THROUGH YOUR REPORT WOULD HAVE SHOWN THAT AND PRESUMABLY YOUR
REALTOR HAD SOME KIND OF CONVERSATION WITH YOU ABOUT
THIS LIKE AND MAYBE IT'S HARD TO TAKE YOURSELF BACK TO 2021
WHEN YOU WERE MAKING THIS DECISION BUT WHAT DID YOU THINK
WAS GOING ON HERE? >> YEAH, I THINK IT'S A FAIR
QUESTION AND I APPRECIATE THE RESPECTFUL OPENING.
>> I THINK THE REALITY OF THIS CASE IS THAT WE DID SO WHICH IS
WHY I OWNED IT OPENLY. I ALSO HAVE THE PLEASURE OF NOW
BEING ON THE RECORD WITH THE CHRONICLE IS CALLING MYSELF A
NUMBER WHICH IS UNFORTUNATE FOR ME.
I OWN IT BECAUSE I THINK ACCOUNTABILITY MATTERS AND WE
ARE FIRST TIME HOMEBUYERS AS SOMEONE POINTED OUT, WE'RE NOT
FROM GENERATIONAL WEALTH THAT DOES NOT EXCLUDE US THOUGH FROM
PARTICIPATING IN LAWFUL BEHAVIOR AND ABIDING BY RULES
WHICH IS WHY WE'VE PROPOSED A SOLUTION THAT WE THINK IS
FEASIBLE AND PROPORTIONAL WHICH IS NOT TO MAINTAIN A SINGLE
FAMILY HOME NOWHERE NOT ONCE HAVE WE EVER ASKED FOR THAT.
WHAT WENT THROUGH OUR MINDS WHEN WE FOUND THIS HOME WAS THE
HOME THAT WE THOUGHT WAS TOO GOOD TO BE TRUE?
>> IT TURNS OUT THAT'S RIGHT. WE WE DIDN'T I TO SAY WE DIDN'T
KNOW I BELIEVE IS DOING A DISSERVICE TO YOUR QUESTION
AND THAT IS IT WAS POINTED OUT TO US WE DID GET THE THREE HOUR
REPORT AND WHAT IT SAID AT THE BOTTOM WAS THE ZONING OR
SOMETHING MAY HAVE CHANGED. PLEASE CALL THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT OR LOOK INTO CITY RECORDS WHICH IS WHAT OUR REAL
ESTATE AGENT DID. >> AND WHEN THOSE RECORDS WERE
PULLED THEY WERE VERY CONFLICTING AND SO THE REASON I
USE THE WORDS WE KNOW IT WAS A MULTI UNIT PROPERTY NOT WE KNOW
IT WAS A FOUR UNIT PROPERTY IS BECAUSE IT WASN'T CLEAR BASED
ON CITY RECORDS THEMSELVES AND SO WE DID KNOW AND THAT'S
WHAT I'M TAKING ACCOUNTABILITY FOR.
>> AND YOU THOUGHT SOMEBODY ELSE HAS LIVED IN THIS
ABSOLUTELY NOT BEEN A PROBLEM FOR THEM.
>> AND TO BE FAIR, THOSE TWO FORMER OWNERS WERE BOTH AT THE
TIME GENERAL COUNSEL AT TWITTER AND GOOGLE AND I AM NOT THAT
SOPHISTICATED TO YOUR POINT. >> I AM AND I'M NOT.
>> OKAY. SO THEN IF WE COULD TALK A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT KIND OF THE PROPOSAL THAT YOU'VE PUT
FORWARD IS SORT OF THE THE PATH TO TO LEGALIZATION AND AGAIN
I'M NOT ASKING THIS TO BE MEAN BUT WHAT IS THE SQUARE FOOTAGE
OF YOU OF YOUR HOME THAT YOU'RE LIVING IN NOW?
>> I SHOULD HAVE BROUGHT MY NOTES UP WITH ME BUT IT IS
NORTH OF 3000FT2 AND THE LOT SIZE IS SOUTH OF 2000FT2
AND THE PROPOSAL IS FOR A NEW APPROXIMATELY 440 SQUARE FOOT
STUDIO DWELLING. >> AND DO YOU KNOW WHAT THE
SQUARE FOOTAGE OF THE PRIOR UNITS WAS?
>> I ROUGHLY KNOW THAT THEY WERE ONE WAS FROM THE PROPOSAL
SORRY EXCUSE ME THE PROPOSAL FROM PETER ISKANDER THAT THE
PLANS ON FOR 20 16 WHAT WAS I'M ASSUMING THOSE ARE LIKE
THOUSAND SQUARE FOOT A KIND OF UNITS ONE WAS SOME THAT'S THE
JUMP ONE WAS SUB 400 I BELIEVE IT WAS 350 ISH ONE WAS THE 440
WHICH IS WHY WE WERE PROPOSING TO REINSTATE THAT UNIT AS THE
PATH OF LEAST RESISTANCE FOR OUR FAMILY.
>> I DON'T RECALL THE SIZES OF THE OTHER BUT I THINK THAT THEY
WERE APPROXIMATELY SIZE OF DUPLEX STYLE I BELIEVE AND AND
SO WHEN WE WERE WE'RE GOING TO PLAN AND PART OF OUR OUR NEW
KNOWLEDGE NOW IS HOW THE SYSTEM AND THE PROCESS WORKS.
AT NO POINT AFTER FILING THIS THE C WAY ON REQUEST OF THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT WAS THERE AN OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO AMEND
THE PLAN WHICH IS WHY I TRIED TO SHARE TODAY THAT WE'RE VERY
OPEN TO A REASONABLE PROPORTIONAL SOLUTION.
>> I WE OUR BIGGEST GOAL HERE IS TO REMAIN IN OUR HOME AND WE
ARE MORE THAN HAPPY TO REINSTATE A UNIT.
>> WE'RE COMFORTABLE WITH UNDERSTANDING WHAT SIDE LIKE
EXPLORING WHAT SIZE THAT UNIT IS WE'RE EXPLORING.
>> WE'RE OPEN TO EXPLORING MORE THEN THAN ONE ADDITIONAL UNIT.
BUT THE CIRCUMSTANCE IS ARE THAT A FOUR UNIT REINSTATEMENT
EVEN THOUGH THE UNITS THAT WERE UNAUTHORIZED PREVIOUSLY THOSE
TO WHICH TO BE ON THE RECORD I'M NOT DENYING THE EXISTENCE
OF THE HUMANS THAT LIVED IN THAT BUILDING AND WE'VE
TALKED WITH SOME OF THEM ONE OF WHICH IS VERY WHO IS STILL OUR
NEIGHBOR AND SHE'S INCREDIBLY SUPPORTIVE OF US
AND UNDERSTANDS THE SITUATION. BUT THOSE UNITS WERE INCREDIBLY
UNDERSIZED ACCORDING TO TODAY'S STANDARDS FOR WHAT IS
ACCEPTABLE WITHIN A HOME WHICH IS WHY I CONTINUE TO REPORT 2.2
THE THREE DENSITY FOR THE LOT SIZE WHICH AGAIN IS IS UNDER
THREE UNITS AT THIS POINT. >> SO WE'RE COMFORTABLE
EXPLORING ANYTHING. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. >> I WILL RELIEVE YOU.
YOU CAN SIT BACK DOWN SO YOU KNOW AND I DO I THINK THESE
HOMEOWNERS ARE OUR SYMPATHETIC. I THINK IT WAS NOT A GREAT
DECISION TO PURCHASE A PROPERTY THAT YOU KNOW AND I THINK IT IS
IMPORTANT PRETTY IMPORTANT FOR THE CITY TO STICK BY THE
PRECEDENT THAT IT IS NOT A GOOD IDEA.
BUYERS IN SAN FRANCISCO TO BE PURCHASING PROPERTIES THAT
PURPORT TO BE FEWER UNITS THAN WHAT IS REPRESENTED IN THE
DOCUMENTATION FOR THOSE YOU KNOW FOR THOSE PROPERTIES.
IF WE ARE GOING TO GIVE OUR OUR RENT CONTROLLED UNIT PROTECTION
LEGISLATION THAT HAS BEEN ADOPTED OVER YOU KNOW, VARIOUS
PERIODS BUT BUT INCLUDING IN THE WORK THAT WAS DONE, YOU
KNOW, AROUND FAMILY ZONING LIKE THAT'S GOING TO LOSE A LOT OF
ITS EFFECTIVENESS IF IT BECOMES CLEAR THAT THE CITY IS WILLING
TO LEGALIZE. YOU KNOW, IF YOU WAIT TEN YEARS
THAT'S JUST GOING TO BE SORT OF A NONSTARTER FOR WELL, IT'S
GOING TO BE A BIG STARTER FOR THE LOSS OF FOR THE THE I GUESS
ACCELERATED LOSS OF RENT CONTROLLED UNITS AND THE FACT
THAT YOU KNOW, DEVELOPERS AND REALTORS NOT ALL OF THEM
BUT THAT SOME OF THEM LOOK FOR OPPORTUNITIES TO MAKE MONEY
AND THAT ONE WAY TO MAKE MONEY IS TO SORT OF DO THINGS THAT
ARE NOT PLAINLY ALLOWED OR QUITE DISALLOWED BY THE LAW BUT
YOU KNOW, COUNT ON THE CITY NOT CATCHING IT AND THE MAGIC OF
CAPITALISM TO ENSURE THAT THAT EVERYBODY EXCEPT THE PEOPLE
WHO'VE BEEN EVICTED PROSPER FROM THESE TRANSACTIONS LIKE
THERE'S INCREDIBLE POWER IN THAT SORT OF ECONOMIC
INCENTIVE TO DO THINGS THAT ARE NOT LEGAL.
AND SO THAT PUTS THE PLANNING COMMISSION AND THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND THE BOARD OF APPEALS AND US AND STAFF ALL
IN THIS UNPLEASANT POSITION OF HAVING TO DO UNKIND THINGS TO
INDIVIDUAL PROPERTY OWNERS BECAUSE WE'RE TRYING TO HOLD
BACK TO THE EXTENT WE CAN A FLOOD OF MORE EVICTIONS THAN
WE'VE SEEN AND MORE DISPLACEMENT THAN WE'VE SEEN.
AND AS YOU KNOW AS I THINK SYMPATHETIC AS THIS FAMILY IS,
I THINK IF WE LINED UP YOU KNOW, ALL THE ALL THE FAMILIES
AND HOUSEHOLDS NOT JUST IN NORTH BEACH BUT IN MY
DISTRICT CERTAINLY AND YOU KNOW, OTHER DISTRICTS THAT HAVE
SEEN THEIR HOMES LOST THROUGH ILLEGAL MERGERS AND VARIOUS YOU
KNOW, MEANS THAT EITHER SKIRT THE LAW OR VIOLATE THE LAW,
THOSE WOULD BE PRETTY COMPELLING STORIES AS WELL.
SO I ALSO I DON'T KNOW WHAT THE RIGHT SOLUTION HERE
AND BALANCING OF THE EQUITIES I DON'T THINK THIS PROPOSAL COMES
CLOSE TO WHAT WE NEED TO DO TO PRESERVE THE IDEA THAT YOU
CAN'T JUST GET RID OF RENT CONTROLLED UNITS AND THEN SOLVE
IT, YOU KNOW, A FEW YEARS DOWN THE ROAD WITH YOU KNOW,
ADDITION OF A SMALL UNIT THAT MAY OR MAY NOT GET RENTED OUT
ANY TIME SOON. I THINK THERE HAS TO BE
SOMETHING MORE SO FOR ME, YOU KNOW, I'M YOU KNOW, ANOTHER
VOTE FOR APPROVING THE DENIAL WITH THAT SUPERVISOR SAUTER YOU
PRESENT AMENDMENT I DID HAVE A FEW MORE QUESTIONS FOR THE
APPELLANTS AND PROBABLY THE ARCHITECT IF THEY WANT TO COME
BACK UP. >> SO THE THE CONDITIONAL USE
THAT IS BEFORE US IS ASKING FOR PERMISSION TO ADD ONE NEW UNIT
OF HOUSING TAKES IT TO TO AUTHORIZE UNITS OF HOUSING
WHICH IS THE MOST IT'S THE SAME AMOUNT OF AUTHORIZED UNITS OF
HOUSING THIS SITE HAS HAD BUT THE REJECTION AGAIN KIND OF
SENDS US DOWN THIS PATH PRESUMABLY WHERE YOU'RE
REQUIRED TO TAKE IT TO FOUR UNITS OF HOUSING.
CAN YOU TELL US YOU KNOW BOTH MAYBE FROM THE APPELLANT
FINANCIAL FAMILY PERSPECTIVE AND THEN THE PHYSICAL
ARCHITECTURAL PERSPECTIVE IS THAT POSSIBLE?
COULD YOU DO FOR ANY UNITS OF HOUSING HERE?
>> IT IS POSSIBLE AND WE ILLUSTRATED PLANS THAT SHOW
FOUR UNITS AND THEY MATCH FAIRLY CLOSELY THE ORIGINAL
DEVELOPER'S APPROVED PLANS AND SO EACH IS ABOUT OR THREE
OF THEM ARE ABOUT 400FT2 440 WE COULD LOOK AT THE NUMBERS BUT
THEY'RE STUDIOS AND THEN IT WOULD BE A FOURTH THAT IS A
LITTLE BIT A LITTLE BIT LARGER .
IT'S QUITE DIFFERENT THAN THE BUILDING IS PHYSICALLY BECAUSE
OF THE THE TWO MEANS OF EGRESS REQUIRED FOR A BUILDING WITH
THREE UNITS OR MORE. SO WE'D HAVE TO DO A FIRE RATED
CORRIDOR AND STAIRCASES AND THE ONE STAIRCASE IN THE REAR DOES
NOT MEET CODE FROM A HEIGHT PERSPECTIVE AND THE STEPS ARE
UNEVEN AND SO FORTH. SO THAT ONE WOULD NEED TO BE
REBUILT. THE ONE AT THE FRONT IS
COMPLETELY OPEN TO THE UPPER THREE STORIES AND SO THAT WOULD
HAVE TO BE COMPLETELY RECONSTRUCTED.
SO IT'S A IT'S A MAJOR OVERHAUL OF THE BUILDING PHYSICALLY
WOULD REQUIRE LIFE SAFETY SYSTEMS BE UPGRADED.
THE WIRING IS NOT SUCCINCT. >> IT DOES NOT GO TO INDIVIDUAL
UNITS AS AS LAID OUT BY THE DEVELOPER.
SO IT'S A WHOLE OVERHAUL OF THE BUILDING MECHANICAL,
ELECTRICAL, PLUMBING, STAIRCASES, WALLS AND THINGS
LIKE THIS AS WELL AS FOR KITCHENS HOW MUCH THAT COST IS
SOMEWHERE IN THE RANGE OF MAYBE $800 PER SQUARE FOOT OR
SOMETHING LIKE THIS IT'S PROBABLY 2 MILLION BUCKS OR
SOMETHING LIKE THIS MAYBE MORE .
THERE'S ANOTHER PATH OF THREE UNITS THAT IS IS PROBABLY LESS
INVASIVE AND MIGHT YIELD SOMETHING WHERE A FAMILY OF
THEIR SIZE COULD STAY I DON'T KNOW.
>> BUT DOES THAT ANSWER YOUR QUESTION OR DO YOU HAVE THANK
YOU MAYBE FOR THE APPELLANT WHAT IS GOING DOWN A PATH OF
FOUR UNITS MEAN FOR YOU AND THEN HOW WOULD THAT COMPARE
TO NOT NOT TWO WHICH IS WHAT YOU'RE ASKING FOR BUT MAYBE A
COMPROMISE AT THREE? >> THANK YOU STEPHEN.
I. >> FOUR UNITS MEANS A FORCED
DISPLACEMENT OF OUR FAMILY AGAIN POINTING TO THE THE M ONE
DENSITY THE UNITS THAT WOULD BE PRODUCED WITH A FOUR UNIT
LAYOUT WOULD NOT BE SUFFICIENT TO HOUSE OUR FAMILY.
>> I RECOGNIZE THAT THE FINANCIAL BURDEN OF THIS IS NOT
A WELL-RECEIVED ARGUMENT AND SO I WON'T MAKE THAT IT IS
MEANINGFUL TO MY FAMILY BUT THE MOST IMPORTANT AND MOST
MEANINGFUL IMPACT TO OUR FAMILY IS IF WE RETURN TO THE FOUR
UNIT CONFIGURATION EITHER THAT WERE APPROVED BY THESE 2013
PLANS OR SOME OTHER ADDITIONAL CONFIGURATION THAT WE HAVE
WORKED VERY HARD TO TRY TO TO MAKE SIMPLY WILL NOT HOUSE A
FAMILY OF FOUR. MY HUSBAND AND I BOTH WORK FROM
HOME. WE HAVE TWO YOUNG GROWING
CHILDREN AND WE HAVE VERY IMMINENTLY AN ELDERLY DISABLED
PARENT THAT WILL BE MOVING IN WITH US AND SO NONE OF THE
UNITS PRODUCED IN A FOUR UNIT PLAN WOULD BE ABLE TO ALLOW OUR
FAMILY TO STAY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. I WANT TO ORGANIZE MY THOUGHTS
AND THEN MAYBE MAKE A MOTION FOR FOR FOLKS TO CONSIDER AND I
DO WANT TO, YOU KNOW, ADDRESS SOME OF THE CONCERNS AROUND
SETTING A PRECEDENT. WE DON'T WANT ILLEGAL MERGERS
LIKE THIS TO BE FORGIVEN OR INCENTIVIZED AND WE DON'T WANT
TO SET A PRECEDENT. BUT I WOULD ARGUE THE TIME TO
SET A PRECEDENT AGAINST THIS IS 15 YEARS AGO WHEN THERE WAS A
KNOWN BAD ACTOR IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD WHO WAS THE OWNER.
>> AS WE'VE DISCUSSED TODAY, I DO HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT THE
INSPECTION HISTORY OF THIS PROPERTY THAT ALLOWED THE
ILLEGAL MERGER TO STEP TO SLIP THROUGH THE CITY'S HANDS FOR
THE PAST TEN PLUS YEARS UNTIL IT WAS BROUGHT TO THE ATTENTION
BY AN ANONYMOUS COMPLAINT FROM A NEIGHBOR.
AND I HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT THE VALIDITY OF SITUATION WHERE
WITHIN 45 DAYS IN 2016 WE WENT FROM A BUY SIGNING OF A
CERTIFICATE OF FINAL COMPLETION FOR A SUPPOSE IT FOR YOU AND IT
REMODEL TO THE HOUSE BEING LISTED FOR SALE AS A SINGLE
FAMILY HOME. I DON'T BELIEVE IT'S PHYSICALLY
POSSIBLE TO CONVERT A FOUR UNIT BUILDING IN THE MATTER OF 45
DAYS EITHER THE DEVELOPER FOUND A LOOPHOLE IN THE PERMITTING
PROCESS THAT DESPERATELY NEEDS TO BE CLOSED OR THE INSPECTIONS
WERE NOT CONDUCTED IN THE MANNER THEY WERE SUPPOSED TO
BE. I ALSO UNDERSTAND THERE WERE
FOLLOW UP PERMITS ISSUED BY THE RBI WHILE THE HOME WAS LISTED
AS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME IN 2017 AND I HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT THAT
AND I WOULD RATHER SEE US FOCUS OUR EFFORTS ON FIXING THOSE
GAPS IN THE CITY'S PROCESSES. I THINK IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT
THAT I AM NOT SUGGESTING I DON'T BELIEVE ANYONE SUGGESTING
THAT THE APPELLANT BEAR NO RESPONSIBILITY.
WHAT WE'RE CONSIDERING TODAY IS PERMISSION FOR THEM TO BE
REQUIRED ADD NEW HOUSING. THIS IS SOMETHING THAT HAS
CONSUMED YEARS OF THEIR TIME TREMENDOUS FINANCIAL COSTS
IN REGARDLESS IF YOU THINK THIS IS ENTIRELY FAIR OR IT IS TOO
BURDENSOME NO ONE CAN LOOK AT THIS SITUATION AND THINK THAT
WE ARE LETTING FOLKS OFF WITHOUT INTENSE SCRUTINY
AND COSTS OR THAT WE ARE INCENTIVIZING OR SETTING A
PRECEDENT HERE. WE CAN'T STOP ILLEGAL MERGERS
THAT HAVE ALREADY HAPPENED BUT WE CAN PREVENT THEM FROM
HAPPENING IN THE FUTURE AND I BELIEVE THAT THIS BOARD IS
DOING THAT THROUGH THE TENANTS PROTECTION ORDINANCE DEBACLE
OPTION AND REFORMS THROUGH PERMANENT SFR CHANGES WHICH
WILL CONNECT PHOTOS AND VIDEOS TO INSPECTION RECORDS WHICH WE
DON'T HAVE AT THE MOMENT. AND I'M ALSO IN CONVERSATIONS
WITH TBE CITY ATTORNEY AND RENT BOARD TO LOOK INTO MORE OPTIONS
TO HOLD DEVELOPERS ACCOUNTABLE WHO DO MERGERS LIKE THIS.
>> THE IRONY IS THAT BY HOPING FOR HYPOTHETICAL FUTURE TENANTS
WE ARE LIKELY DISPLACING THE FAMILY AND LIVING THERE RIGHT
NOW A FAMILY OF FOUR AND I BELIEVE THAT A DENIAL WILL
RESULT IN THIS PROPERTY BEING STUCK IN LIMBO FOR YEARS TO
COME. SOMEDAY MAYBE FOUR STUDIO
APARTMENTS MIGHT BE BUILT FOR PEOPLE MIGHT LIVE THERE.
AND BY THE WAY, WE'VE LEARNED TODAY THERE'S NO REQUIREMENT
FOR THOSE FOUR UNITS TO BE RENTED OUT AND THERE'S NO
REQUIREMENT AROUND WHO LIVES IN THOSE FOUR UNITS.
I THINK AS DISCUSSED TODAY, IT IS VERY FAIR THAT THE
APPELLANTS SHOULD HAVE BEEN MORE CAREFUL.
THEY SHOULD HAVE DONE MORE DUE DILIGENCE.
I BELIEVE THEY NEED TO TAKE RESPONSIBILITY.
BUT DO I BELIEVE THAT A LACK OF EXPERTISE IN REAL ESTATE SHOULD
SUBJECT A FAMILY TO BEING PERMANENTLY DISPLACED FROM
THEIR HOME AND FINANCIALLY DRAINED BECAUSE WE THINK THEY
CAN AFFORD IT? I DON'T I DO THINK THE FAMILY
AND THE APPELLANTS BEFORE US ARE TAKING RESPONSIBILITY
AGAIN. THEY'RE ASKING FOR PERMISSION
TO ADD MORE HOUSING. THEY COULD HAVE COME TO US WITH
A C APPLICATION TO KEEP THEIR HOME AT AS IS IT'S NOT ADD
ADDITIONAL UNITS BUT THEY CHOSE THIS PATH INSTEAD AND I THINK
THAT THE CITY SHOULD BEAR SOME RESPONSIBILITY AS WELL FOR NOT
REVIEWING THE MERGER A DECADE AGO NOT TAKING THIS BAD ACTOR
SERIOUSLY ENOUGH. SO I AM INTERESTED IN A OUTCOME
HERE THAT KEEPS THIS FAMILY IN THEIR HOME ADDS ADDITIONAL
HOUSING AND LETS US MOVE PAST THIS AND DIRECT OUR RESOURCES
TOWARDS IMPROVING THE BUILDING INSPECTION PROCESS AND THE
COMPLIANCE PROCESS FOR BAD DEVELOPERS.
SO WHAT I'M PROPOSING IS REJECTING TODAY'S APPEAL.
THAT'S THE APPEAL THAT WOULD ADD ONE NEW HOUSING UNIT AND TO
INSTEAD URGE THE RECOMMENDATION OF TWO ADDITIONAL NEW UNITS.
THIS IS IMPORTANT BECAUSE THIS WOULD BRING THE PROPERTY TO
THREE AUTHORIZED UNITS. THREE AUTHORIZED UNITS IS A
RESULT OF ONE NET NEW AUTHORIZED UNIT OF HOUSING HERE
AND I THINK THIS BELIEVE THIS MEANS THAT THE FAMILY CAN STAY
IN THEIR CURRENT HOME AS WELL. SO THAT IS MY PROPOSAL
AND SQUARING THAT UP THAT MEANS THAT I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE ITEM
32 APPROVING THE PLANNING COMMISSION DECISION DE FACTO
DENYING THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION.
I'D LIKE TO MOVE ALSO MOVE ITEM 34 TO DIRECT THE CLERK OF THE
BOARD TO PREPARE FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THIS DECISION.
I WOULD LIKE THOSE FINDINGS TO INCLUDE A STATEMENT THAT A
THREE UNIT PROJECT MAY BE DESIRABLE AT THE SITE IF
FEASIBLE AND PROPERLY DESIGNED AND URGE THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND COMMISSION TO THOROUGHLY REVIEW A FUTURE
APPLICATION FOR SUCH A PROJECT IF ONE IS SUBMITTED.
FINALLY, I'D LIKE TO MOVE TO TABLE ITEM NUMBER 33.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR JOSH SAUTER HAS MADE
A MOTION. >> IS THERE A SECOND?
IT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN MY APOLOGIES I JUST WANT A CLARIFICATION OF
THE MOTION PLEASE. IS THE MOTION TO MOVE FORWARD
WITH APPROVING ITEM NUMBER 32 TABLING 33 AND ALSO MOVE
FORWARD AND APPROVING 34 AT THE THE THE MOTION WOULD APPROVE
THE DENIAL THAT IS 32 I BELIEVE IT WOULD TABLE ITEM 33 AND IT
WOULD DIRECT AT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS WHERE ARE IN THE
BOARD WOULD EXPRESS OPENNESS TO A THREE UNIT SOLUTION RATHER
THAN A FOUR AS MY STATING THAT CORRECTLY SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER
THAT APPEARS THAT APPEARS TO BE THE MOTION AND IN THAT EVENT IF
I UNDERSTAND THAT CORRECTLY BECAUSE THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION AND PLEASE LION DEPARTMENT CORRECT ME IF I'M
WRONG IS THAT THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION AT THE MOMENT
IS A DE FACTO DENIAL OF THE IT AND THEREFORE BY MOVING FORWARD
AND APPROVING THE MOTION TO APPROVE THE DECISIONS OF THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT WHICH IS A DE FACTO DENIAL, YOU ARE
BASICALLY DENYING THE APPELLANT OKAY.
>> YES, THAT IS CORRECT. >> IS IT IS GO AHEAD.
YES. YES.
THANK YOU. SPEAK UP STAFF VERONICA FLORES,
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF SUPERVISOR CHAN THAT IS
CORRECT. IF IF THIS BODY DOES NOT
APPROVE THE SEE YOU THEN WE STILL HAVE THE VIOLATION ON
HAND AND THEN THE APPELLANT HAS THE TWO PATHS TO MOVE FORWARD
EITHER LEGALIZE AS IS THIS IS THE APPLICATION THAT'S IN FRONT
OF YOU RIGHT NOW TO THEY CAN ABATE THE VIOLATION BY
LEGALIZING THE FOUR UNITS. WE DO HAVE A PERMIT ON FILE FOR
SUCH PROPOSAL BUT THOSE ARE THE TWO PRIMARY PATHS BUT A
SUPERVISOR SARDAR MENTIONED PERHAPS THERE'S ANOTHER PATH ON
HAND OF ADDING HAVING A TOTAL OF THREE UNITS ON THE PROPERTY
INSTEAD OF THE FOUR LEGAL UNITS HERE.
SO IF YOU DO NOT GRANT THE SEE YOU TODAY THE APPELLANT STILL
NEEDS TO ABATE THE VIOLATION IN THEIR THE PATH THAT THEY
CHOOSE AND TO ADD THAT IF THEY WERE WANT TO ADD FOR A TOTAL OF
THREE UNITS THEY STILL HAVE TO GO BACK TO PLANNING COMMISSION
FOR APPROVAL OF THE MERGER OF TWO UNITS.
SO IF I UNDERSTAND CORRECTLY SHALL WE SUPPORT SUPERVISOR
SOUDERS MOTION TODAY WHAT IT LEAVES TO FOR THE OCCUPANTS OF
THIS SPACE AND FOR THE APPELLANT IS THEN TO GO BACK TO
THE DRAWING BOARD WITH THREE SOUNDS LIKE THREE DIFFERENT
OPTIONS SEE YOU TO TO SEE TO APPLY IN OTHER SEE YOU AND THAT
WITHIN THAT SEE YOU HAS THREE DIFFERENT OPTIONS ONE IS TO
APPLY FOR A C USE THAT IT REMAINS AS ONE SINGLE FAMILY
HOME UNITS AS IT CURRENTLY IS OR A SEE YOU FOR POTENTIALLY A
THREE UNITS WHICH IS THEN THEY CONVERT THE EXISTING SINGLE
FAMILY HOME INTO TWO UNITS PLUS A 450 SQUARE FOOTAGE OF A A ADU
OR THAT THE THIRD C YOU WILL BE THEM FOR THEM TO CONVERT BACK
TO THE FOUR UNITS THEY WOULDN'T NEED A SEE YOU IF TO CONVERT
BACK TO FOUR UNITS THAT WOULD JUST TO ABATE THE COMPLAINTS
BUT IF THEY WANT TO CONVERT THAT TO THREE UNITS THEN THEY
WOULD NEED TO GO BACK TO THE PLANNING COMMISSIONS.
>> UNDERSTOOD. WELL IN THAT CASE THEN THANK
YOU. SO VIKAS, I MEAN THE WRINKLE OF
SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER'S PROPOSAL IS JUST THE THIS BOARD I MEAN
WHETHER I DON'T THINK THERE ARE THE VOTES ON THE BOARD TO
DISAPPROVE THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S ACTION.
SO THE QUESTION FOR THIS BOARD IS DO WE SIMPLY AFFIRM THE
PLANNING COMMISSION'S ACTION IN WHICH CASE THE APPLICANT THE
APPELLANT NEEDS TO GO BACK EITHER NEEDS TO ABATE ABATE THE
VIOLATION BY RECREATING FOUR UNITS OR START EXPLORING OTHER
OPTIONS WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IN THE PLANNING
COMMISSION THE SLIGHT VARIATION IN SUPERVISOR SLATER'S MOTION
IS TO HAVE US SAYING THAT PERHAPS THREE UNITS WOULD BE
ENOUGH TO TO ABATE THE VIOLATION NOT TELLING ANYBODY
WHAT TO DO BECAUSE WE CAN'T I DON'T THINK BUT SUGGESTING THAT
FOR EXAMPLE IF A APPEAL OF A SEE YOU FOR A THREE UNITS WERE
TO COME BACK TO THIS BOARD THIS BOARD MIGHT BE INCLINED TO
SUPPORT THE THREE UNITS SOLUTION OR ANSWER SUPERVISOR
MELGAR THANK YOU. THAT IS WHAT I WANTED TO
CLARIFY ON A PROCEDURAL ISSUE BECAUSE IT IS ONE MOTION TO
DENY THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION AND THEN TO
DIRECT THE STAFF TO AMEND THE FINDINGS AND I'M NOT SURE I
MEAN REGARDLESS OF WHETHER THESE OTHER FINDINGS ARE
SUPPORTABLE BECAUSE WE ARE IN FACT CONTRADICTING I THINK
THE GENERAL PLAN BUT PROCEDURALLY IF WE DID NOT
AGREE WITH THAT SECOND PART OF THE MOTION WOULD WE THEN HAVE
TO MAKE A NEW MOTION OR CAN THOSE TWO ITEMS BE VOTED ON
SEPARATELY? >> TYPICALLY SUPERVISOR MELGAR
THROUGH THE PRESIDENT THIS ITEM IS VOTED ON AS A PACKAGE.
HOWEVER A SUPERVISOR COULD ASK TO HAVE THE ELEMENTS SEPARATE
SO FOR THE QUESTION AND VOTE ON THE MATTER SEPARATELY.
ALTERNATIVELY I WOULD ASK THE DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY IF A
SEPARATE VOTE OUTCOME ON EITHER MOTION BECOMES PROBLEMATIC FOR
THE WHOLE I'VE NEVER SEEN THIS BEFORE SO DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY
BRAD RUSTY I WOULD I EXPECT BOTH OF THESE MOTIONS REQUIRE
SIX VOTES TO BE APPROVED IF IT WERE SEPARATED AND THESE THE
MOTION TO APPROVE THE FINDINGS WERE DID NOT OBTAIN SIX VOTES
THEN I THINK SOMEONE ELSE WE NEED TO MAKE ANOTHER MOTION
THAT'S DIFFERENT BUT THERE NEEDS TO BE FINDINGS IN THIS
CASE. >> NORMALLY WHEN THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DECISION IS APPROVED IT'S NOT OVERTURNED BY
THE BOARD. WE DON'T NEED FINDINGS BUT
IN THIS SITUATION BECAUSE THERE ARE NO FINDINGS FROM THE
PLANNING COMMISSION BECAUSE A DE FACTO APPROVAL OR DE FACTO
DENIAL THE BOARD NEEDS TO MAKE FINDINGS SO THAT IF THIS MATTER
WERE LITIGATED THERE'S A DECISION WITH ACTUAL FINDINGS
BUT IT IS POSSIBLE FOR THIS BOARD I MEAN WE COULD HAVE A55,
RIGHT? >> THAT'S CORRECT.
TODAY YOU COULD HAVE A55 VOTE. >> AND I WOULD ALSO ADD THAT
THE FINDINGS DOCUMENT WHEN IT COMES BACK THE FINAL DOCUMENT
HAS TO COME BACK TO THE BOARD FOR APPROVAL AND AT THAT POINT
THE BOARD COULD AMEND IT TO REMOVE LANGUAGE THAT IT DOESN'T
LIKE AT THAT TIME. AND MR. PRESIDENT, JUST TO
THROW ANOTHER WRENCH IN THIS ITEM THREE IT REQUIRES AN EIGHT
VOTE THRESHOLD FOR 32 AND 34 OUR SIX VOTE THRESHOLD RIGHT.
SO THERE'S LOTS OF WAYS THIS COULD MOVE FORWARD.
SOMEONE COULD VOTE TO SOMEONE COULD MAKE A MOTION TO COULD
ASK DIVIDE THE QUESTION AND HAVE US VOTING SEPARATELY
ON THESE THREE DIFFERENT THINGS AND FIGURE OUT WHAT WHERE WE
LAND ON THAT THERE'S THE POSSIBILITY OF IF SUPERVISOR
SADR'S MOTION DOES NOT PASS SOMEONE ELSE COULD MAKE ANOTHER
MOTION TO DENY THE FOR EXAMPLE TO DENY THE APPEAL WITHOUT THE
CHANGE, WITHOUT THE SPECIFIC DIRECTION AROUND FINDINGS OTHER
THAN TO PREPARE FINDINGS WHICH ALSO MIGHT NOT HAVE A MAJORITY.
>> SO ANYWAY SUPERVISOR WALTON SO JUST REAL QUICK TYPICALLY
THREE WOULD ACCOMPANY 34 RIGHT? >> WE WOULDN'T TYPICALLY
APPROVING IN HALF AND NORMALLY YOU WOULDN'T TYPICALLY SUPPORT
PLANNING AND THEN HAVE FINDINGS.
>> YEAH AND THEN MY LAST QUESTION SUPPORTING HIS CURRENT
SUPERVISOR SUTTER'S CURRENT MOTION COULD POSSIBLY ALLOW FOR
THE REMOVAL OF AT LEAST ONE UNIT.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE WE'RE CLEAR ON THAT.
YEAH, IT ACTUALLY WOULD HAVE TO.
>> YES. IF IF I MEAN WE'RE NOT
DIRECTING IT AND THE SUPERVISORS SADR'S MOTION
DOESN'T DIRECT ANYBODY TO DO ANYTHING BUT DOES SAY THAT THIS
BOARD IS KIND OF OPEN TO THE POSSIBILITY WE WOULD BE MAYBE
SAYING WE'RE OPEN TO THAT. >> YEAH THAT IS WHAT WOULD BE
HAPPENING. >> SUPERVISOR JAN YEAH I'M
RIGHT I WANT TO AGAIN ONCE CLARIFY IS THAT BY APPROVING
ITEM 32 TABLING 33 WHICH THE 33 REQUIRES TO EIGHT VOTE TO TABLE
AND WHAT SUPERVISOR SOUDER AND I NEED CLARIFY ACTION ON
THIS IS AND ON ITEM 34 WHICH IS THE PREPARATION OF FINDING IS
NOW INCLUSIVE OF LANGUAGE DIRECTING OR URGING THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO IDENTIFY EARLY OR APPROPRIATE LIKE
AUTHORIZING THE POTENTIAL APPROVAL OF A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FOR A THREE UNIT THAT IS WHICH I AM
IN DISAGREEMENT WITH. AND SO I JUST WANT TO BE ON THE
RECORD AND TO BE CLEAR ABOUT WHERE I AM TODAY I AM PREPARE
TO VOTE IN SUPPORT OF ITEM 32 WHICH AFFIRM THE DE FACTO
DENIAL BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
I AM ALSO READY TO VOTE TABLING ITEM 33 WHICH THEN WILL BE
TABLING IN THE REJECTION OF THE DE FACTO DENIAL.
I WILL NOT BE IN SUPPORTIVE OF ITEM 34 WITH THE AMENDMENTS
PROPOSED BY SOME OF SPIERS SUPERVISOR SOUDER.
>> HOWEVER I AM PREPARED TO VOTE IN SUPPORT OF ITEM 34 AS
IT CURRENTLY STANDS BECAUSE IT'S JUST SIMPLY LIKE
PREPARATION OF FILE AND I ACTUALLY HAVE INDICATE
SPECIFICALLY HOW WE WANT TO FOR I RELATED TO SEE YOU BUT MAYBE
I'M INCORRECT AND THIS IS WHY I TRYING TO FIND CLARIFICATION
ABOUT ITEM 34 I AM ALSO CONFUSED BECAUSE MY LITTLE
SCRIPT HERE SAYS THAT THAT THE APPROVAL OF THE DE FACTO DENIAL
OF THE SIU IS A COTTON TELLS YOU HOW TO APPROVE IT TELLS YOU
HOW TO DO THIS I MEAN NOTHING I DO UP HERE IS DONE WITHOUT
HEAVY SCRIPTING SO YOU KNOW I NEED THAT BUT THAT THE THE THE
FORMULA FOR APPROVAL OF THE DEFECT DE FACTO DENIAL OF THE
SEE YOU HERE AS PROVIDED IN MY SCRIPT IS TO APPROVE ITEM
NUMBER 32 AND TABLE ITEMS 33 AND 34 WHAT I'M HEARING IN REAL
TIME IN THE CITY ATTORNEY GETS TO DO THIS TO ME BECAUSE YOU
KNOW THAT'S FINE BUT THAT THE CITY ATTORNEY WOULD BE
RECOMMENDING THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS IN ANY EVENT DEPUTY
CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RESSA YES, THAT'S CORRECT.
>> I DID NOT REVIEW YOUR SCRIPT.
SO DID NOT I HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH THAT BUT I WOULD NOT
EXPECT YOU TO WOULD NOT BE A GOOD USE OF OUR CITY ATTORNEY'S
TIME. >> SO YES, BECAUSE THERE ARE NO
FINDINGS FROM BELOW THE BOARD IS GOING TO UPHOLD THE DENIAL
IT SHOULD ADOPT FINDINGS. >> YEAH I WOULD SAY IF THERE IS
A TIE VOTE ON SUPER SUPERVISOR SANDERS MOTION IF IT IS IT
FEELS LIKE WE MIGHT BE MOVING IN THAT DIRECTION.
I WOULD I WOULD RECOMMEND I THINK FINDINGS ARE NECESSARY
HERE SO THE BOARD NEEDS TO REACH AN AGREEMENT ON SOME FORM
OF DIRECTION TO THE CLERK TO PROVIDE FINDINGS SO THAT WHY
NOT BECAUSE THERE NEEDS TO BE A BASIS FOR THIS DECISION IN CASE
IT'S EVER CHALLENGED IN THE FUTURE SO THAT THERE'S A RECORD
TO RELY ON RECORD OF THE PLANNING STAFF'S PRESENTATIONS
TO THE PLANNING COMMISSION WOULD NOT BE THAT I MEAN THAT
COULD BE PART OF THE RECORD IN THE END BUT IT BUT THE IT
WOULD BE BETTER I THINK ADVISABLE FOR THE BODY TO HAVE
ITS OWN FACTS AND LAW SUPPORTING ITS DECISION.
>> BUT IF THE BUT IF THIS BODY CAN'T REACH A DECISION BECAUSE
WE'RE DEADLOCKED THIS IS MY RECOMMENDATION.
>> SO YOU HAVE TO WE DON'T HAVE TO TAKE IT.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR, JUST PROCEDURALLY SINCE GIVEN WHAT
THE ADVICE HAS BEEN BY OUR DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY, COULD WE
POSSIBLY SEPARATE THE QUESTION AND VOTE ON THE MOTION AS HAS
BEEN POSED BY SUPERVISOR SAUDER FOR 34 FIRST BECAUSE IT NEEDS A
60 VOTE THRESHOLD AND IF THAT IS NOT NECESSARILY THEN WE MOVE
ON TO YOUR SCRIPT WHICH HAS 32 AND 34 BEING VOTED ON TOGETHER
AND TABLING 33 IF THAT IS THE WILL OF THE BOARD THROUGH THE
PRESIDENT TO TAKE THE VOTE IN THAT ORDER IT COULD BE DONE.
THAT COULD BE A SOLUTION. >> I'M HAPPY TO DO IT THAT WAY
UNLESS SOMEBODY REALLY HATES IT.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU TO DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY RAMSEY.
SO AS TO MY QUESTION DIFFERENTLY IF WE ACCEPT 32 WE
DO NOT HAVE TO HAVE FINDINGS FOR 34 CORRECT.
SO SO IF WE IF WE AFFIRM IS RECOMMENDING THAT WE DO BUT WE
DON'T WE DO WOULDN'T BUT WHEN HAVE WE DONE THAT IN THE LAST
EIGHT YEARS WE DON'T USUALLY HAVE FIRM PLANNING AND THEN
CAME UP WITH FINDINGS WHEN HAVE WE DONE THAT?
I DON'T KNOW. >> WE DON'T USUALLY HAVE
DECISIONS COMING UP TO US ON THREE THREE SPLIT SO RIGHT.
OR ARE YOU SAYING WE DO WHAT'S GOING ON?
VERONICA FLORES PLANNING DEPARTMENTS DEF IT IS RARE THAT
WE HAVE A DE FACTO DENIAL THAT IS ELEVATED TO THIS BOARD SO
THAT THAT IS THE INSTANCE THAT THE CITY ATTORNEY IS ADVISING
TO THAT WE HAVE THESE FINDINGS ON RECORD NOW.
>> SO IT IS AN UNUSUAL PROCEEDING SUPERVISOR WALTON
THAT'S WHY IT'S NOT THE TYPICAL VOTING PATTERN.
>> THANK YOU. YEAH.
>> SO ALL RIGHT. SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU TO
MY COLLEAGUES FOR NAVIGATING THIS WITH US.
I THINK IT SPEAKS TO HOW UNUSUAL THIS IS.
IT IS IT WAS A33 TIE AT PLANNING.
THAT IS WHY WE ARE IN THIS UNUSUAL CASE WHERE WE HAVE THIS
WRINKLE. I THINK IT IS FURTHER EVIDENCE
THAT THIS COMPROMISE OF SORTS THAT I'M SUGGESTING MAKES ALL
THE SENSE IN THE WORLD GIVEN THE SITUATION OF THIS APPEAL
IN MY DISTRICT. IF WE ARE TO GO DOWN THE PATH
OF SEPARATING THESE ITEMS JUST FOR THE RECORD TO REMIND
EVERYONE OF MY MOTION ON ITEM 34 WHICH IS AS FOLLOWS IT IS TO
DIRECT THE CLERK OF THE BOARD TO PREPARE FINDINGS IN SUPPORT
OF THIS DECISION INCLUDING FINDINGS TO INCLUDE A STATEMENT
THAT A THREE UNIT PROJECT MAY BE DESIRABLE AT THE SITE IF
FEASIBLE AND PROPERLY DESIGNED AND URGE THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND COMMISSION TO THOROUGHLY REVIEW A FUTURE
APPLICATION FOR SUCH A PROJECT IF ONE IS SUBMITTED.
THERE IS NO SUCH APPLICATION AT THE MOMENT.
THIS IS SAYING THAT THAT IS A PATH WE MIGHT SUGGEST AGAIN I
THINK GIVEN THE CIRCUMSTANCES HERE THAT IS A WISE PATH.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THERE'S NO ONE IN THE QUEUE SO I GUESS I
WILL SPEAK FOR MYSELF AND SAY THAT I AM NOT SURE WHAT THE
RIGHT ANSWER ON BALANCING THE EQUITIES HERE IS AND THE YOU
KNOW THE SORT OF THE THE FACT THE FACT THAT THERE IS ACTUALLY
A FAMILY LIVING IN THIS BUILDING RIGHT NOW WITH THEIR
KIDS AND THEIR DESIRE TO STAY THERE AGAINST THE POLICY
IMPERATIVE THAT I THINK A NUMBER OF US FEEL TO HAVE OUR
RENT CONTROLLED UNIT PROTECTIONS HAVE ACTUAL HEFT
AND FORCE IN THE WORLD. IT IS CONCEIVABLE THAT IF AN
APPEAL CAME TO THIS BOARD OF A THREE UNIT SOLUTION THAT AT
THAT POINT I OR MY SUCCESSOR MIGHT BE OPEN TO THAT.
IT'S A LITTLE WEIRD TO ME TO BE MAKING THAT DECISION RIGHT NOW
WHEN I HAVE BEEN ASKED TO CONSIDER A ONE UNIT 440 SQUARE
FOOT SOLUTION AND I GUESS I CERTAINLY UNDERSTAND YOUR
DESIRE SUPERVISOR SAUTER TO TRY TO RESOLVE THIS AND SORT OF
SHOW A CLEAR PATH. I JUST DON'T FEEL COMFORTABLE
RIGHT NOW THAT I THAT I KNOW THAT THAT IS THE RIGHT PATH.
I'M NOT SURE IT ISN'T I'D LOVE TO FOR THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
TO COME UP WITH SOMETHING THAT WORKS AND ADDS UNITS AND DOES
IDEALLY GET TO FOUR AND IF NOT GETS TO THREE BUT IN A WAY THAT
YOU KNOW WILL STRONGLY DISINCENTIVIZE YOU KNOW, PEOPLE
ENGAGING IN PRACTICES THAT RESULT IN THE LOSS OF RENT
CONTROLLED UNITS. BUT I, I DON'T THINK I'M IN A
POSITION RIGHT NOW TO SUPPORT A FINDING THAT PREDETERMINE IS
THAT AND SAYS THREE IS FINE. IT MAY BE FINE BUT I'M NOT
COMFORTABLE SAYING THAT RIGHT NOW SO I'M PROBABLY A VOTE
AGAINST. OH NO YOU PUT YOURSELF IN THE
QUEUE AND I'M NOT THE LAST SPEAKER SO I FEEL BAD.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN GO AHEAD. I, I THINK BEFORE WE CAST A
VOTE TO CLARIFY ARE WE DOING SO IT'S IT SOUNDS TO ME IF I
UNDERSTAND IT CORRECTLY WHAT SUPERVISOR MELGAR HAS PROPOSED
IS TO DIVIDE THE QUESTION AND ALLOW US TO MORE TO CAST A
VOTE ON ITEM 34. YEAH AND THEN WE WILL THEN GO
TO THE MOTION TO CAST THE VOTES FOR APPROVING ITEM 32 TABLING
3332 REQUIRE SIX VOTES 33 REQUIRES EIGHT VOTES TO TABLE
UH 30 THREE IS EIGHT VOTES TO APPROVE IT RIGHT?
RIGHT I AM THE SIX VOTES WOULD ACCOMPLISH RIGHT I AM I'M READY
TO CAST MY VOTES TO VOTE TO VOTE AGAINST THE ITEM 34 AS IT
CURRENTLY PROPOSED BY SUPERVISOR SOUDER AND BE
IN SUPPORT OF MOVING FORWARD WITH ITEM 32 AND TABLING ITEM
33 AS A MELGAR JUST A POINT OF CLARIFICATION I'M SORRY
PRESIDENT AND MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE TO HAVE A SECOND MOTION
TO DO APPROVE ITEM 32 A TABLE ITEM 33 AND APPROVE ITEM 34 AS
IT'S NOT AMENDED BECAUSE THE ORIGINAL MOTION WAS DIFFERENT
CURRENTLY THE SUPERVISOR SADR'S MOTION IS ON THE TABLE BUT THE
ONLY PIECE OF THAT HAS BEEN DIVIDED.
>> THE ONLY DIFFERENCES IS YOU ARE ASKING FOR A SEPARATE VOTE
ON ITEM 34. FIRST, IF IN FACT YOU'VE MADE
THAT OKAY PERFECT. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO ON ITEM 34 AS AMENDED BY SUPERVISOR AS PROPOSED FOR
AMENDMENT BY SUPERVISOR SAUTER MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> YES.
ON ITEM 34 AS PROPOSED BY SUPERVISORS SAUTER SUPERVISOR
MENDELSON NO. MANDEL MAN NO SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR NO. SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WILSON NO.
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO.
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO. SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I THERE ARE FIVE EYES AND FIVE
NOS SO THE MOTION SO THAT PIECE OF THE MOTION FAILS AND THEN ON
ITEMS ON THE REST OF THE REMAINDER OF THE MOTION
APPROVING ITEM 32 AND TABLING ITEM 33 MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE APPROVE ITEM 32
AND TABLE ITEM 33 SUPERVISOR GENTLEMAN ALL RIGHT.
MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR
SAUDER SORTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN
CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I THERE ARE TEN EYES SO THAT
PART OF THE MOTION PASSES MISTER CITY ATTORNEY DO YOU
WANT US TO TRY TO VOTE ON PREPARING JUST 34 DIRECTING YOU
TO PREPARE FINDINGS DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSSI AS I SAID
BEFORE IT WOULD BE PREFERABLE IF THERE WERE FINDINGS TO
SUPPORT THIS DECISION SOMEONE WOULD LIKE TO MOTION TO
DISAPPROVE. >> ITEM 34 MR. PRESIDENT.
ITEM 34 HAS BEEN OH SO WE'VE ALREADY VOTED ON YOU'D HAVE TO
RESCIND THE VOTE FIRST. >> OKAY.
ALL RIGHT. LET'S DO WE SHOULD WE TRY TO DO
LET'S GO. >> OKAY, WE'RE DONE.
WE'RE DONE. EVERYBODY WANTS TO BE DONE.
OKAY, GREAT. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK LET'S GO
TO WHERE ARE WE PUBLIC COMMENTS .
YES, MR. PRESIDENT. LET'S GO TO WE BECAUSE WE
FINISHED ROLL CALL. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT AS
ALL OTHER MATTERS ON THE AGENDA HAVE ALREADY BEEN DISPOSED OF.
>> PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG
THE CURTAINS YOU ARE ABLE TO SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED ITEMS 39 THROUGH 47 THESE ARE THE ITEMS ON THE
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE CALENDAR OTHER
GENERAL MATTERS AS WELL ARE ELIGIBLE TO BE THE SUBJECT OF
YOUR COMMENTARY. HOWEVER THE PUBLIC HEARING THAT
WE JUST HELD ON THE ITEMS I THINK WE'RE LOOKING AT ITEMS 31
THROUGH 34 ARE NOT ELIGIBLE FOR PUBLIC COMMENT AT THIS TIME.
WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> WELCOME MAGIC. THANK YOU.
I HOPE YOU FIND THIS UPLIFTING AT THE BEGINNING OF EACH
MEETING YOU HAVE STATED THAT WE ARE ON UNCEDED RAMA TO A LONELY
LAND. IT IS TIME TO GIVE WEIGHT TO
THOSE WORDS. >> THE INDIGENOUS PEOPLES ALL
OVER THE WORLD HAVE ALWAYS LOVINGLY HELD MOTHER EARTH AS
THE SOURCE OF LIFE NOT AS PROPERTY.
AS SCIENTISTS NOW KNOW, THE EXTRACTION EXPLOITATION SYSTEM
WILL SOON MAKE OUR BELOVED EARTH UNLIVABLE FOR MANY
SPECIES ARE GOING EXTINCT AT AN UNPRECEDENTED RATE.
THERE IS A SOLUTION AND IT IS ALREADY IN MOTION.
IT'S CALLED THE RIGHTS OF NATURE.
THESE LAWS RECOGNIZE THE RIGHT OF ECOSYSTEMS TO EXIST AND TO
FLOURISH. >> TAMAQUA PENNSYLVANIA IS THE
VERY FIRST PLACE IN THE WORLD TO RECOGNIZE THE RIGHTS OF
NATURE AND CODIFY IT. PENNSYLVANIA WAS WHERE THIS
COLONIZER STATE STARTED. NOW WE START AGAIN AND HONOR
THE ORIGINAL PEOPLE OF THIS LAND.
>> IT IS IN THE CONSTITUTION OF ECUADOR.
SINCE 2006 DOZENS OF COMMUNITIES IN TEN STATES
IN THE U.S. HAVE ENACTED RIGHTS OF NATURE LAWS.
>> OVER 40 COUNTRIES HAVE IMPOSED AROUND 500 RIGHTS OF
NATURE LAWS AT VARIOUS LEVELS. >> I WAS SUCCESSFUL IN GETTING
THESE RIGHTS INTO THE GENERAL PLAN OF SEBASTOPOL AND I'M
OFFERING A TUTORIAL TO PRESENT TO THIS BODY AS WE DID AT THE
PIONEERS TO BEGIN THE PROCESS OF ENACTING THESE RIGHTS HERE
IN THE VISIONARY CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> FOR EXAMPLE, IF A BUSINESS WANTS TO DUMP TOXIC WASTE INTO
THE BAY WE CAN IMPLEMENT THESE LAWS.
IT IS NOT TOO LATE BUT WE MUST ACT NOW.
>> SAN FRANCISCO IS DESTINED TO LEAD THE WORLD AND IT IS TIME
TO TAKE THIS EVOLUTIONARY LEAP. >> ON THE FEDERAL LEVEL THE
MASK OF DEMOCRACY HAS FALLEN OFF THE FACE OF FASCISM.
IT IS NOT TOO LATE IN THE LOCAL LEVEL BUT WE MUST ACT NOW.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS TO
THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> HELLO.
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS E.K. KEITH AND I'M
HERE TO SAY HAPPY POETRY MONTH. COMING UP ON FRIDAY APRIL 24TH
FROM 530 TO 8 IN THE NORTH LIKE COURT IS THE 21ST ANNUAL COMES
UNDER THE DOME WHICH BRINGS POETS FROM ALL OF YOUR
DISTRICTS HERE TO CITY HALL TO SHARE A POEM IN A UNIQUE OPEN
MIC. I STARTED THIS 21 YEARS AGO
WITH OUR ICONIC LATE COMMUNITY ORGANIZER DIAMOND DAVE WHITAKER
AND HE'S NOT WITH US BUT THE POETRY STAYS AND I INVITED ALL
OF YOU AND YOUR STAFFS THIS AFTERNOON I VISITED ALL YOUR
OFFICES AND I HOPE YOU WILL INVITE YOUR CONSTITUENTS TO
COME DOWNSTAIRS AT 530 ON APRIL 24TH AND CELEBRATE POETRY
MONTH. IT SEEMS CLEAR THAT THERE'S A
LOT GOING ON IN DISTRICT THREE RIGHT NOW BUT SOME OF WHAT
DISTRICT THREE IS FAMOUS FOR IS POETRY.
>> BUT WE HAVE POETS IN EVERY SUPERVISORY DISTRICT AND I'VE
BEEN GOING AROUND TO ALL OF OUR POETRY READINGS INVITING YOUR
CONSTITUENTS TO CITY HALL. SO THANK YOU ALSO FOR ALWAYS
SUPPORTING THIS EVENT. >> WE GOT IT STARTED BACK
IN 2006 WITH A UNANIMOUS VOTE FROM THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND A PROCLAMATION FROM THE MAYOR.
THANK YOU ALL. HAPPY POETRY MONTH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI. MY NAME IS RICHARD JOHNSON.
I'M A CO-FOUNDER OF A GROUP CALLED HB SAFE.
ONCE AGAIN I'M SPEAKING ABOUT THE HAYES STREET CLOSURE.
WHAT'S HAPPENING ON HAYES STREET WITH THE CLOSURE IS NO
LONGER JUST A PERMITTING ISSUE. IT'S A QUESTION OF GOVERNANCE
AND POLITICAL OVERREACH. THIS CLOSURE AS OPERATED UNDER
A TEMPORARY PERMIT. AND OVER TIME WE HAVE
DOCUMENTED LACK OF COMPLIANCE, LACK OF ENFORCEMENT AND REAL
IMPACTS TO SMALL BUSINESSES AND RESIDENTS.
INSTEAD OF ADDRESSING THOSE ISSUES, SUPERVISOR MAHMUD IS
ADVANCING A STUDY TO JUSTIFY MAKING THIS CLOSURE PERMANENT.
WHILE THOSE PROBLEMS REMAIN UNRESOLVED.
THIS IS NOT A STUDY INFORMING POLICY.
IT IS POLICY BEING BACKFILLED BY A STUDY.
AT THE SAME TIME MEMBERS OF OUR COMMUNITY WERE SUBJECTED TO A
CIVIL HARASSMENT PETITION SIMPLY FOR DOCUMENTING
CONDITIONS ON A PUBLIC STREET. THAT PETITION BOUGHT BY THE
PERMIT HOLDER COST OVER $50,000 AND WAS DENIED BY THE COURT.
THE COURT MADE CLEAR THIS IS PROTECTED CIVIC ACTIVITY NOT
HARASSMENT BECAUSE WHEN RESIDENTS AND SMALL BUSINESS
BUSINESSES RAISE CONCERNS THEY ARE NOT ENGAGED.
THEY ARE SIDELINED. STAKEHOLDERS IN HAYES VALLEY
HAVE HAVE BEEN EFFECT EFFECTIVELY SHUT OUT OF THIS
PROCESS PROCESS. AND YET THIS CONTINUES TO MOVE
FORWARD AS IF THERE WAS CONSENSUS.
THERE IS NOT THIS APPROACH ADVANCING A PREDETERMINED
OUTCOME WHILE EXCLUDING LARGE PORTIONS OF THE COMMUNITY
REFLECTS THAT FAILURE OF LEADERSHIP.
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD HAS A RESPONSIBILITY TO REPRESENT ALL
CONSTITUENTS NOT JUST A SELECT GROUP ALIGNED WITH A SINGLE
OUTCOME. RIGHT NOW THAT RESPONSIBILITY
IS BEING IGNORED. THANK YOU RICHARD YOU VERY
MUCH. >> THANK YOU, RICHARD JOHNSON
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> SO A LOT THIS EARLY OF SAY COMES IN FUTURE WHO WAS ADAPT
TO GET MALADY PRETRIAL AMONG THE SCHWAB OBSCURE OF SO BUT
WERE SHE DUE DO THIS EURO AND ACTUALLY SEE IN PERMA
ALERTS FROM ADDRESS TO AT
ANY VIDEO YOU CAN SEEN SEE ONLINE THAT ARE SOME MUSIC
BEHIND ITS ITS A I MANIPULATION ARE SUBTITLES OR YOU KNOW
PROVOCATIVE TITLES IN CABINET DON'T WASTE YOUR TIME WATCHING
THIS BECAUSE IS GOING TO BE FOR YOUR ON PROBLEMS COMING UP A
DUE MONSIEUR NO. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER THE
MAYOR AND OTHER BILLIONAIRES ARE ENACTING A CORPORATE COUP
OVER LOCAL GOVERNMENTS. THIS DIDN'T BEGIN WITH THE
MAYOR, BUT YOU SURE SPEEDING UP THE COUP WITH THE VIA THE
CHARTER REFORM WORKING GROUP AND THE COMMISSION STREAMLINING
TASK FORCE IN PARALLEL WITH HIM DEFENDING SOCIAL SERVICES LIKE
HOUSING VOUCHERS, THE SHUTTERING OF HOMELESS SHELTERS
WHILE ALSO CRIMINALIZING HOMELESSNESS, REPLACING
GOVERNMENT WITH A.I. AND OBSCENELY FUNDING SFPD
AND HIS EXTENSIVE DRONE SURVEILLANCE COMMISSION
STREAMLINING SEEKS TO GLUE SHOTS IN THE MOUTHS OF THE
PEOPLE BY REDUCING COMMISSIONS THAT SERVE THE MARGINALIZED
AND OR STRIPPING THEM OF POWER. >> THE COMMISSION WENT SO FAR
AS TO RECOMMEND MOVING MUCH OF THE AUTHORITY OVER POLICE
DISCIPLINE FROM THE POLICE COMMISSION TO THE POLICE CHIEF.
>> THEY SAY IT'S TO BRING THE POLICE DEPARTMENT IN LINE WITH
HOW OTHER DEPARTMENTS DISCIPLINE THEIR EMPLOYEES.
>> BUT DO OTHER DEPARTMENTS ASSAULT PEOPLE AS OFTEN AS SFPD
DOES? ARE THEIR EMPLOYEES MILITARIZED
WITH GUNS AND ARMOR? >> DO OTHER DEPARTMENTS DELAY
RAPE RAPE KIT TESTING LIKE CPD? YOU CANNOT TREAT SPD THE SAME
AS OTHER DEPARTMENTS BECAUSE THE STAKES ARE SO MUCH MORE
PERSONAL, TRAUMATIZING AND DEADLY.
>> THE BILLIONAIRE COUP EXTENDS TO CHARTER REFORM WHERE
CORPORATE INTERESTS ARE VASTLY OVERREPRESENTED.
THE WORKING GROUP HAS REPRESENTATIVES FROM
BILLIONAIRE MICHAEL MORITZ REAL ESTATE GROW SURFER BUNNY S.F.
AND ALSO ADVANCE S.F. WHICH REPRESENTS THE INTERESTS OF
CORPORATIONS LIKE OPENAI, GOOGLE GENIE, VISA GAP
AND WAYMO. THESE TWO PROJECTS WILL
CONSOLIDATE AND TRANSFER POWER POWER AWAY FROM THE PEOPLE
AND INTO THE HANDS OF BILLIONAIRES AND THE
CORPORATIONS. >> THEY DO NOT SEE US AS PEOPLE
. THEY SEE US AS HUMAN CAPITAL TO
BE EXPLOITED UNTIL DEATH WEDGING THEMSELVES BETWEEN US
AND OUR SURVIVAL NEEDS. THEY ARE SHARPENING THE KNIFE
THAT IS BEING PLUNGED INTO OUR BACKS AND OUR HEARTS.
ENGINEERING THE KNIFE SO AT THAT SO THAT LESS MANPOWER WILL
BE NEEDED TO BLOODLESS LEE THRUST THIS KNIFE INTO OUR POOR
TIRED SICK BODIES BLOODLESS LEE BECAUSE WHAT WILL KILL US ARE
THE POLICIES THAT FORCE PEOPLE INTO POVERTY MENTAL INSTABILITY
AND HOMELESSNESS WHILE DEFUNDING AFFORDABLE HOUSING
AND PUBLIC HEALTH. >> JUST LIKE HOW THE MILITARY
CAN KILL MASSES OF PEOPLE FROM AFAR WITH A PUSH OF A STERILE
BUTTON, CITY HALL IS DOING THE SAME VIA POLICIES OF A FEW
SECONDS LEFT. SO WE SHOULD ALSO STOP THE WAR
IN IRAN FREE GAZA, STOP ALL THE GENOCIDE, STOP THE GENOCIDE OF
INDIGENOUS PEOPLE HERE, BLACK PEOPLE HERE THE ONE AGAINST
TRANS PEOPLE THAT IS IN THE MIDST.
>> CAN WE JUST STOP KILLING PEOPLE AND START CARING FOR
THEM? >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. WELCOME.
HELLO SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS NADIR RAMON.
I AM A SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT AND I'M HERE TODAY ON BEHALF OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA CHAPTER OF CARE CALIFORNIA, THE
COUNCIL ON AMERICAN ISLAMIC RELATIONS TO GIVE COMMENT ON
THE RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING AMERICAN MUSLIM APPRECIATION
AND AWARENESS MONTH CARE SFB WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU ALL FOR
RECOGNIZING THIS MONTH AND AN EXTRA SPECIAL THANKS TO
SUPERVISOR BILAL MAHMOOD FOR INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION.
>> LAST YEAR WHEN THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGED THIS
OBSERVANCE FOR THE VERY FIRST TIME I CAME HERE TO GIVE PUBLIC
COMMENT TO TELL YOU ALL ABOUT HOW MUSLIM COMMUNITIES HAVE
FACED RECORD LEVELS OF ISLAMOPHOBIA AND DISCRIMINATION
RECORDED IN OUR CIVIL RIGHTS REPORT LAST YEAR AS THE HIGHEST
NUMBER OF COMPLAINTS IN THE ORGANIZATION'S THREE DECADE
LONG HISTORY. TODAY I RETURN TO YOU AS YOU
RECOGNIZE THIS OBSERVANCE FOR THE SECOND TIME WITH AN UPDATE
FROM CARES 2026 CIVIL RIGHTS REPORT WHICH DOCUMENTED 8683
TOTAL COMPLAINTS NATIONWIDE IN 2025.
>> UNFORTUNATELY SETTING A NEW RECORD WE KNOW WHAT IS DRIVING
THESE COMPLAINTS. >> WE HAVE A FEDERAL
ADMINISTRATION THAT IS OPENLY TARGETING IMMIGRANT AND MUSLIM
COMMUNITIES. >> WE HAVE ELECTED OFFICIALS
ENGAGING IN HATEFUL ANTI-MUSLIM RHETORIC AND PROPAGANDA WITHOUT
CONSEQUENCE. AND JUST THIS MORNING THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES DECLARED HIS INTENT TO COMMIT
GENOCIDE AND USE NUCLEAR WEAPONS AGAINST IRAN.
>> THIS ALL HAS VERY REAL CONSEQUENCES FOR YOUR MUSLIM
CONSTITUENTS WHO ARE RIGHT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
ALL OF THESE THINGS DRIVE ANTI-MUSLIM SENTIMENT AND HATE
RECOGNIZING AMERICAN MUSLIM APPRECIATION AND AWARENESS
MONTH IS A GOOD FIRST STEP. >> AND WE THANK YOU ALL FOR
DOING SO. >> THANK YOU NOT EVEN YOU FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT AND MEMBER OF THE BOARD.
ASSALAMU ALAIKUM. MEANING PEACE BE UPON YOU.
MY NAME IS SHAHIN SHEIKH. I'M HERE TODAY TO STRONG
SUPPORT OF RECOGNIZING APRIL 26TH ALSO MY BIRTHDAY MONTH AS
AN AMERICAN MUSLIM APPRECIATION AND AWARENESS MONTH.
I'M A SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT. I BELIEVE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND HENCE PROUDLY SERVED SAN FRANCISCO FOR PAST 30 YEARS AS
A PUBLIC SERVANT. >> I HAVE RAISED I STARTED MY
CAREER ACTUALLY RIGHT HERE IN THE BASEMENT OF A CITY HALL
AT THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS AND CURRENTLY SERVING AS A
SECURITY OPERATION CENTER INTELLIGENCE OFFICER FOR 70.
>> I'VE RAISED THREE BOYS PROUD TO RAISE ALL THREE OF THEM BORN
HERE AND RAISED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND OVERALL A PROUD AMERICAN MUSLIM.
>> FIRST I WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU FOR YOUR HARD WORK.
>> I SEE THIS BEAUTIFUL BOUQUET SITTING BEFORE ME TODAY AND A
REFLECTION OF DIVERSITY THAT MAKES OUR CITY ABSOLUTELY
VIBRANT. WHETHER IT'S RUNNING INTO OUR
MAYOR AT LARK OR NETA OR SEEING MY OWN DISTRICT SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN WEARING HER ABSOLUTELY BEAUTIFUL RED DRESS
AND CELEBRATING WITH KIDS AT EASTER.
OR SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD BEING DUNKED BY AT EDEN FESTIVAL BY
OUR CHILDREN. >> THESE MOMENTS DEEPLY MATTER
. WE THANK SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR
HIS LEADERSHIP. >> BUT ALL OF YOU ARE THE
REASON THAT HE PUT THIS RESOLUTION ON THE TABLE TODAY.
AND I'M CONFIDENT THAT IT WILL PASS IN FLYING COLORS.
AS A MOTHER AND LONGTIME TEACHER AT SAN FRANCISCO
ISLAMIC SCHOOL SUNDAY SCHOOL, THIS RECOGNITION IS DEEPLY
PERSONAL TO ME. I HAVE SEEN IT ALL FIRSTHAND.
IT SHOWS OUR CHILDREN THAT THEY ARE SEEN, VALUED AND PROUD OF
WHO THEY ARE. >> IT TELLS EVERY YOUNG PERSON
IN SAN FRANCISCO THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
MY APOLOGIES TO INTERRUPT ANYONE THOUGH BECAUSE EVERY TWO
MINUTES WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
THANK YOU. WELCOME.
>> HELLO, EVERYONE. HELLO, BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS MAHMUDIYAH HERE AS A RESIDENT CIVIL SERVANT LABOR
LEADER. I MISS SOMEONE ON THE SURE.
WE ALL MISS YOU, JACKIE. HOPE YOU FEEL BETTER SOON
AND JOIN US. I ALSO GIVE SHOUT OUT THANK YOU
TO ALL THE D9 TEAM AND WE ALL ARE HERE SUPPORTING YOU.
THANK YOU FOR WORKING DAY AND DO NOT I'M HERE IN SUPPORT
OF THE RESOLUTION FOR AMERICA MUSLIM APPRECIATION
AND AWARENESS MONTH. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
FOR LEADING IT. IT MEANS A LOT FOR THE
COMMUNITY AND THE COMMUNITY. ONE OF THE MARGINALIZED
COMMUNITIES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND WE WE SERVE THE CITY.
WE CONTRIBUTE TO THE SUCCESS OF THIS CITY DAY AND NIGHT ON
EVERY LEVEL. SO IT MEANS A LOT FOR THE
COMMUNITIES LIKE US. AND AT THE END I WANT TO REMIND
FOR SOME FOLKS WHO STILL HAVE DOUBT SAN FRANCISCO IS A
SANCTUARY CITY. SAN FRANCISCO IS A UNION TOWN.
TAX THE RICH VOTE YES AND PROBABLY.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU, SIR.
AND JUST FOR NEXT TIME WHEN YOU COME TO THE CHAMBERS, SIR,
MAYBE JUST ADDRESS YOUR COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A
WHOLE. TRY TO STAY AWAY FROM
INDIVIDUAL COMMENTS TO MEMBERS. JUST TELL THE BOARD HOW GREAT
MAHMOOD IS. YEAH, I UNDERSTAND THAT.
JUST LET THE BOARD KNOW THAT YOU APPRECIATE SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO TO ALL THE SUPERVISORS
. FIRST AND FOREMOST WE COME FROM
A SINCERE PLACE OF APPRECIATION FOR EVEN HAVING THIS RESOLUTION
BE TALKED ABOUT. FOR ME PERSONALLY WELL, MY NAME
IS BILL AND YOU KNOW I'M A RIVER TO ISLAM.
AND THIS RESOLUTION ALSO RESONATES WITH ME BECAUSE IT'S
VERY IMPORTANT THAT NOT ONLY FOR US TO LEARN ABOUT OUR OWN
RELIGION OURSELVES BUT ALSO TO HAVE THIS MONTH BE AWARE A
MONTH OF AWARENESS AND UNDERSTANDING FOR PEOPLE
WHO ARE NOT MUSLIM. ALSO LOOKING IN FOR THEM TO GET
AN UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT IT IS THAT WE DO.
THE ROLES THAT WE PLAY IN SOCIETY AND THE WAY THAT WE
HOPE. ME PERSONALLY I WORK FOR THE
CDC AND THE TEAL CBD AND THE 2A1 FAMILY TUNNEL AND FAMILY
HOUSING AND ALSO FOR THE YOUTH SAFETY PILOT SAFETY PILOT
PROGRAM GOING ON. >> AND IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT
NOT ONLY FOR OTHER PEOPLE TO GET AN UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT IT
IS THAT WE BELIEVE IN, WHAT IS THAT WE TALK ABOUT BUT ALSO TO
UNDERSTAND THAT ALL WE WANT TO DO IS BUILD BRIDGES TO EACH
OTHER. WE'RE HERE TO SUPPORT ONE
ANOTHER. WE'RE HERE TO ASSIMILATE INTO
EACH OTHER'S COMMUNITIES BECAUSE AT THE END OF THE DAY
THE WHOLE GOAL IS TO ENRICH OUR CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO, OUR
BELOVED CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO. AND IT ALSO GIVES AN
UNDERSTANDING FOR OTHER RIVERS AS WELL NOT ONLY FOR MUSLIMS,
FOR MAYBE FAMILY MEMBERS THAT ARE REALLY, YOU KNOW, DISTANCE
THEMSELVES FROM PEOPLE THAT COME TO ISLAM OR OTHER THINGS
OF THE SORT. SO WE THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
TAKING. FOR TAKING YOUR TIME TODAY.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR FOR
INITIATING THIS FOR INITIATING THIS RESOLUTION AND WE HOPE
THAT YOU WOULD TAKE IT INTO CONSIDERATION.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NICK SPEAKER, WELCOME TO SIT DOWN.
SIT DOWN. GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR TAKING THE TIME TO SPEAK WITH US
TODAY. MY NAME IS IMRAN.
I AM A THIRD GENERATION SAN FRANCISCO MUSLIM AND A
COMMUNITY ORGANIZER AT A SABEEL MASJID NURUL ISLAM.
>> AND I WANT TO BEGIN BY THANKING THE SUPER ADVISER, OUR
SUPERVISOR BILAL MAHMOOD AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
FOR TAKING THIS OPPORTUNITY TO RECOGNIZE APRIL AS AMERICAN
MUSLIM APPRECIATION AND AWARENESS MONTH.
>> AMERICAN MUSLIMS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN DEEPLY CONNECTED TO SAN
FRANCISCO DURING RAMADAN. >> OUR MOSQUE ACROSS THE CITY
ARE FILLED EVERY NIGHT NOT ONLY WITH SEVEN MUSLIM FAMILIES BUT
WITH MUSLIM PUBLIC SERVANTS, EDUCATORS, DOCTORS, BUSINESS
OWNERS, ENGINEERS, STUDENTS PEOPLE WHO SERVE THE CITY EVERY
DAY. >> BUT BEYOND THAT OUR MOSQUES
HAVE ALSO BECOME A PLACE OF SERVICE ORGANIZING FOOD DRIVE,
SUPPORTING FAMILIES IN NEED AND OPENING OUR DOORS TO
NEIGHBORS FROM ALL BACKGROUNDS .
>> AND FOR US AMERICAN MUSLIMS, THE SERVICE IS NOT SEPARATE
FROM OUR FAITH IN ISLAM SERVING OUR COMMUNITY AND CITY AS PART
OF SERVING OUR GOD AND OUR RELIGION.
>> THE MUSLIM COMMUNITY HAS LONG BEEN A PART OF THIS FABRIC
OF SAN FRANCISCO CONTRIBUTING TO ITS GROWTH AND ITS DIVERSITY
AND ITS STRENGTH. >> AND MOMENTS LIKE THIS TRULY
MATTER BECAUSE NOT ONLY DOES IT BUILD UNDERSTANDING BUT
CONNECTION AND A SENSE OF BELONGING FOR FUTURE
GENERATIONS GROWING UP IN THE CITY WE LOVE THIS CITY AND WE
ARE COMMITTED TO IT. AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO SERVE
IT. AND WE APPRECIATE BEING SEEN,
RECOGNIZED, INCLUDED. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> ASSALAMU ALAIKUM AND GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS AL-JABARI AND I AM A YEMENI MUSLIM COMMUNITY MEMBER.
TOO OFTEN MUSLIMS ARE SPOKEN ABOUT RATHER THAN HEARD FROM
OUR IDENTITIES ARE REDUCED TO MISUNDERSTANDINGS AND TO
MISUNDERSTANDINGS INSTEAD OF BEING RECOGNIZED IN OUR FULL
HUMANITY. >> BUT WE ARE YOUR NEIGHBORS,
YOUR STUDENTS, YOUR COLLEAGUES. WE ARE PART OF THE EVERYDAY
LIFE OF THIS CITY. >> FOR MANY OF US BEING MUSLIM
IS NOT JUST A FAITH BUT A PART OF HOW WE SERVE.
GIVE AND SHOW UP IN OUR COMMUNITY EVERY DAY.
YET OUR STORIES ARE OFTEN ARE OFTEN OVERLOOKED.
>> I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR BILAL MAHMOOD FOR FOR
INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION WHICH RECOGNIZES THE
INVOLVEMENT AND PRESENCE OF MUSLIM-AMERICANS IN OUR CITY.
RECOGNIZING APRIL AS MUSLIM-AMERICAN AWARENESS MONTH
IS NOT JUST SYMBOLIC IT IS A STEP TOWARDS VISIBILITY,
UNDERSTANDING AND DIGNITY. IT ALLOWS PEOPLE TO SEE US NOT
AS STEREOTYPES BUT AS NEIGHBORS MEMBERS AND BUILDERS OF THE
CITY WHOSE PRESENCE MATTERS. >> I'M PROUD TO BE PART OF THIS
COMMUNITY AND I RESPECTFULLY URGE YOU TO SUPPORT THIS
RESOLUTION. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU LA DUBAI FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. FELLOW SUPERVISORS ARE SILVEIRA
FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION.
I'M GOING TO BE SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF MYSELF.
I WANT TO LET YOU ALL KNOW I WANT TO LET THE BOARD KNOW THAT
I THINK SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR THIS EFFORT I FEEL AS IF, YOU
KNOW, THESE CRITICAL TIMES THE FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION IS
TRYING TO DIVIDE OUR COMMUNITIES AND IN WAYS THEY
HAVE SUCCEEDED. AND YOU KNOW, TO REPEL THAT,
THE ANSWER IS SOLIDARITY. AND IN MY FAITH, SOLIDARITY IS
EVERYTHING. >> AND MY FAITH TEACHES THAT IF
THE ARM IS HURT, THE WHOLE BODY IS HURT, THAT IF THE LEG IS
HURT, THE WHOLE BODY IS HURT. AND WHEN ONE MEMBER OF OUR
COMMUNITY IS HURTING, THAT MEANS THAT OUR ENTIRE COMMUNITY
IS HURTING. THAT'S SOMETHING THAT I TAKE
HOME EVERY SINGLE DAY. >> I ALSO WANT TO TAKE THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO, YOU KNOW, APPRECIATE OUR JEWISH BROTHERS
AND SISTERS, OUR CHRISTIAN CATHOLIC BROTHERS AND SISTERS,
OUR HINDU BROTHERS AND SISTERS OF ALL FAITHS BECAUSE SAN
FRANCISCO IS A HOME FOR ALL. AGAIN, THANK YOU TO THIS BOARD
. THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
FOR THIS EFFORT AND I LOOK FORWARD TO DOING MORE IN THE
FUTURE. >> THANK YOU COMMISSIONER ASEEL
FARAH FOR YOUR COMMENTS TODAY. WELCOME SIR.
>> THOSE. >> MY NAME IS RICHARD SD
PETERSON. ONE THING I'D LIKE TO CAUTION
THE BOARD ABOUT IS TO SPEAK LOUDER.
IT SEEMS THAT ALL OF THE PEOPLE WHO SPEAK ON THE PODIUM HERE
ARE QUITE AUDIBLE. BUT SOME OF YOU SUPERVISORS
JUST SEEM TO MUMBLE. AND I DIDN'T REALLY HEAR SOME
OF THE THINGS LIKE WE ALL MISS ONE OF THEIR SUPER SUPERVISORS
FROM DISTRICT NINE. >> BUT I DIDN'T UNDERSTAND WHAT
WAS GRANTED. SOMETHING ABOUT UNTIL THE MAY
MEETING OR IN MAY TOTALLY TOTALLY BLEW ME BY BUT THAT WAS
A VERY IMPORTANT TYPE OF THING BECAUSE THE MISSING SUPERVISOR
FROM DISTRICT NINE COULD HAVE SAVED YOU A LOT OF TIME WHEN
YOU WERE DOING THAT DISCUSSION ON THE SALVAGE OF THE PROPERTY
DOWN IN NORTH BEACH. SHE OBVIOUSLY IS WOULD HAVE
VOTED WITH THE THE GROUP THAT WANTS TO KEEP THAT APARTMENT AT
LEAST ON THE PAPER AS A FOUR UNIT APARTMENT.
I KNOW THAT'S BEING REDUNDANT IT'S ALREADY HASHED OUT BUT
THINK OF THE TIME YOU COULD HAVE SAVED IF THERE THE
REPRESENTATIVE FROM DISTRICT NINE WAS HERE AND UNFORTUNATELY
SHE'S NOT HERE. BUT I DON'T KNOW WHEN SHE'S
GOING TO COME BACK. SO PLEASE SPEAK OUT A LITTLE
LOUDER. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, RICHARD SD PEARSON FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
ALL RIGHT. MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION OF THAT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA PLEASE CALL ITEMS 39 THROUGH 47
ITEM 39 THROUGH 47 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TODAY.
ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO
GO TO COMMITTEE. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD CAN BE
SEVER ITEM NUMBER 40 PLEASE AND I'M 40 WILL BE SEVERED.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON I'D LIKE TO BE ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR TO
ITEMS 40 AND 44 AND I'M SENDING 43 TO COMMITTEE.
>> OKAY. GOT THAT, MADAM CLERK AND A
SUPERVISOR WALTON. WHICH COMMITTEE DID YOU WANT TO
SEND TO COMMITTEE? WHICH ITEM TO COMMITTEE?
443. GOT IT TO COMMITTEE.
OKAY. BUT THEN I NEED TO SEVER IT
FROM THE FROM THE REST OF THEM WITHOUT REFERENCE CALENDAR.
NO, YOU CAN JUST SEND TO THE COMMITTEE.
YEAH. >> YES, MR. PRESIDENT.
OKAY. SUPERVISOR DORSEY 745.
>> OKAY. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
I JUST WANTED TO BE ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR TO ITEM 40 AS WELL.
>> THANK YOU. NOTED.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
SAME THING. >> AS A CO-SPONSOR FOR ITEM 40.
THANKS. >> GREAT.
DID I DELETE ANYBODY BY ACCIDENT?
WE GOOD? ALL RIGHT.
MADAM CLERK SO ON THE REMAINING BALANCE OF THE ITEMS I GUESS
EXCLUDING 4045 AND 43 WHICH HAS BEEN SENT TO COMMITTEE.
>> SO THEN I'M GOING TO GO ITEM 39 4142.
YEP. AND 46 AND FOUR IS IN THERE.
>> AND 46 AND 47 IN ADDITION TO 40 SIX AND 47 PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN. >> I RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SANDRA SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THE MOTIONS ARE APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 40 ITEM 40 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO RECOGNIZE AS THE MONTH OF APRIL 2026 AS AMERICAN-MUSLIM
APPRECIATION AND AWARENESS MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO AND TO CELEBRATE THE MYRIAD CONTRIBUTIONS OF THE
AMERICAN MUSLIM COMMUNITY TO SAN FRANCISCO SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
>> COLLEAGUES, AS A MUSLIM-AMERICAN, I WANT TO
SPEAK ON THIS RESOLUTION FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO RECOGNIZING APRIL 20TH, 26 AS AMERICAN MUSLIM
APPRECIATION AND AWARENESS MONTH ENRICHED BY THE
UNPARALLELED DIVERSITY OF ITS RESIDENTS, SAN FRANCISCO TAKES
GREAT PRIDE IN SUPPORTING INDIVIDUAL RELIGIOUS FREEDOMS
AND IS STRENGTHENED BY THE MANY VERY RELIGIOUS, POLITICAL
AND CULTURAL TRADITIONS AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF ITS
DIVERSE POPULATIONS INCLUDING THOSE THE PRACTICE ISLAM.
CALIFORNIA ALONE IS HOME TO NEARLY 1 MILLION AMERICAN
MUSLIMS. TODAY MILLIONS OF AMERICAN
MUSLIMS BOTH IMMIGRANT AND NATIVE BORN REPRESENT A
WIDE RANGE OF ETHNICITIES, LANGUAGES AND BELIEFS UNITED BY
THEIR SHARED FAITH AND CIVIC ENGAGEMENT.
>> OUR CITY IS HOME TO MUSLIM INSTITUTIONS THAT TEACH VALUES
OF COMPASSION, DIGNITY AND LOVE SUCH AS THE ISLAMIC CENTER OF
SAN FRANCISCO. MASJID ELTAHAWY, DAR ES OR
SABEEL MASJID NURUL AND THE SAN FRANCISCO MUSLIM COMMUNITY
CENTER WHICH ALSO PROVIDE EDUCATIONAL ENRICHMENT SERVICES
PROGRAMS FOR YOUTH AND FOSTER PRINCIPLES OF EQUALITY, JUSTICE
AND PEACE. >> WE KNOW THAT IN THIS CURRENT
CLIMATE OUR DIVERSE COMMUNITIES CONTINUE TO FACE RISING LEVELS
OF HATE AND DISCRIMINATION. IN 2024 THE COUNCIL ON
AMERICAN-ISLAMIC RELATIONS RECEIVED 8658 COMPLAINTS OF
ANTI-MUSLIM BIAS NATIONWIDE THE HIGHEST IN ITS 30 YEAR HISTORY.
>> AN INCREASE FROM THE YEAR PRIOR IS OUR DUTY AS ELECTED
OFFICIALS TO UPLIFT OUR DIVERSE COMMUNITIES, FIGHT AGAINST
DISCRIMINATION, XENOPHOBIA AND HATE AND CONTINUE TO SHOW
THAT WE WILL SUPPORT THE FUNDAMENTAL RIGHT TO PRACTICE
RELIGION FREELY. SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN A
HUB FOR IMMIGRANTS AND REFUGEES AND A BEACON FOR DIVERSITY.
THANK YOU TO ALL THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO CAME OUT TODAY TO
DEMONSTRATE THEIR SUPPORT BY SPEAKING DURING PUBLIC COMMENT
ON THIS IMPORTANT ITEM. AND THANK YOU TO MY COLLEAGUES
FOR YOUR SUPPORT AND CO-SPONSORSHIP AS WELL.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMUD. WITH THAT WE CAN TAKE ITEM 14.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 45. >> ITEM 45.
>> THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT CALIFORNIA STATE
ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 2344 INTRODUCED BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER
MATT HANEY WHICH WOULD ESTABLISH THE CALIFORNIA ANIMAL
ABUSE REGISTRY, STRENGTHEN ANIMAL WELFARE PROTECTIONS
AND PROMOTE PUBLIC SAFETY ACROSS THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM AND COLLEAGUES HERE TODAY ASK YOU TO JOIN ME
IN SUPPORTING THE ASSEMBLY BILL 2344 AUTHORED BY ASSEMBLY
MEMBER MAT HANEY TO ESTABLISH CALIFORNIA'S FIRST STATEWIDE
ANIMAL ABUSE REGISTRY. THIS LEGISLATION WILL EQUIP
SHELTERS, RESCUE ORGANIZATIONS AND LAW ENFORCEMENT WITH A
PRACTICAL TOOL TO IDENTIFY RISK, PREVENT REPEAT HARM
AND MAKE MORE INFORMED PLACEMENT DECISIONS.
THIS LEGISLATION RESPONDS TO A CLEAR AND TROUBLING PATTERN
ANIMAL CRUELTY IS RARELY ISOLATED.
WE SEE IT IN LOCALLY OCCURRING CASES OF NEGLECT AND ABUSE
AND TOO OFTEN WE LACK MECHANISMS TO MAKE
COMPASSIONATE INTERVENTIONS BEFORE HARMS ARE REPEATED.
THE REGISTRY CONTEMPLATED IN THIS LEGISLATION IS A
MEASURED COMMONSENSE APPROACH TO STRENGTHEN ACCOUNTABILITY
AND TO BETTER SUPPORT EARLY INTERVENTIONS IN WAYS THAT
PROTECT ANIMALS FROM NEEDLESS ABUSE.
AS SOMEONE WHOSE OWN FAMILY HAS GROWN OVER THE LAST YEAR TO NOW
INCLUDE TWO YOUNG DOGS BOTH RESCUES ONE A STRAY AND THE
OTHER ABANDONED AS A YOUNG PUPPY ON SIXTH STREET.
I REALLY VALUE THIS APPROACH AND I APPLAUD THIS LEGISLATION.
THE BOND THE PEOPLE HAVE WITH THEIR PETS IS GROUNDED IN LOVE
AND TRUST AND NOWHERE IS THAT BOND MORE NOBLY CELEBRATED THAN
HERE IN THE CITY OF SAINT FRANCIS.
AB 2344 WILL HELP TO ENSURE RESPONSIBLE GUARDIANSHIP BY
KEEPING ANIMALS OUT OF THE HANDS OF THOSE WHO HAVE ALREADY
DEMONSTRATED A WILLINGNESS TO HARM THEM.
I PROUDLY SUPPORT THIS BILL. I'M GRATEFUL TO ASSEMBLY MEMBER
JAMIE FOR HIS LEADERSHIP ON IT AND I RESPECTFULLY ASK
COLLEAGUES TO JOIN ME IN SUPPORTING IT.
THANK YOU SUPERVISED DORSEY. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? I HAVE NO TO REPORT, MR.
PRESIDENT. THEN COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? >> YESTERDAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS.
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THE LATE ANDREA SHORTER.
AND ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN FOR THE LATE BRIXTON
AT LARGE THE GOLDEN RETRIEVER THERAPY DOG.
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE LATE ANDERSON J.B.
WILLIAMS AND ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHAN.
SUPERVISORS CHEN DORSEY AND MANDEL ADELMAN FOR THE LATE
JOHN L BURLING. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA DO WE HAVE
ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> MR. PRESIDENT, OUT OF AN ABUNDANCE OF CAUTION, I JUST
WANT TO MAKE SURE THE NUMBER THE ITEM NUMBER THAT SUPERVISOR
WALTON SENT TO COMMITTEE IS 43. OKAY.
I WANT TO JUST DOUBLE CHECK THAT I DIDN'T HAVE THE BOARD
VOTE ON THAT ITEM. I DID NOT.
OKAY. VERY GOOD.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MEMBERS THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR
TODAY. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
AS THERE IS NO FURTHER BUSINESS, WE ARE ADJOURNED